Afternoon, everyone.
Hope you're good.
It's really a pleasure to welcome you here for
the University of Colorado Boulder's eighth annual three-minute thesis final competition.
I'm Scott Adler, Dean of the Graduate School.
Thrilled to have you join us for really one of my favorite events of the year.
And it's really nice to pull everyone together these days for something fun and positive.
The Graduate School at CU Boulder is home to
nearly 6,000 graduate students across 130 different programs.
And these students are engaged in groundbreaking research, creative work,
and creative work training to become the next
generation of scholars, artists, teachers, and researchers.
from astrophysics to dance.
They're pushing the boundaries of their disciplines and
tackling some of the most complex challenges of our time.
Our students' important work is made possible in part by
the generous support of our donors who fund the fellowships
and grants awarded by the graduate school each year.
So if you saw the slideshow earlier,
You caught a glimpse of some of the outstanding scholarship going on by our graduate students.
Their achievements really do reflect the excellence of the
graduate school and the students that we have here.
And we're deeply grateful to our donors for their
commitment to advancing research and innovation at CU Boulder.
And yet, much of the remarkable research
that our students are doing remains known only to specialists within their given field.
And that's why we do the 3MT competition and why it's so special.
It's more than a showcase of research, it's a testament to the power of effective communication.
Today our finalists
will take on the challenge of distilling complex
ideas into compelling, accessible narratives that engage, inform, and inspire us all.
Now this 3MT journey began last fall when 31 graduate
students embarked on a series of workshops designed to
hone their storytelling, writing, and presentation skills, even
including a session on improv comedy techniques.
And after months of hard work and making it past
the preliminary round of the competition, we now have 10 exceptional finalists.
Your program says 11, one got sick.
And these finalists are ready to present their research in just three minutes.
So to our participants, congratulations on making it this far.
Your dedication, creativity, public speaking, and communication skills
are already a testament to your excellence.
To our esteemed judges, thank you for your time and expertise in evaluating these presentations.
And to our audience, students, faculty, staff, family,
friends, and community members, your support is what makes this event so special.
So let's celebrate the power of knowledge, the courage
of discovery and the joy of learning together.
Without further ado, let's begin the 2025 three minute thesis final competition.
So it's my pleasure to introduce our emcee for today.
My dear friend, Bud Coleman, Professor Emeritus and the
inaugural holder of the Roe Green Endowed Chair in Theater
and former chair of the Department of Theater and Dance and
former Associate Dean of Faculty Affairs in the College of Arts and Sciences, Bud Coleman.
We are thrilled to have you here in support of our
graduate students as they rise to the challenge of presenting their research in just three minutes.
Your presence, both here in person and via the
live stream, demonstrates incredible support for CU's Boulder community of scholars.
The three minute
Competition, or known as 3MT, started at the University of
Queensland in 2008 and has since grown into an international
phenomenon hosted by over 900 universities in 85 countries.
3MT cultivates students' research communication skills, pushing them
to distill complex ideas into compelling narratives for a general audience.
To put this challenge into perspective, the average dissertation is around 80,000 words.
It would take approximately 9 to 12 hours to read it.
These students have distilled very complex ideas into three minutes.
No pressure, right?
As Scott mentioned, this year marks the eighth year that
CU Boulder has participated in 3MT, and today's winners
not only receive recognition, but also cash awards.
First place receives $1,500 and will go on to represent
CU Boulder at the Western Association of Graduate Schools competition,
which will be held in March of this year.
The runner-up will take home $750, and the People's
Choice Award winner, chosen by you, will receive $500.
Now, the competition's rules for today's presentations are very simple.
A single static PowerPoint slide is allowed.
No animations or transitions.
Presentations must be spoken word.
No rap, no poems, no singing.
No props, no sound effects or video files.
Just the speaker, their slide, and their ability to engage us.
Each presentation cannot be longer than three minutes.
Exceeding the time limit will result in disqualification.
we extend our sincere gratitude to the 10 graduate students competing today.
By stepping onto this stage, they have embraced the
challenge of sharing their research to the public.
A heartfelt thanks also goes to our esteemed panel
of judges who will evaluate today's presentations on
four key factors, comprehension, content, engagement, and communication.
We'll start with Walid Abdulladi, Executive Director of
the Cooperative Institute for Research in Environmental Studies and also Professor of Geography.
Thank you, Walid.
Next, we have Jared Bahir-Brauch, Director of Critical
Sports Studies and Assistant Teaching Professor in Ethnic Studies.
Thank you, Jared.
Sonia De Luca Fernandez, Senior Vice Chancellor for Leadership, Engagement and Support.
Thank you, Sonia.
And Robert Streeter, Site Supervisor at Polar Field Services.
Now, Robert is also a graduate of the CU Boulder
Graduate School and the winner of the 3MT competition in 2023.
Thank you, Robert.
While our judges will determine the first place winner
and the runner-up, you will decide the People's Choice Award winner.
As you watch today's presentations, consider which speaker
captures your imagination, makes their research accessible, and sparks your curiosity to learn more.
After the final speaker today, a QR code will be placed
on the screen where you can cast your vote.
At its core, 3MT is about storytelling, about sharing
new ideas, discoveries, and perspectives in a way that resonates with us all.
On this chilly day, we gather around the proverbial fire
to listen, learn, and be inspired by our next exciting generation of scholars.
Now, let's get started.
The presentation order has been already randomly assigned, so
first up, I'd like to invite Casey Hunt, PhD candidate at the Atlas Institute.
The title of their presentation is Building a Shared
Future, a Toolkit for Collaborative Robot Design.
Robots are the future.
They make work safer, reduce the cost of goods, and
support exploration into deep oceans and outer space.
And that's just a few of the things that they can do.
But what will our robot future look like?
Will it be user friendly and community focused?
That depends on who builds it.
To create a future filled with safe and relevant
robots, engineers must collaborate with the stakeholders of our designs.
Valuing stakeholder knowledge leads to robots that are
more trustworthy and require less fine-tuning, saving resources, and increasing adoption.
For example, a medical robot is more likely to
reflect the realities of hospitals if engineers prioritize
the perspectives of doctors, nurses, and patient advocates.
During my PhD, I've helped facilitate stakeholder-driven robot design.
What I learned is that these processes are invaluable, but they can be complicated.
One challenge is that when we imagine robots with stakeholders,
we have to use techniques that are accessible to everyone, like crafting and brainstorming.
We learn a lot from these exercises, but their simplicity can be limiting.
For instance, it's pretty hard to build a detailed
robot prototype with pipe cleaners, so even valuable outcomes can be limiting and vague.
My research asks, is it possible to design a
technique that leads to more fruitful collaborations with robot stakeholders?
And could this technique be inexpensive and easily remixed
to the many contexts where robots solve important problems?
To explore this question, I use a research
through design approach, surveying literature from robotics
education and design, interviewing experts, and creating hundreds of prototypes with my collaborators.
The result is a promising solution, a kit of 3D
printed joints and connectors that when combined with PVC
pipe, facilitate approachable and playful robot prototyping.
The kit is educational, teaching non-engineers about robots
as they create, while giving engineers the tools to convey precise technical ideas.
In testing, the kit has been transformative, supporting
stakeholders to create detailed prototypes of their ideas,
reducing ambiguity and fostering mutual understanding.
As a result, collaborations using the kit
give engineers clear foundations that they can build on.
Next, I'll explore the wide range of contexts the
kit could be used with elderly adults, firefighters, and children.
Although it sounds simple, this kit is a carefully
engineered solution to one of robotics most persistent challenges,
how to ensure all stakeholders have a voice.
By supporting engineers to create robots that align with
people's needs and values, I helped create a future that we can all be excited about.
Thank you.
As you heard from Dean Adler, CU Boulder is home
to nearly 6,000 graduate students, spread over 130 different programs.
As our judges need time to evaluate the presenters,
I'll be asking these incredible students some questions about what
they do when they're not doing their research.
So Casey, I understand that you like to go camping and hiking.
Where are your go-to spots for camping and hiking?
Yeah, well my family is from the San Luis Valley and
so we love to go camp in southern Colorado and one of the
places we like to camp is at Valley View Hot Springs.
So we'll go camp on the side of the mountain and we take a dip in the springs.
It's super awesome, yeah.
That sounds fantastic.
Yes, hot spring sounds really good on a day like today.
Like many people in this room, our graduate students are under a lot of stress.
And food and the idea of food can be very comforting.
Now Casey, I understand that one of your go-to foods is a tomato sandwich.
So can you give us your recipe for that perfect tomato sandwich?
Yeah, it's like the perfect late night snack.
It's toast with a little bit of mayonnaise.
You put some really good sliced tomato and then salt
and pepper and then obviously the second piece of bread.
It's so good.
You're going to hear a lot about food today.
There is a reception after all the presentations, so we're
not just tempting you and then saying, no food.
You will get food.
Unfortunately, no tomato sandwiches, but they'll be good stuff.
Now, some of us are very lucky to have inspiration to give focus and meaning to our work.
Would you please tell us about your great aunt?
Yeah, so when I first got interested in doing the PhD,
my grandma would not stop talking about my great Aunt Eva.
So Aunt Eva is the only person I share DNA with who
has gotten a PhD, and she helps teach English as a second language speakers in the San Luis Valley English.
So she developed new techniques for doing this, and
she was specifically focused on Spanish speakers because
there's a significant population of Spanish speakers in that area.
Great.
Thank you, Casey.
Thank you so much.
Thank you.
Our next presenter is Anna Turner, PhD candidate in media studies.
The title of their presentation is Building Bridges Through Popular Media.
How many of you have been to show on Netflix or any streaming service?
What if I told you that by watching television, you could actually be helping the United States?
I know, right?
I'm going to show you how.
But first, I'd like to tell you a story.
This is a story of two different people.
They actually have a lot in common, but they don't know it.
You would think that they should get along, but they have one big difference.
The first person is a member of team A, and the second
person is a member of the rival team, team B. So how do
we get the first person and the second person to get along?
This is where my research comes in.
Team A is actually the Democrats and Team B is the Republicans.
They have very different views on certain things and
they dislike each other because they're members of opposite teams.
This is a problem known as polarization.
One of the issues with polarization is that we're not
often exposed to other viewpoints or to people unlike ourselves.
The Republicans, for example, tend to be white living
in rural areas, whereas many Democrats are people of color
or members of the LGBTQ plus community living in urban areas.
And while there are exceptions to these generalizations, the fact
is that many of us on opposite sides of the political spectrum don't often interact.
The one place that we can interact with
people from different geographic locations, socioeconomic statuses, and
a number of other characteristics is through media.
but not news media.
The news polarizes us more.
But popular culture, like television, doesn't have the same baggage.
For my research design, I've run an experiment to
see whether exposure to people unlike ourselves can give us an experience that unites us.
Participants in my research watched a short clip of a
political drama on Netflix and then took a survey to measure their levels of polarization.
While the findings are not yet confirmed, I'm hoping
to show that diverse characters and dialogue can depolarize.
The key here is that networks and streaming services
must begin to consciously craft messages to allow for this exposure.
Similar to how media companies hire diversity officers,
they could also employ experts in political polarization and popular culture, like me,
to consult on diverse characters and dialogue that represent both sides of the aisle.
This is a slow and ongoing process, but if we can
get media companies on board, we could see bridges being built
through television and a more united Team A and Team B. Thank you.
So I understand that you're a runner.
What are some of your favorite trails or routes?
Oh, I am usually a treadmill runner because I am terrified of ice.
I'm terrified of ice and snow.
But the amazing thing about Boulder is all of the bike and running tasks.
So I can pick a different one every time I go in the summer when it's not snowing and slippery.
That was going to be my next question.
What temperature is your cutoff spot?
I'm from Florida, so probably like 60, 70 degrees really, like in the summer.
I'm with you.
I'm from Texas.
So we found out that Casey enjoys a good tomato sandwich.
I hear that you go with mac and cheese.
So any particular brand or recipe?
I really like Gouda in my mac and cheese but the best
thing about mac and cheese is that there are a million
different cheeses and you can make it different every time.
So that's why I like it so much and because cheese.
And we're going to hear more about cheese later too, so it's a thread.
So some people collect baseball cards, some people collect Disney characters.
I understand that you collect dogs.
Pugs, in particular.
Yeah, I collect pugs.
Not like figurines, like actual dog, pug dogs.
So I've had up to three at one time.
I fostered for the Florida Pug Rescue.
And I'm only down to one now, but he's 15 and he's still kicking and he is such a good boy.
So right now I'm only at one, but I have been known to have a grumble actually.
The collective noun for pugs is a grumble, so I used to have a grumble.
These things that you never would have known if you hadn't come today.
So what's the name of your pug?
So did you practice your 3MT presentation to her me?
Oh, he knows it like that.
So if we see a pug walking around talking about media, it's yours.
Yeah, mine.
So I understand you also like to binge watch.
What's the most recent binge?
I have been on this cop show kick, I guess, and firefighting kick.
So I'm watching Station 19 and The Rookie right now, both on Hulu.
Do you recommend them?
Yeah, I actually like both of them a lot, in fact.
SWOT is also actually a really good one, and it's one
I'd like to research later because they do a good job of showing both sides of opinions.
Very good.
Well, thank you so much, Anna.
Thank you, bud.
As you heard, unfortunately, one of our presenters today is
ill, so Heiko will not be presenting for us today.
But next, we do have Celeste Giles, PhD candidate in aerospace engineering.
The title of their presentation today is Bringing You Safely Home from Outer Space.
Imagine you're coming home after a luxurious sightseeing vacation on the moon.
As your spacecraft begins to enter Earth's atmosphere, you
start to hear strange noises, feel vibrations, and see pieces
of spacecraft fly by outside your tiny window.
Will you make it safely back to Earth?
My research is on entry vehicle heat shields, the
protective layer critical in ensuring your spacecraft survives that
high-speed entry as you get pulled by gravity back down to
Earth and that you stay nice and cool the entire time.
These heat shields have been used for over 70 years.
However, much is still not known about them.
As we continue to explore space and build heat shields,
it has been discovered that there are differences between the predictive models and actual flight data.
This is very concerning.
These heat shields need to reliably protect people from
the very hot plasma formed around the spacecraft as it
enters an atmosphere and make sure the spacecraft doesn't completely burn up.
So, how does my research come in?
I get to test heating up small pieces of heat shield
to 10 times the temperature of boiling water, see how they decompose, and what they decompose into.
Similar to wood, when it burns, these heat shields blacken and char when they're heated.
After testing many different heating scenarios, I measure
each sample's mass loss, density, and decomposition products.
My favorite part is I can even reconstruct the
actual chemical mechanisms involved in the decomposition of these heat shields.
After testing multiple different types of heat shields, I
discovered that the density of the heat shield matters a lot.
Similar to wood when it burns, these heat shields produce gases when they are heated.
If the heat shield is too dense, these gases build up
inside causing bubbles and cracks to form in the heat shield.
This is not good for an actual heat shield.
These bubbles and cracks can harm the structural integrity, cause
pieces to fly off, or cause the heat shield to completely fall apart.
Also, the very hot gases formed around the heat shield
can make its way through these cracks, closer to the spacecraft and people inside.
To improve,
Our understanding of the decomposition of these heat shields, I
share my data on the gas products and chemical mechanisms with the scientific community.
To improve the models involved with these heat shields, I
share my data with modelers who then improve their models,
making sure you can reliably and safely land after your moon vacation.
Or if you're super adventurous, help you visit Mars.
Thank you.
So we have to get this out of the way first, especially given the weather.
Please tell people where your hometown is.
I grew up in Honolulu, Hawaii.
I'm not used to the cold.
Can we all just be a teeny bit jealous?
OK.
What would be the temperature approximately in Honolulu right now?
Average is always nice 80.
I right now I can't even imagine 80 so I'm my gosh up like many of us
where we grow up affects the foods that we come to
love and I understand that your favorite is chicken katsu curry
and please tell us what's in chicken katsu curry chicken katsu
breaded deep-fried chicken, and the curry is a Japanese golden curry, very basic, but delicious.
And served with?
Some rice.
There we go.
Have to have the whole package there.
So we already talked about some collections.
Anna has Pugs, and you have a?
collections.
What kind of rocks do you collect?
Oh, all sorts.
It started with my great uncle who was a geologist for
the Bank of America and I inherited some of his collections and then added from there.
So do you have a favorite?
No, they're all precious.
Okay, do you have a favorite collection story?
Let's see, a good one is we used to collect agates from the West Coast beach.
They're like clear rocks you can look up in the sun and see through and they're very pretty.
Fabulous, love that.
I understand that you practice kendo.
Would you please tell folks who don't know what kendo is first?
Kendo is a Japanese stored martial art I started last semester here at CU actually.
Oh my goodness.
So beware, you know, out in the hallway.
So I understand you have two cats?
I do.
They've been helping me through grad school.
And have you practiced your presentation to them?
I have.
They just stare at me in disdain.
So does one like outer space more than the other one?
I believe my fluffy cat named Lily might like outer space more.
So we have Lily and... Noodle.
Noodle.
Are they siblings?
No, they're just rescue mama cats.
Fabulous, fabulous.
Thank you all very much.
Thank you.
Next up, we have Casey Middleton, PhD candidate in computer science.
The title of their presentation is Testing.
Testing.
One, two, three.
It's two days before grandma's birthday and you haven't seen her in ages.
But you're starting to feel a little sniffle coming on
and you really don't want to get grandma sick.
Luckily, you have a few COVID-19 rapid tests in your cabinet.
When should you use them?
Maybe you take one now so you can tell grandma your plans.
But what if it's negative?
Do you take another one?
When?
We know that even if you do have COVID-19, a test isn't guaranteed to detect you.
Rapid tests require us to have lots of virus in our system.
Too little virus and you'll test negative even if you really are sick.
And in fact, the amount of virus you have changes throughout your course of infection.
A typical infection might look something like this.
At that first inhale of virus, only a few virus particles
take root in the lungs, but that number grows super quickly as the virus replicates in the first few days.
Eventually, your immune system kicks in and starts to reduce the amount of virus.
If we knew when your symptoms started during this course
of infection, maybe we could tell you if you have enough virus to test positive.
This is the idea that sparked my research question.
can we predict the effectiveness of different testing
recommendations, considering what we know about how the virus behaves during an infection?
But we know that not everyone's infection looks exactly the same.
So first, I needed data from lots of infections.
To get this data, I dove into the literature, collecting
data from as many studies as I could find, focusing on three key ingredients.
One, how much virus do people typically have throughout their infection?
Two, when do their symptoms typically start?
And three, how much virus does our tests need to detect you?
Now I had a ton of data, but I still needed
some way to synthesize that data to answer my question.
To do this, I created a rigorous mathematical
framework combining probability theory and calculus to help us predict testing effectiveness.
Now, I find multivariable calculus really exciting.
But sadly, we don't have time for a whiteboarding session today.
But I can tell you what I found.
For any virus, it's typically best to test right before
you visit grandma, because a negative test today doesn't guarantee that you won't infect her tomorrow.
And I also found a surprising result for COVID-19.
If you only have a few rapid tests in your cabinet,
you should wait two days after your symptoms start to use them.
This is because our immune systems are primed and ready for COVID-19.
So symptoms start early, even when you haven't built up much virus yet.
And our lessons don't stop at COVID.
The beauty of the math is that it can help us
make better testing choices for other viruses, too, from flu
to RSV to even new viruses we haven't discovered yet.
The math I developed can help us make better testing choices for any virus.
And I like to think this helps us do a
better job protecting grandmas and three-minute thesis participants everywhere.
Thank you.
Thank you, Casey.
So I understand that your path to becoming a computer scientist has been anything but linear.
Indeed.
Would you share with us some of the jobs that you've had before you arrived in Boulder?
Yes.
I was a certified pharmacy technician.
I have been a Zumba instructor.
I've been a data scientist for a housing policy nonprofit,
and I've also been a high school geometry teacher.
Yeah.
So how long were you a high school teacher?
I was a high school teacher for one year.
It was the hardest job I've ever had.
I think we can all agree on that.
Yeah, mad respect.
So do you have a story take away from that experience?
I guess from being a high school teacher, it taught me a lot about empathy
and how you never know what people are going through
because I was trying to teach my kids geometry and they had
so many problems that were not just my geometry homework.
You had nothing to do with your geometry.
Yeah, they actually really didn't care.
There's that.
So you also have a very eclectic palette of sports that you participate in.
It's boulder.
It is boulder.
But even for boulder, this is pretty good.
Rock climbing, trail running, downhill, and backcountry skiing.
Got to do both.
So, do you have any favorite trails or?
Oh yeah, I will say that for hiking I really love
Royal Arch and it's so incredible that that's just right in our backyard.
But this summer I was training for a trail marathon and
I went to Golden Gate State Canyon when the leaves were just
at peak changing and it was so beautiful and that was really fun and hard.
And hard, yes.
So we've heard about tomato sandwiches, mac and cheese.
I don't remember what I put for this question, bud.
Oh, that sounds right, okay.
I have to remind her of her favorite food.
What is her favorite food?
Well, according to your paper, Bud, it is
homemade buttermilk biscuits with strawberry jelly because I'm from
Tennessee and that has to be my answer legally.
Yeah, and if your stomach is not growling by now, I don't know what is in store.
But like I said, we will have food later.
Thank you.
Thank you, Bud.
Next up, we have Nandi Pointer, PhD candidate in media studies.
The title of their presentation is Exit to Entry,
Black Expatriates Teaching English as a Fugitive Liberatory Practice.
Quote, when I'm in America, I'm black.
When I'm abroad, I'm American.
This comment by Troy Benson, a black English teacher from Wisconsin who lives
and works in Iraq, affected me deeply because it cuts at
the heart of a long history of black death and suffering in the U.S.
that dates back to the transatlantic slave trade.
From lynching photographs to cell phone videos of murder, this
history can be traced in the visual field, which has
made the state violence that black people experience hyper visible.
Reflecting on this history, Troy further told me, quote, I wish
there was a country I could go to where I could be invisible.
In America, we don't have that option, end quote.
My dissertation, Exit to Entry, investigates the largely
unstudied phenomenon of black men who leave the U.S.
to work as English as a second language or ESL instructors in Asia and the Middle East.
Focusing specifically on black expats in Iraq, Vietnam, and the Republic of Korea,
I seek to understand how and why these men have taken
the path of teaching abroad as a fugitive practice of liberation.
Drawing on my own personal experience as an ESL
instructor, my dissertation is based on interviews with 20 black male expats.
Multimodal and innovative in nature, it incorporates writing and documentary filmmaking
as a method to tackle questions about race and identity, moving beyond the persisting
and indeed harmful categories of classification, separation,
and representation that have violently marked the black body in the US.
Three primary questions motivate my dissertation project.
One.
How do black male expats re-articulate their identity, sense
of place and agency when located in context free of
the violent ruptures of anti-blackness found in the US?
Two, how does the context of education as an important historical vehicle
for the movement and liberation of the black mind
and body animate black teaching practices overseas?
And three, how do these expats navigate or potentially
experience other structures of racism when located in context shaped by US wars and empire?
In conclusion, I seek to better understand how these
ESL teachers open up new horizons for thinking about black
male identity and racial justice in the US today.
embracing life abroad as a way to free the black body
from what they perceive to be its limited expression and proximity to violence in the U.S.
Thank you.
So, Nandi, as you mentioned in your presentation, she was
a ESL, English as a Second Language instructor.
Where did you do this?
I taught English in the Republic of Korea, Vietnam, and Saudi Arabia.
And how did that come to be?
Well, I was actually inspired by my brother who was on one of the slides.
He taught in Japan and then in Korea.
And after working at MTV in New York, he was like,
what do you think about living overseas for a year?
And I was like,
where am I gonna get my hair done?
How am I gonna do that?
But yeah, life changing experience.
And so do you have a takeaway story from that experience?
From Korea?
Or Vietnam?
I have a funny one from Vietnam which is actually be
careful because I was staying in this little apartment and I went out on the balcony.
I had a little bitty balcony out in front of my little
place and I went all of a sudden like I closed the doors and I heard the little lock like go down.
And I guess the cleaning lady had locked it.
I always just kept it locked.
So me and my brother are out on the balcony.
And I'm like, three stories up.
How am I going to get back inside?
And he's starting to get tense.
And I'm like, I don't know.
I don't know what to yell out in Vietnamese.
It's like, help, or you know.
Luckily, I was able to get down and slap.
up and, you know, get back inside.
Yeah, clearly y'all got back inside.
Yeah, we got back inside.
It would have been a sadder story though.
Oh, that wouldn't help.
Not good.
So I understand you have a dog, Ginger.
Yes, Ginger.
So did you practice your 3MT presentation to Ginger?
I did.
Actually, last night, when I was trying to do it, I guess
her water bowl was a little low, and she gave me this aggressive bark.
And I was like, what?
You don't like my presentation?
She wanted some water.
It was OK.
We never know.
So I understand you also play a musical instrument.
Yes, I play the flute.
And when did that start?
That started in the fifth grade when I was living in Decorah, Iowa.
We could take like little 30 minute lessons and part of our school day, like pretty amazing.
So yeah, that's when I first started playing.
Do you still play?
Yes, I do.
Oh, how exciting.
I just performed at the Cause Black History Month event with my brother and we played.
Fantastic.
Oh my gosh.
Yeah.
So many of the candidates wrote a fun fact about their
life and I have to admit my inner fangirl kind of went into hyperdrive when I read that you are the niece of
The Pointer Sisters.
And so, for anybody who maybe grew up under a rock, who were the Pointer Sisters?
Well, there's a legendary group during the 70s and 80s.
They actually won one of the first country Grammys for a
fairy tale written by my aunt Anita, May She Rest In Peace.
And so, yeah, it was pretty fun having them as
these pioneering black women with these amazing voices growing up.
Amazing voices.
Yeah, the harmonies.
Yeah, and I had to, of course, do a little research of
my own, not only winning the Grammy in the country category,
but they were the first female group to perform in the Grand Ole Opry.
So trailblazers, as well as being brilliant musicians.
Yes, very proud.
Thank you.
Thank you so much.
Next up, we have Marwa Yakuchi, PhD candidate in aerospace engineering.
The title of their presentation is Unveiling the Hidden Stories of Materials.
What does training an Olympic athlete have in common with sending materials to space?
Picture this, you are training an Olympic athlete for the competition of their life.
You analyze everything, the athlete's weaknesses and strengths to ensure a peak performance.
Imagine if you can foresee the challenges this athlete would
face before they even step onto the field.
You'd know how their body would react to each hill, rough terrain, and blazing sun.
Now, think about applying that kind of foresight to the materials that build our world.
Like athletes, materials have their own challenges, especially
in the space environment, from extreme temperatures to radiation.
What if I told you that we could predict
how materials respond under those extreme conditions before they are even created?
That is exactly what I'm working on.
My research asks, how can we use AI to design materials capable of thriving in space?
Think of it as mapping the story of the material
before it's created, ensuring every challenge it faces is accounted for before it ever leaves the lab.
Spacecraft heat shields, for example, inter-temperatures nearly have
as hot as this one, protecting astronauts and equipment.
While we have heat-resistant materials, we need ones that
are lighter, reusable, and faster to produce.
The challenge is finding the right material combination.
So to do this,
I've developed computational models, mathematical tools that
combine physics with artificial intelligence.
First, I gather data on material properties like strength and heat resistance.
Then I use AI to uncover patterns within that data.
So instead of spending months physically testing thousands
of material combinations, AI helps us identify the most promising candidates in minutes.
But here is the twist.
AI doesn't replace physical testing.
It guides us to smarter choices faster.
We take AI's predictions to the lab, refining materials to meet the required standards.
What once took months of trial and error can now begin with AI-powered guidance.
One of the most surprising things I've found throughout
this journey is that, like people, materials have hidden stories.
They respond differently under pressure sometimes and in unexpected ways.
And machine learning helps me uncover these stories, teach us
lessons that could one day lead to breakthroughs in material design.
So next time you watch an Olympic athlete deliver a flawless performance, remember,
behind that success is careful preparation and foresight, just
like the work we do to ensure materials not just survive in space, but thrive.
Thank you.
Thank you, Marwa.
To give yourself a break from your rigorous graduate
studies, I understand that you enjoy reading of horror novels.
Yes, I do.
So any titles or authors that you recommend?
Oh, that's a tough question.
It definitely should be a Stephen King book.
I recommend The Pet Sematary.
I like that one.
I assume you've read this multiple times, it sounds like.
Yeah, I love it.
So I understand you like reading horror novels but not watching horror movies.
Exactly.
There is a movie for the bit symmetry act.
I've never watched it.
I don't know.
I can't handle that.
Just the jump scares and everything in a horror movie.
No.
That's enough for me.
Your own imagination is enough.
That's more manageable.
Right.
We have control over that.
Now, I know people in aerospace engineering have a lot
of different interests, but I think the fact that you're a painter makes you unique in my book.
What do you enjoy painting?
Oh, like there are two types.
I like basically drawing portraits and also natural sceneries.
Yeah, I mean, I just like, all the time looking for sunset pictures.
I just like throwing that, yeah.
I feel like that's kind of my way to get away from research.
So that's very like soothing and calming.
I think your coping skills are... I'm going to take notes.
As a native of Morocco, you note that one of your favorite Moroccan dishes is chicken pastilla.
Could you please explain what that is?
So it is made of chicken with some Moroccan spices.
It has cinnamon and with the crispy phyllo dough.
It is like a mixture of sweet and salty.
I don't know if anyone here has ever visited Morocco.
Oh, there are a few people.
OK, that's amazing.
If you ever have the chance to go to Morocco, I really recommend trying Moroccan pastillas.
They're delicious.
Do you make chicken pastillas?
No.
So we don't ordinarily do product placements, but have
you found any good Moroccan food in Boulder, Denver?
Unfortunately, no.
I'm still looking.
If any Moroccan is interested in opening a Moroccan restaurant,
I guess that would be great, like business.
Thank you, Marwa.
Oh, thank you.
Next up, we have Anna Deese, PhD candidate in Educational Foundations, Policy and Practice.
The title of their presentation is, When Students and
School Voters Differ, The Promise and Peril of Local Control.
Hi, everyone.
My name is Anna, and I study the local democratic control of American schools.
Local control means that resident citizens of an area can
vote on things like increasing taxes to support their
schools, or electing school board representatives who can create and oversee district policies.
Most of the time, local control is a good thing for both education and democracy.
But it can be problematic, and a really awful example
out of East Ramapo, New York is what inspired my research.
There, the local schools served mostly black and Latino
students, but the elected school board was dominated by
white officials whose own children attended private religious schools.
These white officials regularly enacted policies that hurt the education of the students of color,
all so that the white community could save money on
taxes and direct those savings back to the private schools.
What's worse is the legal voter suppression techniques were
used to prevent candidates of color from earning seats on the school board to reverse those policies.
This is a story not from the 1950s,
but within the last decade.
The goal of my research is to identify school
districts where local control might be harming students in racialized ways.
If these districts can be identified, then protections within
the Voting Rights Act could be used to help fix things.
To do this,
To find my problematic districts, I first do a very
technical squishing of lots of maps and demographic data in
order to calculate what I call the representation index.
My index is a measure of how different the race and
ethnicity of the eligible voters in an area are from the
race and ethnicity of the students using the schools.
Districts with large differences, districts like those up
there in red, districts like East Ramapo,
are places where local advocates might wanna step up
their monitoring or where the Voting Rights Act could be used to fix harms.
Of course, it would be way better if no harm came to students in the first place.
So in addition to calculating my index, I add in a
variety of other measures that are related to education
policies that previous research suggests might have a racialized impact.
This way, local decision makers can use my index,
those measures, and their knowledge of what's happening on
the ground to make more equity-oriented decisions.
Local control can be a good thing, but hasn't served communities of color well.
I want to fix that.
Thank you.
Hi, Bud.
So before coming to CU Boulder,
Anna had a lot of very different types of jobs.
Would you tell us about some of those?
I can see my cohort here from the School of Ed
all laughing because they are well aware of how weird my background is.
So I was a corporate consultant.
I was in the military.
I've been a teacher in both inner city and in rural settings.
I've been an elected school board member.
I don't know what else I have on there.
You have a licensure.
Oh, I have my principal's licensure.
Yeah, yeah.
I have a lot of things.
So do you have a story from your experience teaching in Oregon and Chicago?
Um, I mean, there's lots of, there are lots of stories.
I guess one of my favorites was I taught anatomy and
physiology and I always wanted to start by having, um,
My students do a dissection right away.
And we didn't have a lot of money.
Schools need more money, y'all.
Vote for those things.
So I bought the cheapest things I could, which were these sharks.
And they were messed up when they were putting in all the
stuff to preserve them.
And so, like, you just, like, find random blobs of, like, whatever dye they were using.
And my kids thought it was great, so I had them write up practice, like, forensic files and stuff.
But, yeah, it was really weird, but it was better than the pickles we did the year before.
So.
Messed up sharks to pickles.
Yeah.
Only in public school.
Yes.
So it sounds like your experience as an elected school
board member in Montana was kind of a direct path to your dissertation research.
Definitely.
Because you realize when you're an elected member, you do
have so much control, so much power, so much potential.
But also in a lot of ways, you don't.
And you're really shaped by so many other things.
And so that's been a question that's been going through my mind for the last many years.
Sorry to my advisors.
Getting out of here soon, though.
No, no, no, no dates, no dates.
Like Marwa, you enjoy reading as an escape.
I do.
What types of books do you read?
I read really, like, junky crime novels, like the ones
that you will buy at the airport, and you're like, why are there 15 books by this person right here?
Like, this can't be that good.
But I will go through them like nothing else.
So do you have any titles or authors you'd recommend?
No, because that would be embarrassing.
No.
No one's taking any notes.
And yeah, we're safe.
You can come look at my Libby later on while we're eating.
That's it.
So in addition to your work at CU as a graduate student, you're also a mom.
Yes.
So did you practice your 3MT presentation to your son?
He does.
Did I practice my speech to you?
Yes.
So, Des, did you have any recommendations for your mom?
Good answer.
Thank you, Anna.
Thank you so much.
Next up, we have Hunter Ray, PhD candidate in aerospace engineering.
The title of their presentation is Drones to the Rescue, from Tools to Teammates in Public Safety.
As a first responder, having the right tools and the
right teammates is what's going to make the difference when trying to save your life.
One of the best tools we can carry is a drone,
because they can quickly cover large areas, and they keep my
teammates and I safe and aware of changing situations.
Imagine 14-year-old Taylor went for a walk a few hours
ago that hasn't come back yet, but it's getting dark and there's a storm coming.
When you call 911, I might be one of the first responders to arrive to help you find your child.
But even though we constantly train for this exact scenario,
it still takes two to three people to manage a single drone.
And that's because as a pilot, I need to be
laser-focused on flying the drone around trees and buildings, so
I need my teammates' help in looking at the video and talking on the radio.
All this people adds complexity, which adds training, so that
when the time comes, we know that we can find Taylor.
And so that's where my research comes in.
I aim to turn drones from simply tools into teammates
by helping them understand the context of the mission and giving
them the ability to give feedback to make sure those goals are aligned.
So the first step towards that is helping the drone understand context.
Instead of flying the drone left and right and up, I want to be able to say, go over there.
Search up the stream to the trail that leads to the farm.
And so to do that, I built a user interface and
wrote some software that provided a foundation for helping the drone understand that mission context.
But when we tested it, something wasn't quite right.
Even though we could give the drone a lot of
information, its goals weren't always aligned with their pilot.
And so what we thought we needed, we needed a way of
giving feedback for the drone to show what it thought it understood.
And to test that idea, we ran a simulated experiment.
where we see how pilots worked with drones, and the drone actually gave feedback.
In this case, it would simply ask a question as to
whether they thought the victim was near a certain landmark.
And this worked.
Not only did the team find more missing people, the pilots actually trusted the robot more.
And that's because whereas tools do exactly what you
do, sometimes they're detriment, a teammate works with you to accomplish a shared task.
And adding feedback fundamentally changes this dynamic.
This reduces the number of people we need per
aircraft, magnifying the impact of the team, simplifying our
operations, and reducing the training time we need.
All to make sure that when the time comes, we can find Taylor.
So whether we're fighting fire, looking for a
missing person, recovering after disaster, this research gives
first responders a safe and reliable teammate.
that works with them to support and protect their communities.
So that in these matters of life and death, like the
search for Taylor, you know that these robots will have your back.
Thank you.
Thanks, Hunter.
So some of your colleagues have shared with us the types
of food they enjoy, and I understand you have a go-to food.
I think cheese is one of the best foods in the world.
It comes in different flavors, shapes, sizes, smells.
You know, you really can never get bored.
So do you have like a top three?
Well, I did grow up in France, and they have this great cheese that translates to Golden Mountain.
And it's so creamy, it smells like a barnyard, but it's a real symphony in your mouth.
We'll let it go there.
Although, have you talked to Anna Turner about her mac and cheese?
Because she, I think, might be open to cheese recommendations.
Yeah, that might be a bit much.
So yeah, we'll let that one go.
Like Casey, you also enjoy skiing.
What kind of skiing do you do?
You can always find me in the trees.
I love flying through the trees on a nice day.
Maybe to my detriment sometimes.
But every, every time down the trees you're always exploring
a new way, and you're, you're really enjoying yourself in nature, and I really love that.
Do you have any go-to?
Well, steamboat's great.
I mean, flying through the aspens and, and those trees out there is really something special.
Wow.
Okay.
I'll let you do that.
Before coming to see you, Boulder, Hunter also had quite a range of jobs that you did.
Can you tell us about some of them?
Yeah, so I worked as an aerospace engineer building spacecraft systems.
So I was working on moon landers and instruments that would be going across the solar system.
And that was a really exciting place to be as a young engineer.
But I got really interested in how people play a part,
and that's where I decided to come here and do my
PhD, understanding how people and machines can really work together in a better way.
And how long have you been a first responder?
Just four years now, and that's been a really rewarding experience.
You know, the people that we work with and the people
that we show up to, we're often engaging with them on their very worst day, right?
It's oftentimes the worst day of their lives.
So it's a real honor to be able to help them in that situation.
But there's also a huge amount of responsibility that comes
from that and actually being able to help them execute the mission with your team.
Absolutely.
That's amazing.
So you mentioned spending time in France as a youngster.
You also were in Japan.
That's right.
Very lucky.
So were you as tall then as you are now?
I sure was.
And I remember they have these signs in the subways that stop at six feet.
And I remember when I was younger, I started hitting
my head on those advertisements in the subway.
And that's when I realized I was really tall.
Thank you, Hunter.
Thanks, bud.
Next up, we have Aoife Henry, PhD candidate in electrical computer and energy engineering.
The title of their presentation is, directing wind turbines with foresight.
The shepherd and the sheep dog find a crystal ball.
In my research, I am a shepherd of wind turbines.
You see, wind turbines are like sheep.
They're sturdy, they're obedient, but they're also kind of
simple creatures and they don't know how to handle themselves for the good of the group.
When the wind rolls in they need to be firmly instructed which way to face as conditions change.
Their default behaviour is to all very slowly rotate to face
the wind and to greasily lap up as much of its energy as they can.
But what the turbines don't know is that by doing this they're blocking the wind
for their less fortunate friends in the middle and at the
back of the pack and that the entire flock is producing less energy overall.
They also don't know that by the time they have
finally rotated to face the wind they measured, the wind direction has changed anyway.
Now, I'm a busy shepherd.
I don't have time to tell these turbines what to do every second of every day.
Instead, I design a wind farm controller.
This is like a sheepdog who's been trained to read
the situation and to direct the turbines accordingly.
This sheepdog looks at the wind speed and direction measurements,
and it barks at the turbines to rotate in a way that produces the most overall wind farm power.
The best research has come up with so far is to tell
the turbines at the front and the middle to face the wind at an angle.
This leaves more wind energy for their pals at the
back, achieving 10% more overall power in simulations.
The problem is that this result dwindles to 1% in real wind farms.
The focus of my work is to design a wind farm controller that can adapt to real wind conditions.
So what's wrong with this existing controller?
This sheepdog, he's a good boy, but the wind is disorderly and very unpredictable.
This sheepdog doesn't foresee how the wind will behave in the future.
It doesn't understand how much weaker, more turbulent, and
diverted the wind becomes as it blows in and around the turbines.
In simulations, the wind is well behaved, but out in the
Wild West of Texas, where most of the U.S.'
's wind farms are, it's a different story.
My thesis is to create a crystal ball.
We'll call it a forecaster.
that can make predictions about how the wind will change
in the coming minutes once it's been agitated by the turbines.
I've trained a computer program to decrypt months' worth of wind farm data
and to learn the relationships between the wind speed
and direction, turbine power, and rotation measurements over time.
I've upgraded the existing sheepdog with this forecaster so
he can direct the turbines with foresight.
My sheepdog can start their sheepishly slow rotation early
so that their positioning is just right for the winds they will see in the future.
Finally, I will fine-tune its training with live feedback from the Windfarm ex-operating app,
so that both the forecaster's predictions and the controller's instructions get better and better.
By equipping a Windfarm controller with a forecaster, I have trained a very clever sheepdog.
This could enable real Windfarms to reclaim the 10% extra
energy yield lost on the path from academia to industry.
reducing the cost of green energy by a dollar for
every ten, and hopefully, kicking fossil fuels to the curb, no matter how the wind blows.
Thank you.
Thank you, Ethan.
So, I understand that you know two languages that
are commonly considered to be endangered languages, Irish Gaelic and Scots.
That's right.
How did that come to be?
I was born in Scotland.
I usually tell people I'm Irish because that's my dominating accent at the moment.
We'll see how that changes in the next few years.
But I was born in Scotland.
My dad is Irish but was an enthusiast for dead languages.
So he sent me to one of very few Scots-Galic speaking schools.
And we were a half and half household.
And we spoke Irish at home and then Scots-Galic at school.
Wow.
So I understand you and your father can do something when you're around other people.
Sure.
Yeah, it's kind of a secret language at this point.
And actually, when I was in undergrad, I also lived in
a house, a grand house where they pay you to live there as long as you spoke Irish with each other.
But it appeared quite culty from the outside because we
all wore matching hoodies and spoke the secret language to one another.
But it wasn't a cult.
Yeah, not a cult.
So I understand that you try to run most days.
I do, yeah.
And where do you like to run?
I'm kind of boring at the moment.
I'm trying to graduate soon.
So I try to use my brain as little as possible outside of work.
So the less turns, the better.
If I could run in a straight line and come back, I would.
But usually routes around the boulder trails.
No judgment.
So were you a big runner before you came to Boulder?
Yeah, I used to be more competitive.
I used to do a lot of trail marathons but I've pulled
back from that a little bit now because it's not a reasonable
distance to run and I don't recommend it to anyone.
So do you have a temperature cutoff that you won't run below?
I actually relate a lot to Anna from earlier because I did run the ice
and suffered a very unusual injury for a runner in that I
tore two muscles in my arm a month ago from slipping on ice.
Maybe a treadmill would be a safer bet.
When it's cold and icy, yeah.
So in addition to your research on winter blinds and coding, you also do stand-up comedy.
When did that start?
It had been something I'd wanted to do for a long time, and then my strategy, I was so nervous.
My strategy was to go to a very small place, which was
the Trident, where they do it once a month, and to kind of dominate the space with my friends.
I duped about 11 people into going there.
There was only about 25 people there.
So I thought I'd at least get 11 laughs.
And they're well-behaved friends.
So is there a joke that you'd like to try out on us?
Different audience.
Safe, yeah.
I understand that one of your favorite foods is wellness sushi.
In Denver, what is wellness sushi?
I'm ethically fussy in my diet, and it's an all vegan sushi place, which I love.
It's well worth the drive.
And I've been on dates there.
I've taken friends there.
I've been there to celebrate things and grieve things.
So it's sushi for all occasions.
It's good.
Fabulous.
Thank you, Eva.
Thank you.
Next up, we have Heather Kinney Dudelo, PhD candidate in ecology and evolutionary biology.
The title of their presentation is Feathered Flinges, the Dating Lives of Barn Swallows.
Finding a romantic partner is a big decision, and it's no easy task.
You might turn to dating apps for help, but how do birds find a date?
Understanding the dating habits of birds can actually help
explain the amazing diversity of bird species.
Many birds use their colorful feathers to attract mates.
For example, in barn swallows, individuals with darker brown dress feathers are more attractive.
traits that are favored for mating become common in
the population, and this helps explain why different bird species are different colors.
However, dating is about more than just good looks, right?
It also requires being in the right place at the
right time and forming a social bond with someone.
My research explores this in barn swallows by
asking how social interactions, movement patterns, and nest locations matter for mate choice.
Barn swallows nest on barns and other human-made
structures which makes them accessible for research.
Multiple barn swallows can nest together in the same barn,
which we can think of as a nest neighborhood.
First, I used backpack tags like the one pictured on
the left to record social interactions of birds within a single neighborhood.
The tags detect which birds got close to each other and how long they spent together.
Using these data, I can find out how strong a social bond
needs to be in order for two birds to mate and produce offspring.
Next, I used backpack tags again to record GPS locations
to see if some birds fly farther in search of mates than others.
Think of your friend who sets their dating app's match
radius to 100 miles and the other friend who sets it to only five miles.
On the map, you can see that the female shown in
purple covered a larger area than the female shown in black.
Females that flew farther were more likely to have babies with multiple males.
Finally, the nesting barns are often located close to
each other, and the combined nest neighborhoods form a sort of town.
I found that barn swallows are more likely to mate
with neighbors from the same barn than with birds from the barn down the road.
Instead of looking everywhere for Mr. Right, females often choose Mr. Right here.
Studying the breeding biology of swallows can help
us improve conservation efforts for this declining group.
And more than that, understanding how social interactions, movement patterns,
and nest neighborhoods matter for barn swallows allows us
to explain how large scale patterns of plumage evolution emerge from the mate choices of individual birds.
I hope the next time you're outside and you see a
bird, you take a moment to wonder about its social life.
Where does it go and who does it meet?
Dating is complex in the bird world too, and you might
have more in common with that bird than you ever imagined.
Thank you.
Thank you, Heather.
So like Casey, you enjoy hiking.
Do you have any trails that you would recommend when the weather warms up?
Yeah.
So I live in North Boulder, and so we're near Wonderland Lake.
And so we really like the trails around the lake and also up from Lee Hill.
How far up Lee Hill?
Not too far.
There's a trailhead.
Just a block in.
All right.
I haven't seen that one.
I was like, OK.
So Marwa and Anna enjoy reading novels.
What sort of books do you enjoy reading?
I enjoy sci-fi and fantasy novels.
But unlike Marwa, I like cozy fantasy.
So this is like a story where you might have an ogre, but they decide to open up a coffee shop.
Clearly, I need to read more.
Do you have any titles or authors you recommend?
The author I really like is Becky Chambers.
She has a book called The Long Way to a Small, Angry Planet.
That's quite good.
Great title.
I love that.
This afternoon, you've heard a lot of fantastic food
stories from our graduate students, things that keep them fueled and inspired.
What is your favorite food?
The meal that came to mind when I was answering these questions is I really love
when I go back and stay with my parents in
Northern California to make like buttermilk waffles in the morning and
we have a big blueberry patch in our backyard so
putting fresh blueberries and my mom also grows strawberries and raspberries so just triple berry waffles.
And when will you be home this summer?
Because I think we'll all try to have a little look.
Oh my gosh, that sounds amazing.
So in addition to your graduate work in ecology
and evolutionary biology, you have also undertaken to learn the language Telugu.
Yeah, Telugu.
Telugu, one of the 22 official languages in India.
Is your husband able to join us this afternoon?
He is here, yes.
Well, keeping in mind that tomorrow is Valentine's Day, is
there anything you would like to say to your husband?
We're actually going to dinner tonight because he four years
ago proposed to me on February 13th, and so we celebrate on the 13th now.
Oh, my.
You can't make these stories up.
Thank you, Heather.
Thank you.
Let's give another huge round of applause to our ten amazing presenters.
What an incredible showcase of talent, research, and communication skills.
While our judges finalize their evaluations, it's your turn to make your decision.
The People's Choice Award is in your hands.
In just a not even a moment.
Right here is
You'll have exactly three minutes to cast your vote for
a presenter that you felt delivered the clearest, most engaging, and most compelling talk.
To vote, simply scan the QR code on the projection screen.
And remember, each audience member only gets one vote.
This is not Louisiana.
You can't vote early and often.
So only one vote.
So we'll now take a short break while the judges compile their scores.
There will be refreshments available.
You feel free to chat with your fellow attendees, and we'll see you back here in about 15 minutes.
Thank you all so much for being here today.
Dear friends, we are back.
Please stay in line.
Please enjoy the beverages and great food.
But we are back.
The Graduate School here at CU Boulder is home to
graduate students from around the world, each contributing
their expertise, creativity, and dedication to research.
Today, we had the privilege to hear from 10 of these remarkable scholars.
Now, multiply that 10 by the brilliance you saw today by 545.
That gets us up to the 6,000 graduate students who
are currently enrolled here at CU Boulder to give you just
a glimpse of the talent within our graduate community.
So once again, let's give a big round of applause to our 10 finalists.
Now it is my great pleasure to welcome back Dean of
the Graduate School, Scott Adler, and we will announce and celebrate our winners.
So first up, the People's Choice Award goes to, now everybody have to do a drum roll.
The People's Choice Award winner is Heather Kinney Dudela.
Come on down.
Next up, drumroll.
Our runner up today is Casey Middleton.
And one last drum roll.
The winner of today's 3MT 2025 competition is Aoife Henry.
Well, that was absolutely phenomenal.
Great presentations.
Congratulations to all our winners and truly to every participant.
Each of you showcased not only the depth of your
research, but also the power of making knowledge accessible and engaging.
A heartfelt thank you to our competitors, to our judges for their thoughtful evaluations,
and of course, to all of you, our audience,
for supporting and celebrating graduate research with us today.
Now, stay, enjoy the refreshments, and join us in
celebrating the winners, and have a wonderful evening.
Oh, one more thing, if I could get all the competitors on the stage for a group photo.