All right, cool.
Okay, welcome back everyone.
Good to see you.
I have a few announcements before we get started.
Number one, I know we can probably get to chapters 12, 13, and 15.
But I didn't want to rush things.
So I don't know if you noticed, on Canvas, I push all of those slide decks to the final exam.
It doesn't mean you're really getting too much more on
the final exam because we'll have some guest lectures and some special topics and things like that.
So don't worry that we're overloading the final exam.
I think we'll be OK with this, having a little bit
less material to worry about in this short period of time before spring break.
So we're really just focusing on
chapters 8, 9, 10, and 11.
That way we can kind of take our time with these
and make sure we're really focusing on these last two slide
decks as opposed to trying to worry about that physiology of
training, which is actually a decent number of slides.
I believe I updated the syllabus, the calendar on that to reflect it,
but just know for exam two, lecture exam two, we're
just focusing on what's on that Canvas module all the way up to chapter 11.
Any questions on that?
Okay.
When is that exam?
two weeks from today.
So it's coming up pretty quick.
The nice thing is you'll just get that out of the way
and you can enjoy spring break and then come back for that last leg before we take the final.
So you're pretty much through the...
The bulk of things, we got your first lecture exam, you got your first lab exam in the books.
Next week during your lab, at the end of each lab,
we'll hand back your lab exams and you'll see, you'll get to
review your lab exam and then you can ask any questions to the TA.
And then we can meet again later if you have any other questions.
All right.
Okay, so.
We'll move on here to respiration during exercise.
Here's the general outline.
We're going to start with the mechanics of breathing.
So we need to talk about
Just a few things to make sure we're on the same page with the mechanics of breathing.
Then we'll talk about pulmonary ventilation.
Then the control of ventilation at rest and during exercise.
So this is almost like the why and this is the how.
And then blood flow to the lungs.
We kind of touched on this already with Harms' work, but we'll touch on it a little bit more.
Ventilation-perfusion relationships, so this is pretty important, especially
if we're trying to take these concepts to, say, different environmental settings like altitude.
Then the O2 transport in the blood and muscle, CO2
transport in the blood, and does the pulmonary system limit exercise performance?
So there's this idea that, in general, our lungs are a little bit overbuilt.
But we'll take a look into that concept.
OK, so let's start with a brief introduction.
I think we know all about pulmonary ventilation.
But here it is.
Ventilation is just breathing.
And we're just exchanging different gases.
We're primarily concerned about oxygen and CO2.
And so that's why a lot of the times it's just labeled as the exchange of O2 and CO2 in the lungs.
Cellular respiration, on the other hand, well, this is happening at the tissues, right?
At the cells themselves, they are also kind of exchanging or moving oxygen
and CO2 in different ways because it's utilizing the
oxygen in order to undergo oxidative phosphorylation and then
producing CO2 once you start breaking down some of those carbon chains in the Krebs cycle.
Okay, so the overall broad purpose then of the
respiratory system during exercise is just moving the air from the outside into your body.
The other piece that we sometimes forget about is we also
try to exhale some molecules in order to really regulate
acid-base balance during times of maybe large pH changes.
Typically, that happens during exercise, but you could imagine
that can happen in a variety of different situations, not during exercise.
But since we're an exercise physiology course, we're gonna focus on the during exercise here.
Okay, mechanics of breathing, pretty straightforward, ventilation, moving air.
We really do that by bulk flow.
We need some type of pressure differential.
If we can get low pressure inside of the lungs, the air will just move into the lungs.
If we can increase the pressure into the lungs more
than the pressure in the environment, then the air will leave our lungs.
So that's basically what these two pieces are saying.
We have inspiration when intrapulmonary pressure is less
than atmospheric pressure, and then expiration when intrapulmonary
pressure is greater than atmospheric pressure.
One thing to kind of keep in mind is sort of a
little bit separate, but it still has to deal with what we're talking about is Boyle's law.
We know this.
If you kind of decrease the pressure here, you're going to increase the volume.
And then if you increase the pressure, you're going to
decrease the volume inside of a closed container space.
OK, changes in thoracic cavity size during breathing.
Luckily, we've kind of touched on this.
This is one of the mechanisms that we use to
increase kind of that end-diastolic volume or the venous return.
So if we undergo inspiration, the diaphragm actually pushes
downwards, and the ribs kind of lift outward.
That helps increase the volume of the lungs.
And that would be this piece here.
During expiration, the diaphragm just relaxes.
And once the diaphragm relaxes, it returns to its normal position.
And the ribs just normally go back to its position as well.
And then that helps decrease the volume of the lungs.
And we expire some of that air.
You can almost think of it like a rubber band.
So if you expand the rubber band, then you just let it go.
It'll compress on its own or go back to its original position.
Going back to that original position is going to increase
the pressure inside of the lungs to move the air out.
But especially during exercise, we do need to engage
some respiratory muscles to forcefully push some of the air out.
And so we do use other muscles in order to help with moving air in and out of our lungs,
but you will never really be, not never, but in this
course, we're not really going to be testing whether you know the locations of these muscles here.
This is basically just saying there are muscles that we
use primarily or a little bit more dominantly on inspiration versus expiration.
But especially during rest or maybe very light exercise,
it's really just you're working on the diaphragm and then you just let everything relax on its own.
So we would call all of these like accessory muscles for respiration.
Okay, so sometimes I like to show this slide just because
you're in the middle of things in the semester and it can
get a little stressful, but it's always a good reminder to just breathe sometimes, right?
Independent of the fact that
A nice deep breath might help you relax by
maybe inhibiting the sympathetic nervous system to prevent the
release of cortisol as well as maybe activate the
parasympathetic nervous system to reduce some heart rate.
No, we're not even worried about all that, right?
You just, all right, it's gonna be okay, right?
Like it's gonna be okay.
All right.
But the other topic I like to talk about is nasal strips.
So let me bring this in.
You've probably thought about this, or maybe you've heard about this.
So I'm going to ask you, do nasal strips reduce the work of breathing during exercise?
True or false?
What do we think about this?
Let's try a couple more seconds on this one, maybe 15 seconds or so.
Does anyone need more time getting set up?
OK, yeah, take your time.
All right, how about 45 seconds from now?
We're doing okay?
Maybe shorter?
All right, 10 seconds.
Double check you got something in.
Feel like we're a little light today, but it looks like we have a decent number in here.
Okay, I'll close this down in three, two, one.
All right.
I'd just like to show this because we'll talk about
this, but in past semesters, most people, it's usually like 50-50.
I don't know if it's because you've kind of caught on
to how these questions are going when I usually present them, but why are we thinking false?
I actually like that answer, but maybe true or false.
Any ideas?
Yeah, and what was that first part you said?
Yeah, most of the muscles are in the chest.
But I guess, so you are correct about that, but what's
the point, or for the people who said true, what's the point of a nasal strip?
Yeah, decrease resistance, and especially in the nostrils here.
So then if I'm increasing the airflow in the nostrils, why wouldn't maybe that work?
Why wouldn't that maybe
improve athletic performance.
So the majority of you said false, and I feel like you're on the right track here, but maybe why?
Because I am curious.
And it could just be because... Yeah.
And so that's one of the biggest things, right?
If you try primarily breathing through your nostrils, that's
always going to be much harder than if you start breathing through your mouth, right?
And one of the biggest things that we sometimes forget
is, yeah, at rest and maybe light exercise, most of the ventilation does occur through the nose.
But as you increase with exercise intensity, airflow maybe can
be through both of them or one of them.
But what would be the primary limiting factor in bringing more air in?
So whether I'm breathing through my mouth and my nose.
Yeah, how much oxygen your body can take in as well as what's another physical limitation?
Yeah, so your trachea.
Eventually, it doesn't matter how much air is moving in
through either your mouth and your nose, but then the trachea is
going to limit how much air you can push through.
So theoretically, nasal strips would increase airflow into
the lungs by reducing airway resistance.
That's the whole idea.
But it really doesn't do a whole lot.
The only thing that they did find was it changes the switch point.
And the switch point is basically when you start maybe
breathing through the mouth versus only the nose.
So if you're just relying on your nasopharynx to breathe, you would be able to do
that for longer or for higher intensities before you have
to switch to maybe both or just one breathing through your mouth.
So it doesn't necessarily improve performance, but it
could potentially improve your ability to perform when only breathing through your nose.
So that's pretty much what they found here.
That's no surprise if you think about the physical limitation of the trachea itself.
And they sometimes call this switch point, like they give you terms where if you can sing,
then that's probably a really low intensity.
If you can talk while exercising, then things are getting a little bit harder.
But then once you start getting quiet, so it's like the
sing, talking, and shut up, then you know when you can't talk anymore, you're working really hard.
And you've probably done that before.
If someone's just talking and yapping away when you're
just really struggling running, then you're probably thinking that in your head a little bit.
OK, so yeah, nasal dilator strips do not work.
There was no difference even in the switch point between these two.
No significant difference, although some did improve.
But the biggest thing would be is there's just no reduction in the work of breathing.
So if we really believed that there was some type
of improvement or we are increasing the ability of the
air to get in, then the respiratory muscles themselves should be working less.
And there was no difference between nasal strips or the control or placebo.
So definitely does improve nasal breathing, but doesn't improve performance.
OK, so let's move on to pulmonary ventilation then.
Before we go into pulmonary ventilation, I'll often show
these four little boxes here, and we'll start moving our way down these four boxes.
So we're going to start with pulmonary ventilation, then
go to alveolar gas exchange, gas transport, and systemic gas exchange, and then kind of coming back out.
As you might already know, pulmonary ventilation is
also called minute ventilation or expired ventilation.
So most of the time, we're only measuring the
expired ventilation, not necessarily the inspired ventilation.
So that's this VE over here.
And that's really just the amount of air that's moved in and out of the lungs per minute.
The tidal volume is the amount of air that you're moving per breath.
So you can think of this almost like very similar to
how we measure stroke volume, the volume of blood leaving the heart.
Well, this is the volume of air leaving the lungs per breath.
The breathing frequency is just the number of breaths per minute.
So if you remember, that's very similar to beats per minute or heart rate.
You multiply those two together, you get VE, again, very similar to the concept of cardiac output.
So you have this absolute amount of air that you're moving
at a given frequency, so we get the total expired ventilation.
One thing to note, though,
This is not something you need to know, but we need
to be really careful about this concept of anatomical dead space.
So even though we're moving all of this air in and out of our lungs,
There is a portion from the bottom of your trachea all the
way up to your mouth and the end of your nasopharynx.
That actually doesn't exchange any gas.
You're just moving air back and forth.
And so that is considered anatomical dead space, because
we're not really exchanging gas with the alveoli.
And that doesn't really get a chance to diffuse into the lungs.
So that's not accounted for here, but just know that that
becomes a little bit of an issue in certain instances.
So if you were to hyperventilate at a really, really high frequency, then you're not allowing
for the lungs to fully inflate, sort of like the
same concept we were talking about with filling time, and you would just
ventilate with anatomical dead space and that's when
usually people have problems and they hyperventilate and they need
to like breathe into a bag, things like that, right?
Because you're just really moving air from the anatomical dead
space and instead you want to take nice big deep breaths to try
to get all of the air down to the gas exchange area.
OK, so moving on from that, the ventilatory responses,
if we have expired ventilation, it does increase with increasing exercise intensity.
So here, if we have light exercise, maybe we're at
40 liters per minute, moderate at 80, severe around 120 liters per minute.
And so that's a decent amount of air.
If you think of a two-liter bottle, if you have 60
of those, that's how much you're moving in and out of
your lungs every minute during this high or heavy intensity exercise.
And you probably noticed this when you were using the Douglas bag technique.
Those bags started to fill up pretty quick at some of those higher intensities.
I will say, though this is typically the average
ventilation towards heavy or maximal exercise, we did some research with category one cyclists.
So these are basically professional cyclists, cat one cyclists.
And they had upwards of 222 liters per minute for their ventilation.
So they were quite a bit higher than what we're seeing here.
And yeah, that was a little bit high.
But on average, I think they were at 200.
So there are people at 180.
Some people are at 215.
So just know that it is possible to get quite a bit higher than this 120 mark here.
All right, tidal volume, breathing frequency during graded exercise tests.
This is more of the same concept here.
As I'm increasing exercise intensity down here on the
x-axis, I am increasing the respiratory rate on the y-axis.
So that's going to increase relatively linearly here.
Tidal volume will also increase as we increase with exercise intensity here.
the changes in breathing pattern here.
The way you want to kind of interpret this figure here is
as I am increasing the kind of height, I am increasing the tidal volume.
As I'm bringing the waveforms closer and closer together, I am increasing the frequency.
So you can see from
I guess heavy exercise all the way to very heavy
exercise, the tidal volume isn't as maybe impactful as the change in frequency.
So typically we have an increase in frequency at
those higher intensities as opposed to tidal volume.
And that should make a little bit of sense, one,
because we're reducing the filling time of the lungs, but two, we are kind of
at some type of max as far as how much air our lungs
can move in and out or how much our lungs can move air in and out of those spaces.
So typically the tide of volume kind of plateaus a little bit faster than the frequency.
Any questions on this one?
All right.
Okay, so what about the control of ventilation at rest and during exercise?
So I'm trying to bring it back to the same kind
of pathway that we did with the cardiovascular system or the heart,
is we want to focus on maybe what is happening with
the pulmonary system and then how we're actually getting this control to happen.
Okay, so control of ventilation at rest.
So we're focusing at rest here.
So inspiration and expiration.
We are, again, contracting and relaxing the diaphragm.
This is controlled by somatic motor neurons, so those kind
of skeletal muscles or the muscles in the diaphragm.
And that is basically those signals in the spinal cord
as well as the respiratory center in the medulla oblongata.
If those signals are coming from those two regions in
our nervous system, then we should think about how that's actually causing us to start to breathe.
So number one, neural input.
So from the motor cortex and the skeletal muscle mechanoreceptors.
So once you start exercising, what this is saying is,
There's something coming from the motor cortex as
well as the skeletal muscle mechanoreceptors that are sending that
signal back up to tell the brain to send a signal to the lungs to increase ventilation.
Those signals are coming from the muscle spindles, the
Golgi tendon organs, and the joint pressure receptors, as well as that motor cortex.
So as soon as you get activation or some changes
in those signaling at the muscles, they are synapsing and telling your brain to increase ventilation.
Which is kind of cool because if you were to do the study and they have, you know the little like
TENS machines that they sometimes put on you at the physical therapy.
If you put enough of those on a large enough or a large kind of muscle area
and you increase the stimulation, those individuals will all
of a sudden start to increase their ventilation.
So those signals are just being sent to increase ventilation.
So as soon as you start exercising, your muscles are
sending signals to the brain to say, hey, increase that ventilation.
OK, so that's this piece here.
We have some receptors in the muscles and the joints.
Those are sending signals to the respiratory center.
And then those kind of go up to the higher brain centers.
But then you're also then sending those signals back down to increase ventilation.
Pretty cool.
And that would go to the same if you were like lifting weights or something like that.
OK, number two, humoral.
So humorals kind of like inside of the blood.
And then chemoreceptors.
We have two locations for these chemoreceptors.
The central chemoreceptors, which are located in the medulla.
Those, well, you have some other receptors as well that
are kind of sensitive to partial pressure of CO2 as well as hydrogen concentrations.
And those are in the cerebral spinal fluid.
So anytime you think central chemoreceptors, think central nervous system.
They're located in the central nervous system.
They are a little bit more sensitive to the partial pressure of CO2 and hydrogen ions,
and they are gonna cause, depending on the influx of
them, are gonna cause an individual to increase or decrease ventilation.
The peripheral chemoreceptors, they're not really like in the periphery like your fingers.
They're just not in the central nervous system.
In particular, the aortic and carotid bodies.
These chemoreceptors are a little bit more sensitive to
partial pressure changes in oxygen, CO2, as well as ion changes in hydrogen and potassium.
Regardless of the chemoreceptor, does anyone know which one we rely on first?
Meaning, which of these four, if they were to change, would
we respond to first as far as changing ventilation?
Hydrogen is close.
It's not hydrogen, so now it's one out of three now.
It is the partial pressure of CO2.
So when you hold your breath and you get that
little urge to breathe, that's because you're building up CO2 pressure.
The one thing I will note, especially when we get
to altitude, it changes at rapid or acute changes in elevation.
If you go to Pike's Peak, you will immediately
start increasing ventilation because of a large change in partial pressure of oxygen.
But the primary sensitivity that's coming from these chemoreceptors is CO2.
It then switches to oxygen if you start changing
elevation or the inspired partial pressure of oxygen.
OK, so these central peripheral chemoreceptors, this is a nice little figure here.
So you have some of these kind of sending signals to increase respiration.
OK, so that was at rest, right?
We still have these.
I guess, sensor our sensors when we exercise, but
we now have preferential treatment on what's controlling ventilation.
I can't stress this enough, right?
Like I need to underline this, right?
So ventilatory control during submaximal exercise is primarily mediated by the neural input.
So that number one, right?
We talked about neuro and humoral.
Well, submaximal exercise is primarily mediated by neural input.
So that's this kind of piece over here, this neural piece.
So we're still on submaximal.
So you have your higher brain centers and your
respiratory muscle control centers, and then you have your
peripheral chemoreceptors and all of these pieces.
But the primary drive to increase ventilation is the higher brain centers.
Secondary would be these chemoreceptors and mechanoreceptors down over here.
All right.
I do have a note in here.
Temperature is not on here, but temperature is a driver of ventilation.
So it'd be the same thing.
If I just increase the temperature here high enough
for everyone and your core body temperature started to
increase, you will start to increase your ventilation.
Most people think it's very similar to like dog's
pant because that's their primary drive of thermal regulation.
They need to exhale that heat out.
It is believed that we also increase ventilation to try to exhale some heat.
But it's a little bit controversial as far as the
magnitude of temperature change due to that ventilation.
OK, this looks the same, but it is kind of trying to get at a different point here.
Ventilatory control during maximal exercise is primarily mediated by humoral input.
So submaximal is primarily neural.
maximal exercise is primarily humoral.
That doesn't mean that's the only thing going on.
It's just primarily mediated by humoral factors.
And so that would be this piece over here.
Any questions on that?
Again, just try to circle rest, submaximal, maximal.
All right.
OK, so that kind of finishes the pulmonary ventilation.
We can now move to alveolar gas exchange.
Finally, we moved all the air into our lungs.
We want to get the important pieces into the blood.
and some waste products out of the blood.
So oxygen into the blood, CO2 out.
That means we need to focus on the partial pressure
of oxygen, PO2, and then the partial pressure of carbon dioxide, PCO2.
Sometimes you will see letters after the P. That just indicates location.
So if I saw PI02, that's the inspiratory partial pressure of oxygen.
If I saw a little a, it'd be PA02, so not
capitalized, lowercase a, that would be the partial pressure of oxygen in the arteries.
So we'll go through that, but just if you see
those small little letters there, they're just kind of keying you in on the location.
OK, so this should look relatively familiar.
We have some type of partial pressure of oxygen inside of the inspired air, so the environment.
We bring that in into the lungs.
We get a little bit of humidification, so the partial pressure drops.
And we want to match this partial pressure, this 104, with the partial pressure in the lungs.
So we're diffusing some of that oxygen down into the blood.
And then you lose a little bit because you're feeding some of the other organs.
So you're down at 95.
And now the partial pressure at 95 is here.
It's going to drop off some oxygen.
And then we're going to get 40 back in the veins.
So it's nice to kind of keep these numbers in the back of your mind.
You would never really need to like,
be quizzed on when or what value is in the venous blood versus the arteries.
But sometimes it would help if you kind of keep an idea of like 100.
Around 100 is the partial pressure of oxygen in the arteries.
And then around 40 is the partial pressure of oxygen in the veins.
You'll spend some more time in lab with these calculations.
But again, just kind of keep those in the back of your mind.
Okay, so pulmonary capillaries are pretty much going to grab
some of that oxygen or allow for the diffusion to occur.
So we have air inside of these alveoli.
And yes, they're going to exchange with these capillary beds here.
And hopefully we can then move that back to the heart.
clinically or some clinical applications to this is
quite relevant, especially because we were dealing with a
quite severe pulmonary disorder or disease with COVID.
Interestingly, or I guess not surprisingly, it's causing some
issues with individuals who had some of these moderate to severe symptoms.
So they can promote lung injury because they are
collecting additional fluid inside of the alveoli.
in addition to the space between the capillary as well as the alveoli wall.
So you're almost increasing the diffusion distance if you have
some type of fluid buildup in those areas.
That means you are kind of experiencing a reduction in the partial pressure of oxygen.
So a healthy kind of
alveolar bed here is looking like this.
If you have an infection that's going to cause some sort of response,
and the response as well as the damage from the infection
itself is going to cause a little bit of fluid buildup here.
If you had severe fluid buildup, then that would cause a pretty big problem.
An example of that would be this here.
So this would be moderate damage, and we have some
fluid buildup because we have an immune response.
Well, now I'm not going to be able to exchange gas
down here, and I'm really just relying on these smaller pieces over here.
If I had severe damage, then there's really
very, very little room to exchange any type of gas between the capillary as well as the alveoli.
And so this is why it was so important for individuals who had severe COVID to go on a ventilator,
because they were trying to really one force air in
there, but increase the partial pressure of oxygen to kind
of maximize the alveoli that were available to exchange gas.
We also actually see this with maybe extreme high-altitude issues.
So we call it like HAPE, so high-altitude pulmonary edema.
You can actually get fluid to just seep into the lungs, and then you get the same issue as this.
So not good to have fluid inside of your lungs, outside fluid.
OK, blood flow to the lung.
Pulmonary arteries receive mixed venous blood from the right ventricle.
Oxygenated blood returned to the left atrium via the pulmonary vein.
The low pressure system with the rate of blood flow equal to the systemic circuit.
We kind of already touched on this.
If you have any change in pressure inside of any
of that system, whether it's the pulmonary system or the systemic,
you are going to have blood move from high pressure to low pressure.
And that's the same with movement of air flow.
OK, blood flow to the lung.
So during resting conditions or standing, most of the blood flow is to the base of the lung.
That is just due to the gravitational forces, right?
If we're standing up and down, most of the blood flow is kind of
not really pool, but it's going to kind of aggregate towards the bottom of the lung.
During upright exercise, blood flow does increase to the top of the lung.
You also see this as a little bit of an issue with astronauts who go to microgravity.
Or again, if you simulate microgravity, then some of that blood is going to rush towards the apex.
And it sometimes does cause a little bit of a
problem, because then you start pushing plasma out of the capillaries and into that space.
And we don't really want to do that.
OK.
This one's kind of straightforward, but if you happen to,
what happens to blood flow in the lung during supine or face up or prone face down exercise,
and I guess this is a little bit different because
they're traveling a certain direction as well, but if someone
is face down or prone, if they're laying down, most of the blood will kind of aggregate where?
Yeah, towards the top of the lung, and then if you decide to flip yourself upside down
or maybe you want a trip to go on one of those
space flights, then most of the blood will kind of pool down to the top of the lung.
Okay, ventilation-perfusion relationships.
This is important because even though, or even if the
alveoli are well ventilated, if you don't have adequate blood
flow, then that's still going to impair gas exchange.
This then introduces the topic or the concept of ventilation-perfusion ratio.
We also call that the V-Q ratio.
We say this is V because this is ventilation, Q
because that's more referring to the cardiac output or blood flow.
So the V is ventilation, the Q is blood flow.
Sometimes, right, perfusion pressure, perfusion, that's usually referring to blood.
Okay, so this indicates a matching of blood flow to ventilation.
An ideal V-Q ratio is about one or slightly above if
your blood flow is a little bit higher, meaning maybe moderate to heavy exercise.
So you can think of it this way, where if we
have a blood vessel here or a pulmonary capillary, the blood is moving through that capillary.
The speed at which this blood moves to the capillary
will dictate a little bit of how well saturated we can get some of those hemoglobin molecules.
This pressure here from the alveoli is the partial pressure of oxygen in the alveoli.
So here's another kind of piece down here.
So the capital A is kind of referring to the alveoli.
So alveolar ventilation or pulmonary ventilation, and then cardiac output down here.
We do have different VQ relationships depending on the anatomical location of the lung.
So towards the apex, the ventilation can be at 0.24 liters per minute.
But the blood flow is going to be quite a bit lower at 0.07.
And so the ratio is going to be about 3.43.
And in this instance, because it's well above 1, we
are saying it's underperfuse relative to the ventilation, meaning
the ventilation is much higher than the blood flow.
So we're not really maximizing things a whole lot because
you're getting a lot of oxygen into the lungs, but the
blood's not really moving past, so you're not really maximizing
the amount of transfer or diffusion of that oxygen into the blood.
Here at the base, because again, the base of the lung
has a higher blood flow compared to the apex.
This does change whether you lay down or you go to microgravity or you flip on your head.
So the ventilation will be 0.82, for example, on average, with the blood flow being 1.29.
The ratio then drops below 1 to 0.64.
And so we would say this is over perfused relative
to ventilation, meaning the ventilation is much lower than the blood flow.
So in this instance, the blood is just moving too fast.
And it's not giving enough time to allow for adequate
oxygen delivery and transfer as well as saturation of those hemoglobin molecules.
We'll touch on this a little bit later, but this is
a really good introduction to a concept called pulmonary capillary transit time.
So how quickly is the blood moving past the alveoli?
that does determine how well we can saturate some of
those red blood cells or those hemoglobin molecules.
Any questions here?
Yeah.
Yeah, the top one, we're saying the blood's moving too
slow compared to the amount of air that we're moving in and out
of the lungs at the top of the lungs, at the apex.
At the base, it's flipped.
Now these are examples.
It's not always this way, but it starts changing a little bit when we exercise.
But it's nice to see
that we sometimes have an imbalance in this VQ ratio
and that could impair or maybe underutilize some of the diffusion and transfer of oxygen.
Okay, so exercise-induced asthma here.
This is caused by a contraction of smooth muscle around the airways.
You also or those individuals typically also get a little
bit of mucus or some type of fluid buildup inside of the lungs or the airways.
This can cause some labor breathing or dyspnea, so difficulty breathing.
It is characterized by a wheezing sound.
So sometimes you can hear this pretty well without a
stethoscope, but it's much easier to hear with a stethoscope.
It does occur in about 10% of the elite endurance athletes.
So it is relatively common.
However, if it is corrected, we use some sort of inhaler
or some sort of steroid, then we can manage this and it doesn't impair performance.
And we'll talk about this a little bit more as well.
All right, hopefully I've got your mind off of the VQ ratio because here we go.
What will happen to the VQ ratio in a patient with asthma or a type of airway obstruction?
Okay, let's go, I don't know, 30 more seconds.
Pretty excited for this one.
Thought I went slow enough through here.
All right, 15 seconds unless someone needs a little more time.
10 seconds, double check you have something in.
I'll close it down in three, two, one.
Oh, 96, that's good.
That's good.
Okay, so if you have asthma or any sort of airway
obstruction, which is kind of depicted here in this figure, what happens to ventilation?
Yeah, it goes down.
So by default, one of these ventilation is lower than blood flow.
Okay, so local control of ventilation and perfusion, all is
not lost if we have some sort of airway obstruction.
There are ways we can try to protect against and
under or over perfusion by making some adjustments to areas that we have control over.
So for example, if we have some sort of
narrowing of the airway or obstruction in the airway, the
body does respond by kind of reducing some of the perfusion.
So pulmonary arteries serving these alveoli constrict.
You would think, right, like there's nothing we can really
do, but we could just reduce the blood flow to try to match that inflow or the ventilation.
And so we can try to
correct the mismatch by constricting some of these alveoli.
If an individual is exercising, that might not be the
best option for performance, but I think we put on a higher order survival over your 10K performance.
Okay, so if there's a blood clot then, so if you
have a VQ ratio greater than one, then the pulmonary artery serving these alveoli can dilate.
And so we can try to increase that flow to try to get back closer towards the one.
Now these are in response, right?
We have a blood clot or we have some issue with the flow of blood going through these capillaries.
And so it's possible we can try and correct that by vasodilating.
If we already have some type of obstruction with ventilation, so ventilation goes way down,
well, we can try to correct that by constricting or
reducing some of the blood flow that's coming through there.
You might think, why would we do that?
Well, this is the concept that I first brought in
a little bit earlier, a pulmonary capillary transit time.
So low to moderate intensity exercise does improve the VQ ratio.
However, high intensity exercise results in a slight VQ inequality.
So here's the best way to try to look at this.
One, in both situations, the partial pressure of oxygen is the same.
It's at 100.
However, if I am exercising at max versus rest
or sorry, max versus maybe moderate exercise intensity, we would
have some sort of cardiac output that's delivering blood to the lungs.
The partial pressure of oxygen is 40 here.
And so if it has enough time, so where the pulmonary
capillary transit time is slow enough or long enough,
then there's plenty of time for the red blood cells
to pass through and fully saturate with oxygen, so now we're at 100.
So there's just 100 to 100.
If, however, the blood is moving too fast because
we're at high intensity exercise, the stroke volume, the cardiac output is quite high,
then like what we knew before, the venous blood partial pressure
of 40, but now some of these red blood cells are not
fully saturated and so now we have a partial pressure of 80.
And that's when we get a substantial decrease or a shorter pulmonary capillary transit time.
Now, I like to use this example, and it doesn't help everybody, but sometimes it does.
And as long as it helps one person, I'm going to keep using this example.
But if you could imagine that on the side of a sidewalk there was a fire hydrant
that was broken and it was just pushing water onto the
sidewalk, that, to me, would be the partial pressure of oxygen.
So you can imagine the water molecules are oxygen.
Now, if you had to go through this kind of broken
fire hydrant, I could walk through very slowly, and then all
of my clothes would be fully saturated with water.
If I didn't want to do that, what would you try to do?
Yeah, you would try to sprint through.
So if I sprinted through as fast as I could, maybe just
the right side of my clothes would be wet, but the left side would be dry.
And so you could imagine the red blood cells that
are furthest away from the alveoli might not have enough
partial pressure to get fully saturated because they're just moving too fast past the alveoli.
We okay here?
This is pretty straightforward when we're thinking about it like this.
But once we get to elite athletes and high altitude,
well, now this number changes and pulmonary capillary transit
time becomes even more important to think about.
And it kind of causes this concept of exercise-induced arterial desaturation.
But we'll get to that a little bit later.
Any questions so far?
Am I moving too slow?
Trying to make sure we're, OK, cool.
All right, so we talked about pulmonary ventilation.
We moved on to that alveolar gas exchange.
And now we need to see, how are we going to get that O2 transport into the blood and muscle?
So that's this part here.
So now we're over here.
Okay, so we finally, right, the oxygen's in the alveoli and it's diffusing into the blood.
Where does it go in the blood?
Does it just hang out with the red blood cells?
Seeing some shakes, so where does it go?
How do we transport oxygen in the body?
I've kinda mentioned it a few times, but... It's a protein.
Hemoglobin.
Nice.
Thank you.
So 99% of the oxygen that is transported is bound to hemoglobin.
If a hemoglobin molecule has oxygen bound to it, we call it oxyhemoglobin.
When hemoglobin or hemoglobin site does not have oxygen bound to it, we call it deoxyhemoglobin.
Where do we think the other 1% of oxygen is being transported?
So we have oxygen in the blood.
99% of the oxygen that's in our blood, if we were to take a blood sample, is bound to hemoglobin.
Where's the rest?
Where's the other 1% going?
It'd be part of the buffering system.
Yeah, so I like where you're going with that, but where
would oxygen then either be bound to or not bound to something?
How are we transporting it?
So it's stuck on some hemoglobin molecules.
That's 99% of the 100 partial pressure that we just looked at.
So where's that other 1%?
It is just floating, but where?
It's in the plasma.
It's just like dissolved into the plasma, right?
Like if you have a, I don't know, some people call it soda, some people call it pop, right?
If you have a can and you shake it up and you just
open it, well all of that kind of just diffuses out of the liquid in itself.
So that's CO2, but O2 is dissolved into the plasma.
So there is a small contribution of oxygen diffused into
the plasma, but it's very, very, very little.
When we go through that formula, you'll see how small of a fraction it is.
OK, so then the amount of oxygen that is transported is dependent on these three big factors here.
One, hemoglobin concentration.
So how many hemoglobin molecules do we have floating around inside of the blood?
Then two, out of the hemoglobin molecules that we do have, how many are fully bound with oxygen?
When we see them fully bound, we see an SpO2 of 100%.
Then this small, right?
Very minor contribution, we have a small amount dissolved in the plasma.
Any questions here?
So these are three big factors here, try to keep those in mind.
Even though it's a minor contribution, you can't forget about the amount dissolved in plasma.
Okay, so this brings in the oxyhemoglobin dissociation
curve, or the sometimes hemoglobin dissociation curve.
I know you've seen this in physiology, but we're gonna bring it back because it's quite important.
So the direction of the reaction does depend on the partial pressure of oxygen in the blood.
It also depends on the affinity between hemoglobin and oxygen.
There are different states of hemoglobin.
We're not going to get into the exact chemical
states that change during different pressure pressures and acidities and temperatures.
All you need to know is that there is a
change in affinity for oxygen on these hemoglobin molecules depending on the situation.
We'll go through those.
So at the lung, a high partial pressure of oxygen
encourages the formation of oxyhemoglobin.
We call that loading.
So we're loading oxygen onto the hemoglobin molecules.
At the tissues, in particular the skeletal muscle, there's a low partial pressure of oxygen.
What is causing this decrease in partial pressure of oxygen?
Who can help me out?
It is relatively simple, or straightforward, I guess.
Yeah, the tissues are using it.
So the mitochondria are consuming the oxygen at the
electron transport chain, which then removes the oxygen.
So there's a decrease in concentration or partial pressure oxygen at the mitochondria.
That means there's a decreased pressure-pressure concentration of oxygen at the myoglobin.
And so now, overall, next to the capillaries, it's lower
in the skeletal muscle compared to the capillaries.
So we have this low partial pressure of oxygen
at the tissues.
So that's going to encourage the hemoglobin molecules to drop off the oxygen at the tissues.
So it's going to move down its concentration gradient.
Every time one oxygen molecule drops off, it starts
reducing the affinity overall to the hemoglobin, and then they're a little bit easier to drop off.
OK, here's that oxygen hemoglobin dissociation curve
I would spend a decent amount of time here.
So just make sure you understand what's going on on
all these axes as well as different situations.
Okay, we're gonna start with partial pressure of oxygen here.
Notice how there really isn't a distinguishing factor of
location, but this is the partial pressure of oxygen inside of the blood.
This is the percent hemoglobin saturation, or SAO2, so
saturation of the hemoglobin molecules in the arteries.
Hemoglobin molecules are in the arteries, so that's why we say SAO2.
If we say SPO2, that's pulse oximetry.
That's like when you use a little light.
You put that little thing on your finger.
That's SPO2.
But this is SAO2 over here.
OK, so if I see a partial pressure around 100 at sea level, it's a little bit lower at altitude.
But at 100, based on what we talked about earlier, where are we as far as anatomical location?
Who's brave enough?
100.
Where do we see that in the body in the context of what we were just talking about?
Partial pressure of?
Yeah, at the lungs.
So when we're looking over here, this is usually at
the lungs and kind of when it's being delivered to the rest of the body.
Well, what about here?
40.
Well, that's interesting.
I know it says it up there, but where is that?
Closer to the tissues, right?
The venous blood.
So now that kind of gives us a little bit of an idea of how to maybe interpret this graph.
The nice thing about this oxygen hemoglobin dissociation curve is it's sigmoidal.
What we mean by that is there's a really steep portion
here and then there's a flat portion up here.
This is very, very important because the flat portion at
the top allows us to have really big changes in the partial pressure of oxygen
with very small changes in saturation.
So let's say that again.
The flat portion allows us to have really big changes in the partial pressure of oxygen, right?
So I can go from, I don't know, 70 to 110.
This is a really big change in the partial pressure
of oxygen with a very small change in saturation.
And this is really nice for us to be able to
defend against large changes in partial pressure when we go to different altitudes.
So most of you, even though we're at a higher altitude than
sea level, will still be at 99 to 100% saturation, even though you might be dropping down from 104 to 80.
Okay, so the second part of the sigmoidal curve is we have this steep portion here.
That means we'll have small changes in partial pressure
of oxygen with large changes in saturation.
Again, the steep portion of this curve, I can have
small changes in the partial pressure of oxygen and that will result in large changes in the saturation.
Why would I want that?
I want to be as sensitive as possible to a small
disturbance in the partial pressure of oxygen so I can just
dump off as much oxygen as possible any time the cells are utilizing oxygen.
So that's pretty cool the way this hemoglobin oxygen dissociation curve functions.
And ironically enough, or just like what we talked about, this is venous blood.
This is the partial pressure that we're typically experiencing,
this 10 to 20 here, at the mitochondria.
So if we're getting down into this or higher intensity exercise, right, like
so if this is rest here and we're starting to get down
here to exercise, we wanna be able to drop off a lot of oxygen.
We wanna encourage that oxygen to kinda drop off as quickly as possible.
But,
If we're having some issues at the lungs, so in this area
over here, we want to be able to try to defend that
as best as possible and have very small changes in saturation.
We don't want to be offloading oxygen at the lungs.
So we want to have that really flat portion of this dissociation curve.
All right.
How did I do?
Any questions here?
The last piece for this would be, I then can take the area of this curve.
You don't need to do that, right?
We need to rely on calculus and integrals.
But I could take this difference here.
And this is the arterial venous over here.
So arterial venous O2 difference.
What?
The Fick equation?
It's back?
So arterial venous O2 difference is this difference right here.
So during exercise, if the mixed venous VO2 or partial
pressure of oxygen dips down here, well, then I'm going to shade a larger area.
And that indicates that I've now just dropped off more oxygen into the tissues.
It's pretty cool.
All right, so this curve can shift to the right and the left.
These are the three factors that we will start with on Tuesday.
Have a good weekend.