Okay.
Welcome back everyone.
What a great, what a great day, right?
This week is starting to get warmer.
It's pretty nice.
I always like the weather.
Weather's pretty good.
It's a good time of the year.
It's like super cold and it's getting a little warmer.
The days are getting a little longer.
It's a great time.
Great time.
OK.
So on Thursday, we left off talking about fiber typing, so how we have different proteins that,
depending on how they are coded, have different
properties or force-producing properties, and we label them different fiber types.
You know, type 1, type 2a, type 2x.
And then we talked about type 2b.
Do humans express type 2b fibers?
No.
We have the proteins or the genes for them, but we don't actually express some of those genes.
And we typically don't have those proteins as well,
unless you're in some rare instances with muscular dystrophy.
Okay, so today we're gonna basically pick up where we
left off there and talk about force regulation in the muscle.
So we just got done talking about fiber typing,
but then there becomes this little situation where, to be
honest, does fiber typing really matter if everything is being controlled at the neuromuscular level?
So clearly they are different fiber types, but how
we regulate when the muscles actually contract are from neuromuscular activity.
So we're gonna touch into force regulation in muscle.
We'll talk about three major pieces.
We'll start with the first one, which is the type and number of motor units recruited.
So if you recruit more motor units, you are going
to produce a greater force, independent of muscle fiber type, right?
Like if you're just recruiting more muscles in general, you're gonna produce more force.
If you have fast motor units, those typically are
more associated with producing or activating fiber types that have a greater force.
Okay, so if we're talking about motor units and different
types of motor units, let's get into that as well.
So here we have the type S, or the slow motor units.
These are the smallest of the motor neurons, and they typically innervate type I muscle fibers.
Then we move down to type FR,
or fast fatigue resistant.
These are typically innervating the type 2a muscle fibers.
And then lastly would be the type FF, or the fast fatigable.
These are considered the largest of the motor units,
and they typically are innervating the type 2x muscle fibers.
Now this is the only piece where we start to get in
a little bit of a discrepancy or maybe a debate
between the neurophysiology side and the exercise physiology.
If you read a exercise physiology textbook, this is exactly what's
in there, but if you go to the neurophysiology textbook,
They would almost suggest there's no discrimination between the
motor units and the fiber types that they're innervating.
There is a distinction between the slow fast fatigue
resistance and the fast fatigable, but that they innervate an equal proportion of type 1 versus type 2.
We are gonna go off of this particular model just because your textbook is going off of that.
And there's some evidence to suggest that something like this might be happening.
And we'll talk about that in a little bit as well.
So just know that this isn't like,
The end all be all, right?
There are other kind of concepts out there suggesting
that yes, there are these three different types of motor
units, but they're all kind of innervating different fiber types in equal proportions.
Okay, recruitment pattern during graded exercise.
If we have a graded exercise test, what's increasing on the x-axis?
I think I heard it, but.
I can get a few brave volunteers.
What's increasing on the x-axis with the graded exercise test?
Intensity, thank you, thank you.
All right, so if it's increasing with intensity, then we
are doing more work with every kind of grade for that exercise.
So we're gonna start with the type S.
moved to the type FR, so slow, fatigue resistant, and the fast fatigueable.
And that tracks with what we were just talking about with type one all the way to type 2X.
Okay.
We'll touch on Twitch and rate of fatigue in a little
bit, but I wouldn't really worry too much about the distinction in these ones.
Just know
I guess the level of recruitment and typically when you
are recruiting each motor neuron during a graded exercise test, which will be on this next slide here.
So typically the recruitment pattern during graded exercise tests, as I mentioned,
was type one to type two A to type two X. Well
then that would be the S and then the fatigue resistance.
So the slow fatigue resistant and the fast fatigueable.
Keep in mind though, if I am doing maximal exercise or this
exercise in here at 80 to 100%, all of these muscle fibers are being activated.
So if I wanted to produce the most force, it would
make sense to me that I would recruit every single fiber
that I potentially could recruit so I could generate the most amount of force.
It's not that you're at 100% or you're doing a maximal
exercise and only the type 2x fibers are recruiting.
Well, to me, that wouldn't be as advantageous because the type 1 fibers are still producing force.
So at 100% active muscle fibers, all of these are being activated.
This should help with the sizing principle concept, which is this next slide here.
So low force on this x-axis going to high force production,
and low recruitment all the way up to high recruitment.
If I am recruiting,
low or a low number of these motor neurons and the
units that are smaller, then I'm gonna produce a lower force.
But I'm gonna produce the most force if I can activate everything.
But they go on this kind of continuum, this little spectrum.
So progressive recruitment of motor units begins with the
smallest motor units and progresses to larger and larger motor neurons.
Are we OK so far?
Yeah.
But we're still at the high point.
We're still recruiting the small motors.
Yeah, yeah.
Yeah, this is more of a continuum.
So you're moving along this continuum, but it's not like
you're turning off the smaller ones down here.
Yeah.
Good.
Now.
There's one caveat where there is some cycling going on
because obviously you can't have a motor unit continuously firing signals forever.
Eventually it's possible, right?
These motor neurons and the muscle fibers are fatigable, right?
So it will cycle through them, but essentially they're
active all the way throughout if we're trying to produce a very short-term high-intensity bow.
Okay, the relationship between stimulus strength and force of contraction.
If I increase the stimulus strength, then you are also going to increase the force of contraction.
A stronger signal is potentially going to recruit more
muscle fibers, which is going to reduce into more force.
All right.
Let's see how we're doing with this.
And you can think of maybe primarily or a larger quantity.
Is it not on?
So if your clicker wasn't working, it should be good now.
Let's try another 45 seconds or so.
OK, 10 seconds here.
Anyone need a little more time?
OK, I'll close it down in five, three, two, one.
OK, how did we do?
Nice job.
So C is the correct answer.
We typically are not producing a ton of force in the
eye, right, compared to a, if we're looking at the rectus femoris muscle.
So C, slow and the fast fatigable would be the correct answer there.
Okay.
Force regulation in the muscle number two.
The initial muscle length is also going to influence
how much force the muscle can actually produce.
There is an ideal length to be able to produce that force.
And this is inherently behind the concept of the cross-bridge formation.
If I'm in a certain length where I don't have the
maximum number of cross-bridges that are able to form in that given time point,
then you're not gonna be able to produce as much force compared to that optimal overlap.
And you may have seen this length tension relationship
for skeletal muscle, where if you have three different muscle
lengths, and we can think of these as different positions.
So maybe this is one position, this is another position,
and then this is that third position on the end there.
This third position is kind of easy to start with because
if you look at the overlap between the myosin and the actin, it's not very high, right?
Like if I'm all the way extended like this and I try to grab something
and it's pretty heavy and I try to lift it up, it's
gonna be a lot harder than if I start maybe halfway or where I'm having optimal overlap.
This would be the same deal if I start having, if I
start going all the way over and it's like double overlapped and
it's still gonna be a little bit of a problem.
Meaning there's nowhere to really move.
Like I can't really generate any force if I'm starting in this position right here.
Number three, nature of the neural stimulation of the motor units.
This is where we're gonna talk about the frequency of stimulation.
We're gonna touch on a simple twitch summation in tetanus.
Okay.
So the reason why we talk about this is because a
lot of the times they'll pull out a muscle fiber, put it on a force transducer and kind of stimulate it.
And when they stimulate it like that, a lot of times they can get twitches.
But we need to be careful because normal
body movements, they're sustained contractions and they're not really dealing with simple twitches.
But if we can repeatedly activate the muscle, then we
can start getting some results that are more similar to what we deal with with muscular contractions.
So a contraction is the result of a single stimulus.
So if I have a twitch here, there will be some
delay because obviously that signal needs to reach the muscle fibers.
And then you will have a contraction and a relaxation phase.
The muscle contracts and then it relaxes.
If we were to zoom in on this bottom piece right here,
then we can look at the three phases of a muscle twitch.
The first one will be this latent period.
Again, we have to wait for that signal to get to the bottom of the motor end unit.
Then it has to send that signal across the
sarcolemma, down the T-tubule, sarcoplasmic reticulum, cross-bridge, right?
There's some sort of delay there.
It's not instant.
But as soon as that calcium reaches,
opens those sites, and then you have the cross-bridges
that form, you're going to generate a contraction.
Well, eventually, that signal, right, if it was just one simple twitch,
that signal is going to disappear, and then the calcium
is going to be re-uptaked, and then you're going to
have the cross-bridges no longer formed, and then you're going to have relaxation.
But as we start to get multiple twitches, we can see something pretty interesting here.
If I increase the frequency of the stimulus, this results in some summation of those twitches.
So here, on the x-axis, we have the stimuli.
So maybe I'm just stimulating it once, and then there's
some time frame before I stimulate it again.
Once I stimulate it, it produces some force.
If I give it enough time and stimulate it again, when
it's fully relaxed, then it will produce the same force.
And so notice this is the same strength of stimulation,
but if I just decrease the resting period before the next
stimulation, you can actually get them to some on top of each other.
So the stimuli is the same strength of the stimulus,
but the frequency at which I'm applying the stimulus is now increasing.
eventually you will reach something called tetanus.
And that's where it doesn't matter if I increase the
frequency even more, which is down over here compared to here, the force production is the same.
Any ideas as to why this is happening?
Yeah, the cross bridges could be already formed.
What else?
That is a good one.
Anything else?
Which is kind of on to that.
Well, so the motor units wouldn't necessarily be innervated
because I'm just sending a signal down once, right?
Like I send one signal, it sends that signal down to the muscle fiber to contract.
Yeah, and I don't know if that's where you're going to,
but a lot of the time it's because it takes a little
bit of time for the sarcoplasmic reticulum to get all the calcium back out.
But if you send a signal before all the calcium
gets released from the troponin, well then that next signal is gonna be additive.
And so you'll have a little bit of calcium
residue maybe or leftover from the first stimulus, and then
you have another signal and it's gonna push out even more calcium.
So then they're gonna sum on top of each other and produce more force.
So even though the strength of the stimulus was the same,
if you don't let calcium kind of recover or fully recycle
or get back into the sarcoplasmic reticulum, then overall you'll have that build.
But eventually, if you keep stimulating it as fast as
possible, well, there's just going to be all this calcium that you could possibly release.
And that's when you get that tightness.
Any questions here?
All right.
Okay, let's move on then to muscle soreness.
Our last fun topic of muscles.
All right, what do we think about this one?
Maybe I've influenced this, but you could also answer
to what you think maybe the majority believe.
What is the overall sentiment behind lactic acid and soreness?
Okay, we'll close this down in about 10 seconds.
Anyone need more time?
Okay.
All right, three, two, one.
Okay, most people said false here, but,
And I hope this is what you knew coming into this
class and not me influencing it, but that's good.
So right now, it's possible out in the future we could find something new.
But we don't have any evidence to support the claim
that an increase in lactate production will cause muscle soreness.
Any ideas?
And it's pretty much the same concepts that we talk about with a lot of these myths.
But any ideas as to what the problem might be with
this particular claim based on what you know about lactate
production and then maybe even where soreness even occurs?
Yeah, yeah, so one, if I took a lactate sample for
everyone in here, we'd have a baseline lactate concentration.
We don't get sore every day, but then one could
argue, well, it's only during high intensity exercise.
Okay, well, during high intensity exercise, we get lactate to go everywhere.
But it's interesting that we only get sore in one area.
Did someone have a question up there?
And another piece, when you do a high intensity
exercise and you continuously do that same exercise, do you
keep getting the same amount of soreness over and over and over again?
No, I think most people realize, like, if you did a novel bout of exercise, like,
okay, I haven't done any resistance training for five years
or something like that, and I go in there, and I'm just
like, I'm gonna build all the muscle today during this workout, right?
Like, this is the workout that's gonna make everything change.
And you just kinda overdo it a little bit, and then you get really, really sore that day.
But then if you continuously do that exercise, you're not gonna feel the same soreness.
So it's a little interesting that even if you start increasing the power output
and you produce more lactate, you actually start getting less
and less and less sore, if not at all, with repeated exercise.
OK, so then let's look into what is actually happening
with resistance training or any type of muscle damage and then muscle soreness.
So muscle soreness in the exercise physiology community, we
typically call it DOMS or delayed onset muscle soreness.
It typically appears 24 to 48 hours after strenuous exercise.
That's another interesting piece.
We're producing the most amount of lactate during the exercise,
but we feel the most sore after the lactate levels have all dissipated.
So if I were to take a lactate sample before and after exercise and then four days later
or two days later, well, all of those non-exercising lactate
samples are gonna be much lower than when you are actually exercising.
Okay, so what's actually causing this?
This is being caused because there are microscopic tears
in the muscle fibers or connective tissue.
Okay, well that makes sense.
I'm physically disrupting the proteins for those muscle fibers.
Try to remember that eccentric exercises can cause the most damage just
because you usually can deal with higher forces or more
force or more weight when you're doing an eccentric exercise.
So eccentric exercises can cause more damage than a concentric exercise.
So what does this look like?
So here we have some healthy sarcomeres here and then
here we have some sarcomere damage in the center.
And this is happening hours to days after the resistance spout.
Once you get that damage, the immune system responds to that damage.
And here we can see immune cell infiltration here.
And this is also on the magnitude of days.
And then after that, so days to weeks, we see some satellite cell activation.
And that's gonna really help with the repair as well as
the growth of those same fibers to deal with subsequent bouts of exercise.
So we can categorize this muscle injury
between these steps that are outlined in your textbook here.
First, you have some strenuous exercise, which is up here.
Then you get some structural damage to those muscle fibers,
which leads to some sort of membrane damage.
That damage typically includes the sarcoplasmic reticulum, so you see some calcium leaking out.
You get protease activation, and that also results in breakdown of cellular proteins.
What this is basically saying here is there's this
pretty interesting response that once you see the cell damage in those muscle fibers,
You get the immune system to go around and
start activating certain cells to undergo apoptosis, which is self-destruction of the cells.
So not only do you get the damage from the
resistance exercise, your immune system goes through and says, hey,
you need a self-destruct, you need a self-destruct.
And so you get this kind of compounding impact of even further damage.
This inflammatory response, I don't really like the positioning of this one,
this typically is happening throughout this first piece
here, but you get an inflammatory response, you get some swelling and pain.
Eventually, the muscle fibers repair themselves using
resident satellite cells, or myogenic precursor cells, just like what I depicted on the previous slide.
Yes.
Yeah, so I can't really speak on why that might
feel better because that might be personal preference, but if you can increase blood flow to the area
and help clear out some of the pieces that are
being damaged here, that potentially can make an individual feel a little bit better.
Yeah, so it depends on what you're trying to achieve, but if I'm trying to increase blood flow,
right, that circulation, then that's always going to potentially
improve the ability to clear out some of the waste products.
The one problem with this idea of waste products is
people usually thought lactate was a waste product, but it's not.
And we'll touch on to a few of those things.
I think a few of these slides might answer those questions as well.
Yeah.
Yes.
Yes, they are.
And we'll get into that, too.
It's that repeated dot effect.
So I'm sorry.
I didn't hear you.
Is this like, is DOMs related to like injury, or is it related to like temperature?
Well, so DOMS is the injury, and then eventually you get the hypertrophy.
Okay, so what is a typical study designed to do this?
Because we can induce muscle damage quite easily, right?
We can have individuals perform some really tough eccentric
tasks over and over and over again until we induce some type of muscle damage.
Don't worry about the study design in itself here.
You would never be tested on this, but it's nice to see how
maybe complex some of these relatively simple ideas become when designing a study.
But when we are getting some blood samples and
you do pre-exercise, you do pre-exercise measurements and
then post-exercise measurements, and then you look at it maybe 24 to seven days post, let's look and see
what we find from these results.
Okay, no surprise.
Compared to baseline and before exercise, the soreness rating is significantly lower
than after exercise, and it typically is the highest as far
as how I feel sore 24 to 48 hours after the exercise bell.
If you are sore,
It's also, you probably noticed, your range of motion changes.
So your range of motion is probably the highest before you exercise.
And then you probably can't extend too much before you
kind of experience some sort of tension or pain.
And so your range of motion decreases.
But as time goes on, you start to recover with that range of motion.
I think we've all kind of felt this in the past before.
No, it's on a physical level.
So if I do a bunch of curls and then I get
sore, it's going to be really hard to fully extend here.
So the range of motion will be this angle, this joint angle.
Is that OK?
Yeah.
This isn't super related, but is this the same process as
when you get a vaccine in the next day or more?
Well, a little bit, yeah.
So if you induce muscle damage in any way possible, those same steps occur, right?
they'll need to clear those waste products from the acute damage in itself.
And then eventually the immune system goes in and activates apoptosis around the area.
And then yes, you do get a little sore from any muscle damage.
Okay, limb circumference, no surprise here.
You get that swelling and edema, so the limb circumference gets a little bit bigger, right?
We're not getting all swole because all of a
sudden you're building muscle fibers here immediately, right?
It's more because you're getting that increase in blood flow.
Okay, and then force production.
This is the one piece where people kind of don't realize what's going on.
It makes sense now that we're talking about it.
If I straight destroyed a percentage of your muscle fibers,
would you be able to generate the same amount of force?
No, and that is what we're seeing here.
So we have force production here, the highest before
that exercise, but after the exercise, you're getting a decrease
in the force and slowly you're bringing this back up.
The reason why this is so important is because we
need to be careful about the subsequent exercise bouts we do after this.
Because typically, if you have this muscle fiber damage and
you're not able to generate the same amount of force and then
I apply the same amount of weight, you are now risking
yourself or putting yourself at risk for injury, right?
Like if I can't sustain that exercise, maybe my form
changes because I'm trying to get that same amount of weight up.
Or if I'm doing some type of repetitive task, the form
kind of deteriorates and maybe I get some tendon damage or I get an overuse injury.
So we need to be really careful with this piece
because if you are experiencing soreness, you are having a
loss in force production that could potentially put individuals at risk for injury.
And the one thing you don't really wanna do if
you're really going on a long-term training exercise bout, or
if you're an elite athlete, is you don't wanna go seven days with a decrease in exercise kind of intensity.
And it's fine to cycle on and off, but we need to be really careful about this.
And so not always is soreness a good thing, right?
And we can avoid this whole process.
Okay, and the last piece here, this is nice, right?
How do I actually know that the muscle fibers are being damaged?
So this is plasma creatine kinase activity.
Baseline, pre-exercise, post-exercise, even 24 hours are still relatively low.
And then we get this big spike.
So what is that telling me?
First, we need to figure out what is creatine kinase?
What is it?
What does it do?
And where do we find it?
Help me out.
Yeah, phosphorylates creatine, right?
Like it's basically allowing us to undergo that immediate energy pathway, the PCR ATP pathway.
Well, we store the majority of our creatine in our
muscle fibers and we undergo this process in the muscle fibers.
So then it would make sense that that enzyme is also in the muscle fibers.
So if I take a blood sample and then all of a sudden
I see a spike in this enzyme, what is that telling me?
It's usually in the muscle fibers, now it's not.
It's flowing kind of everywhere in the blood.
What's the only way it can get out?
Well, maybe not too much, but if the muscle, yeah.
Yeah, muscles rupture, right?
The membranes are rupturing and you're releasing all this creatine kinase out.
Creatine kinase isn't the only one.
Myoglobin is another one.
You get these proteins that are only found in muscle fibers.
And you might think like, ah, I don't care about this.
Well, maybe.
Most of you might go into future health care professions.
The first thing people do in the hospital, especially in
the emergency room when they take a blood sample, is they run these.
If they see these levels high, that indicates muscle damage.
Well yeah, that could be soreness, but what else could it be?
Heart attack.
If you have damage in the heart, you will have
an increased level of myoglobin and creatine kinase.
These are standard panels in the emergency room.
they will look at it and say, okay, this is going
to increase the probability that they may have had a heart attack.
They'll do some background, hey, been going to CrossFit lifting a ton of weights?
No, okay.
Well, the only place they're gonna have this damage,
especially if they've been having chest pain or anxiety or any
other problems, this is a good little sign that is telling
us, okay, let's do some further testing because it's probable that they had a heart attack.
So it's nice to kind of piece these things together, especially in future healthcare professions.
Right, so we know these kind of are recurring inside of the muscle.
Okay, so muscle excitation, contraction, and relaxation.
We already know about this piece.
We've talked about it.
This whole thing is here.
This includes the motor end unit, the sarcolemma,
and the sarcomeres themselves, sarcoplasmic reticulum with the calcium.
What is causing this loss in strength?
Well, it should make sense that something is being disrupted over here.
but it's not all the same.
And so this figure does a really, really good job
at looking into this kind of EC complex specifically.
Okay, so there is a strength loss immediately after
this high intensity bout that's causing some sort of muscle damage.
The majority of the strength loss is coming from EC coupling failure.
a relatively small proportion is coming from physical disruption.
Then you get this increase in contractile protein loss.
So if you remember, this is a little weird, right?
We get a decrease in the physical disruption protein
loss, but an increase in the contractile protein three days after injury.
The change between the physical disruption in doing the
exercise and the contractile protein is the evidence of that apoptosis that we looked at.
You have the physical disruption, and then a few days later, because of the immune response,
your immune cells are just going in, and they're just
like, nope, you're going away, you're going away, you're going away.
And so you're getting this really large increase in contractile protein loss days afterwards.
the EC coupling failure is going to subside.
And then 14 to 28 days later, you're having that contractile protein loss.
This makes sense to me, right?
It's not immediate that you're gonna be able to recover and experience hypertrophy.
It's going to take a little bit of time.
The next question would be, will these pieces make sense, right?
If I have physical disruption in the contractile proteins, that causes a loss in strength.
Where are we actually losing the ability to sustain a contraction from the EC coupling failure?
Well, they tested multiple different sites, and it seems
like the signal from the alpha motor neuron to
the sarcolemma, right, acetylcholine binding onto those receptors, are OK.
OK, that's not the place where the EC coupling failure is.
Do the signals then propagate down the T-tubule, and they say yes, they're OK.
What about the ability for, I guess, the thick and thin filaments or the cross-bridges to form?
It looks like that's okay.
Where they're not sure, they're thinking it's between the
signal that gets to the T-tubule for some reason is not
able to send that signal to the sarcoplasmic reticulum.
Everything's functioning okay, but for some reason,
it appears that the signal transmission from T-tubule
to sarcoplasmic reticulum is not really getting across.
And so therefore, the calcium is not being released.
So this is where we believe the mechanism or the actual
failure site is when we're dealing with EC coupling failure.
Pretty cool.
Okay, so now you're sore, you dealt with that pain,
and then eventually you're gonna go back and do the same exercise bow.
We call the ability to do the same exercise bow and
not experience the same amount of soreness as the repeated bowed effect.
So it's a bout of unfamiliar exercise that results
in the delayed onset muscle soreness, but following recovery, another
bout of the same exercise results in minimal injury.
So you have that initial bout of exercise, you get the muscle damage,
and then you get some adaptations that are multiple theories
here, and then this repeated bout of exercise is going to cause less muscle damage.
So then just like what I was mentioning before, to me, if I wanna avoid all the strength loss,
avoid the structural protein damage that lasts up to 21
plus days, that's a really long time, right, to be dealing with the strength loss.
If my overall goal is to continue to progress in,
if I'm doing a resistance training program, strength gains.
So then,
The recommendation is that you should slowly begin a
specific exercise over five to 10 training sessions to avoid delayed onset muscle soreness.
So we wanna do submaximal kind of eccentric exercises over kind of multiple days
and not try to go to the extreme and build your way
or ease your way into it before you start adding on a ton of weight.
or whatever program it is, right?
You don't want to just go off and start doing downhill
running right off the bat if you're not an experienced runner.
Because downhill running is primarily eccentric.
That's why I mentioned that.
OK, some of you are like, no, no pain, no gain.
True or false?
Okay, let's go 20 more seconds on this one.
Double check you have something in.
10 seconds here.
I think we're missing four clickers, three clickers.
All right, I'll close this down in three, two, one.
I'm just curious what people said,
OK, so some people are like, all right, yeah, no pain, no gain.
You have to feel the burn.
You have to feel the pain.
And you need the soreness.
Well, we need to be careful.
Because if you overdo it, does anyone know the
risks, especially with muscle damage, what the risks are here?
Yeah, it's pretty bad, right?
You can get something called rhabdomyolysis.
And this occurs when there is excessive muscle tissue damage.
And with that damage, you are releasing a lot of
things that should not be released into your blood at a fast rate, right?
Like creatine kinase, myoglobin, all those things we talked
about, and actin, myosin, all of those things we don't really want inside of the blood.
If you do that, the initial muscle damage bout then
starts to activate the immune system and then you get an even larger response, right?
And so this can really exponentially become a problem
very quickly because your body doesn't really know what's going on.
It's trying to clear all these problems and then all
of a sudden it's going in there inducing apoptosis.
And so the kind of
The problem is now you're forcing the kidneys to deal
with all of this excess protein and electrolyte kind of dispersion
into the blood and it causes a lot of problems in the kidneys.
If you have rhabdomyolysis, especially in a severe kind
of condition, you will find those red blood cells in your blood.
You are overworking your kidneys, and your kidneys have a really hard time dealing with it.
So you definitely don't want this.
If you're seeing this type of color in your
urine, that's probably an indication you should probably seek
some medical attention as quickly as possible.
So what's the story here?
Moderation is key, right?
Like, we need to be really careful.
It's this whole idea, like, too little?
No, that's probably not good.
Too much?
Yes, that's also a really big problem, right?
There's always something in the middle where we're achieving probably the most optimal results.
Okay, so the next time you're in the gym, you can think of this figure here.
Okay, any questions on
Muscle soreness, damage, repeated bout effect.
Okay.
If not, then we will move on to chapter nine, circulatory response to exercise.
So up to this point, we've kind of outlined a few things.
We've talked about work and power.
We talked about energy production and how important it is
to get oxygen from the outside into our body and then what
happens at our cells as far as how we're generating oxygen or ATP with and without oxygen.
But now we need to think about, well, how do we get the blood from our heart
to our muscles.
So this is the circulatory system.
and the response to exercise.
The body has to deliver more blood to those tissues.
So we're going to talk about an overall organization of the circulatory system,
hemodynamics, which is basically how blood is kind
of moving around, cardiac cycle, cardiac output, changes in
oxygen delivery to muscle during exercise, the circulatory responses to exercise,
And then the regulation of cardiovascular adjustments to exercise.
So these are kind of the topics we're going to touch on chapter nine.
OK, so we're going to start easy here.
Organization of the circulatory system.
Well, the circulatory system works very closely with the pulmonary system.
which is pretty much your lungs, right?
The lungs have to bring the oxygen in from the outside
and then deliver it to basically the heart so then the heart can pump it to the rest of the body.
So the purpose of the cardio respiratory system, so the heart and the lungs,
would be to transport oxygen nutrients to the tissues and
then remove CO2 and waste products from the tissues.
What we often forget about the circulatory system is
it's also extremely important in the regulation of core body temperature.
The movement of blood and the dissipation in different regions
of the body can really only happen if the circulatory system
is working together to send the blood to different areas.
So you can think of it as like
cooling system or air conditioner inside of the body.
It needs to redirect some of that warmer blood flow so it can dissipate it to the skin.
There are two major adjustments of blood flow during exercise.
We have one, an increase in cardiac output, and
two, the redistribution of blood flow from inactive to active muscles
or to the skin, which is this bottom piece here, thermoregulation.
OK, here's the structure of the heart.
You definitely don't need to memorize all these structures.
It's nice to know that we have ventricles and atriums.
And separating those, we have valves.
I highlight these four here, only because sometimes you'll hear
us talk about the names of these valves.
And so you can go back and reference
where they actually are.
So if I say the aortic semilunar valve, you know
if it's referencing this valve here that is pretty much the opening from that ventricle to the aorta.
OK.
So we have the pulmonary circuit, which is the right side of the heart.
It pumps deoxygenated blood to the lungs via the
pulmonary arteries, returns oxygenated blood to the left side of the heart via pulmonary veins.
It's basically this piece right here, pulmonary circuit.
Then we have the systemic circuit, or kind of the rest of the body.
This is the left side of the heart, and that's going
to pump oxygenated blood to the whole body via the
arteries and returns deoxygenated blood to the right side of the heart via veins.
So that's this, right?
Pumping oxygenated blood out to the rest of the body so we can deliver that oxygen.
And then the veins are going to return the deoxygenated blood to the right side of the heart.
So then you can then pump that blood to the lungs and repeat the process.
Hopefully we're all already familiar with this.
OK, so we'll move on to hemodynamics.
But before we can look at hemodynamics, we need to understand the components of blood.
So the physical characteristics of blood are easily distinguished
when we can centrifuge a blood sample.
If we were to take a blood sample and then centrifuge
it, you will see some separation in the blood.
The majority of your blood is kind of this
fluid that's free of any cells, and that's the plasma here.
You then get this white buffy coat that contains platelets,
white blood cells, some kind of immune cells.
And then down here, you get this red cell volume where it contains packed red blood cells.
And inside those red blood cells, we have the hemoglobin molecules.
In order to get hematocrit, we typically do the height of
the red blood cells divided by the total height here to get a fraction.
So again, plasma's liquid portion of the blood contains
ions, proteins, hormones, cells, red blood cells, white blood cells, and platelets.
Okay, so why do we care about hematocrit?
Hematocrit is a percentage of blood that is composed of packed red blood cells.
The average hematocrit for college age males is 42% and females is 38.
It's nice to know
because if we have a decrease in plasma volume or
an increase in red cell volume, the hematocrit could increase,
and that would change the viscosity of blood.
If you change the viscosity of blood, that's gonna change
flow, and we'll talk about that a little bit later.
It's also good, just like I mentioned, that hematocrit is highly dependent on fluid status.
you can have an individual who is anemic, where their hematocrit is lower than normal.
And so we would say in this instance, this individual
maybe needs iron or something else to help red blood cell production.
But you could imagine that I could probably get to this same point
and then decrease plasma volume here, so maybe dehydration,
and still get a hematocrit value that looks normal.
So we need to just be really careful because just because
you have a high or a low hematocrit for one particular blood
sample does not mean we know for sure what's going on.
Because polycythemia here, we have hematocrit over 70%, and dehydration is 70%.
So I don't know whether this increase in hematocrit is due
to a loss in plasma volume or an increase in red blood cell production.
And that's why they always recommend, along with fasting, but
just, hey, when you come in and do this blood draw, make sure you're hydrated normally.
You're not over hydrating or under hydrating.
You're just normal, and you come in for this blood draw with the best normal baseline possible.
Because you can imagine someone coming in who actually
is anemic, but they're dehydrated, and then now the physician's like, no, you're good.
Everything's normal here.
And you just need to be careful with that.
OK, blood flow.
Blood flow is directly proportional to the pressure difference between the two ends of the system.
The only way inside of the body you can get blood to move
from point A to point B is if you move the blood from high pressure to low pressure.
the way you create that pressure is the heart contracts,
and now you have an increase in pressure right at the
aorta, and a decrease in pressure wherever the blood is going.
So that is this change in pressure.
It is inversely proportional to the resistance, meaning as
resistance goes down, we have an increase in blood flow.
If you remember, resistance is a pretty complicated, it's not
that complicated, but it has a lot of other pieces to it.
There's a constant, you multiply it by length, divide it
by, or multiply it by the viscosity and then you divide it by the radius to the fourth power.
So if it's radius to the fourth power, the major factor that is influencing resistance is radius.
So vasoconstriction, vasodilation is going to be a big piece for this resistance.
So yes, length does matter.
Viscosity does matter.
But resistance, small changes to resistance is gonna have
large impacts to, sorry, small changes in radius is gonna have a large change in resistance.
Because it's radius to the fourth power.
Okay, pressure.
Just like I mentioned, just a change in pressure.
We have low pressure in the veins and high pressure in the arteries.
Because of that, it's very easy to move blood from the arteries to the veins.
It then becomes a little bit of a problem to move blood from the veins back to the heart,
but we'll touch on some cool characteristics or some strategies
the body kind of undertakes to get that blood back to the heart.
Okay, the cardiac cycle.
We have two major cycles.
We have diastole, which is the relaxation period, and
then we have systole, which is the contraction period, or the contraction phase.
So diastole, or the relaxation period, is when pressure in the ventricles is low.
The pressure's low in the ventricles when the ventricles are relaxing or the heart is relaxing.
Because the pressure is low in the ventricles and blood
is kinda coming back in to the atrium, they are filling the ventricles.
So you get blood filling from the atria, the mitral
and the tricuspid valves open when ventricle pressure is lower than atrial pressure.
So that's what these P's are indicating, pressure here.
Okay, during contraction, so the heart contracts, pressure in the ventricles rise.
But the blood doesn't leave just because the pressure rises.
It has to overcome or open the aortic and pulmonary valves.
That only happens, again, when ventricular pressure is greater than aortic pressure.
Once those valves open, blood leaves and it goes to the pulmonary and systemic circuit.
Okay, if we can combine these two, the cardiac cycle with
these two phases, we know that at rest, diastole is longer than systole.
It's about kind of one third to two thirds, meaning we
spend about 66% of the time in diastole, one third of the time in systole at rest.
As soon as we start exercising, we get the heart to beat faster.
Both systole and diastole are shorter, but we typically spend
a little bit more time in systole than diastole.
But it's closer to a 50-50 as opposed to a 33-66.
OK, any questions here?
So this will come into play, especially in lab, when
you start doing the formulas to calculate mean RTL pressure.
So you'll see like 1 third.
If you ever wonder where that 1 third comes from, well, that's this.
Okay, so the relationship among pressure and volume during
the cardiac cycle can be represented pretty well from this
kind of pressure-volume loop in the Wiger's diagram, which we'll go over.
In this instance, if we have the mitral valve closing,
You now have an increase in pressure from the left ventricle.
So we're just looking at left ventricular pressure here.
The pressure goes up, but no volume is changing inside
of the ventricle until the valve opens, which is at this point.
Pressure continues to go up.
But then the pressure from the outside is exceeding the inside.
So then the semilunar valve closes.
So the aortic valve closes.
The pressure decreases because now you're in relaxation.
Kind of the ventricle relaxes.
The mitral valve then opens.
And then we move on through here.
And you can see the volume changes here.
When we have the most amount of volume in the ventricles,
we call that, at least in this frame here, N-diastolic volume.
After systole, so after contraction, we have the N-systolic volume.
And that makes sense that after contraction, there's less volume inside of the ventricles.
This is another artist rendering.
If this doesn't kind of sit well with you, don't worry.
There are many other different figures that you can look at here.
But here, we're filling up the ventricle, so that's the end diastolic volume.
You undergo contraction.
And now, inside the ventricle, there's less blood.
Where did all that blood go?
Well, that goes out into the blood vessels, and we
call that volume that left the heart stroke volume.
So N-diastolic minus N-systolic gives me stroke volume here.
Wigger's diagram.
I believe you all have already seen this and memorized
this and done a really great job in physiology.
we are not gonna use the Wiger's diagram here in XFIS.
We're still gonna deal with this concept, but we're
not gonna, don't worry about the Wiger's diagram.
We're actually gonna use something called the left ventricular pressure volume loop.
And this tracks the same way as the Wiger's diagram.
It puts the pressure and the volume into one graph.
And so it makes it a lot easier to deal with.
The key thing that you want to remember about the pressure
volume loop is you are moving kind of right to left.
So I'll restart this here.
So even though you're going left to right over here, this
is going up, up, left, left, down, down, down, and then to the right.
So this is the direction of the pressure volume loop.
right, this counterclockwise movement.
So I would draw arrows making sure you know the direction of everything here.
On the X axis we have left ventricular volume.
On the Y axis you have left ventricular pressure.
So volume over pressure.
So I'll play that one more time just so you know, just
because it is a point of confusion as far as direction.
OK.
I think this might be a decent place to stop here.
We'll start with kind of filling this box in on Thursday.
Enjoy the rest of your day.
Let me know if you have any questions.