All right, let's get started here.
What a great day today, right?
It's like some of my, I guess, favorite days of the year or favorite time of the year.
The days are getting a little bit longer, there's more light out, it's warmer.
Such a good time, right, when some of you are graduating.
It's a good semester.
Okay, so today we're gonna finish up hormonal responses to exercise.
We finished up the kind of impact of the hormonal
responses during exercise and how that impacts substrate utilization in particular carbohydrates.
And then today we're going to move on to the fats.
But really quick before we do that,
We kind of have five or I guess four hormones if you kind of combine two of them.
But as exercise intensity goes up and as duration gets longer, which hormones increase?
Who wants to help me out with that?
Yeah, catecholamines.
Yeah, norepinephrine, epinephrine.
So we have those catecholamines.
What else?
Yeah, everything except for insulin.
So let's just add a curiosity, because we had the catecholamines.
Someone else mentioned something else or had their hand up?
Cortisol.
That's another one.
So we have three of them now.
Growth hormone.
Say again?
We'll get into that in a little bit, but that's not one of the ones we touched on.
Glucagon, good, nice.
So we had those four hormones, or I guess five hormones
going up, and then insulin goes down in both of those situations.
And we kind of looked at the impact of what
those increasing and decreasing hormone do on carbohydrate metabolism.
Let's look and see how they're impacting fat metabolism.
So just to make sure we're on the same page,
what happens to fat utilization during prolonged submaximal exercise?
Anyone wanna help me out with that?
Yeah.
Say again?
Increases, nice.
So as fat utilization, or as exercise starts to increase
in duration, we increase in the fat utilization.
and decrease in the carbohydrate utilization.
Okay, what about during graded exercise?
So as exercise intensity increases, what happens to fat utilization?
You sure?
Up, down?
I'm just kidding.
Decreases, yeah, yeah, you gotta be confident.
Decreases.
So now that we kind of have this picture in the
back of our mind, we can start applying these concepts as
far as how do hormones impact these two things here.
Okay.
So fat metabolism.
Free fatty acid mobilization and fat metabolism is critical to endurance exercise performance.
As glycogen becomes more and more depleted,
we need to rely on our kind of unlimited energy source, which is fat or triglycerides.
If we are dealing with endurance performance, typically we're
thinking more in the realm or context of longer duration.
And so our body here,
responds by increasing the hormones that are going to help accelerate the breakdown effect.
And again, that term is lipolysis.
Just as a reminder, we go from triglycerides to free fatty acids and the glycerol.
The glycerol, we don't really use in energy kind of production.
So we just focus on the free fatty acids.
The free fatty acids that need to be transported to the muscle.
And then once we get to the muscle, how do we break down these free fatty acids?
Does anyone remember that term?
Well, so lipolysis gets us from triglycerides to free fatty acids.
So I like that.
Beta oxidation.
So we undergo those multiple turns of beta oxidation.
And then we free up.
It's not on here.
The beta oxidation results in what?
What molecules do we get from there?
The exam is next week.
Acetyl-CoA, good.
And then acetyl-CoA enters the Krebs cycle.
You go through that process, get the NADH, FADH, so you can get ATP.
So that's this piece here.
Any questions on that?
OK.
So.
If we start back towards the top, lipolysis or that
breakdown of the triglyceride to the free fatty acid is stimulated
by these kind of four or I guess five if you are separating these two.
So growth hormone, epinephrine, cortisol, and glucagon.
One thing to note here, insulin is an interesting hormone when it comes to lipolysis.
If you have a higher concentration of insulin or you
just have insulin present at all, insulin is actually a potent or a very strong inhibitor of lipolysis.
So if you decrease the concentration of insulin, then you increase lipolysis.
So insulin is a potent inhibitor of lipolysis.
So by removing insulin or decreasing insulin, you actually increase lipolysis.
So that's what this decreased is here.
That's going to be a little important, especially when we talk about nutrition and feeding.
Because typically when I eat something, what happens to insulin?
Spikes, right?
If you increase blood sugar, you kind of spite the insulin.
OK.
So same, I guess, format as what we have done in
the past with carbohydrates, but I'm gonna move a little
bit faster through here because again, it's the same picture.
If I have growth hormone and it is stimulating lipolysis,
we are acting on the adipose tissue to free up these
free fatty acids, glycerol too, but we're really more kind of concerned about these free fatty acids.
Catecholamines also stimulate lipolysis, so it's gonna target
the adipose tissue, increase free fatty acid production.
Cortisol is doing the same thing here in the adipose tissue.
And of course, glucagon doesn't wanna be left out of
the party, so glucagon's gonna meet everyone at the adipose
tissue and also help break down triglycerides to free up these free fatty acids.
Are we okay there?
So then let's talk about this.
If all of these hormones are going up as
exercise intensity increases, and then insulin's going down, why do we see the crossover concept?
Everything we just talked about right now, exercise
intensity increases, these five hormones go up, or four,
again, catecholamines, those five hormones are going up.
I just told you all five of those are going to
stimulate lipolysis, free up free fatty acids, and allow us to use those for substrate utilization.
But we don't see that, right?
we see a decrease in the fat utilization.
So without looking too far ahead on the slides, can anyone try to help me out with this?
Any thoughts, or maybe, yeah, anyone help me out with this?
I didn't wanna spend too much time on this.
Just because we're gonna go over it.
Maybe some similar concepts of what we talked about with carbohydrates.
Say again, decrease.
Yeah, yeah, so that's one of the bigger factors, right?
We're gonna talk about a few more.
One of the biggest factors is as I increase in
exercise intensity, I need to redirect blood flow to the muscles.
That is taking blood away from the adipose tissue.
You could secrete all these hormones that you want, if
they don't have a mailbox to get into, they're not going to be able to send that signal.
Okay, so that's one, we'll get into, there are a few other cool ones.
Just as a reminder, free fatty acid mobilization does depend on hormone-sensitive lipase.
This is not the only one.
We usually categorize them as lipases, but this is a very important one.
Please do not worry about these mechanisms here.
Basically, it's saying a hormone binds to a receptor,
causes some secondary messenger systems or some G protein-linked activation here.
You're gonna break down triglycerides into free fatty acids.
We just already talked about that, so don't worry about these details here.
What we do wanna focus on are the factors that are impairing free fatty acid mobilization.
We're gonna talk about four of them.
Number one.
Elevated hydrogen concentration inhibits hormone-sensitive lipase.
Well, if I just showed you that hormone-sensitive lipase
is extremely important in breaking down triglycerides, but I
then inhibit that lipase or that enzyme, well, now I'm gonna
have a harder time freeing up free fatty acids.
Number two, high levels of lactic acid or lactate
promotes the resynthesis of triglycerides.
So if we're looking at figure B down here on the left with this green circle,
here I have lactate entering in the adipose tissue, and
because of that, you have an interaction that actually helps the formation of triglycerides.
So it's going reverse of what we really want as far as mobilizing free fatty acids.
Here, if you're looking at these, some of these interactions with these hormones,
but this one in particular, right, so the hormones are gonna increase hormone-sensitive lipase,
but we also have this funny little ion over here, so
we have this hydrogen that has this negative sign here, and the negative sign is implying inhibiting.
So it's inhibiting this hormone-sensitive lipase, so it's preventing this arrow from occurring.
And when we get into respiratory physiology, we know that
as we get to higher intensity exercise, we actually produce quite
a bit or a lot of hydrogen ions, especially due to the bicarb buffering.
So these hydrogen ions are gonna outweigh some of
the impact of the other hormones on hormone-sensitive lipase.
On the right here,
So this isn't enough, right?
I can't just say lactate goes here.
Let's do an experiment.
So on the right here for this figure A, on the x-axis, they have lactic acid or lactate.
And then on the y-axis, they have free fatty acids.
And as far as the y goes, you can think of it as mobilization, right?
The more free fatty acids you have, the more
you're breaking down triglycerides, the less you're breaking down triglycerides.
First, let's look at the blue.
The blue is exercise.
As we exercise, we produce more lactate.
And it looks like that trend's going down.
But then someone can say, well, what if there's
something else going on in exercise producing lactic acid or lactate, right?
Or what if something else is causing the free fatty acid to go down besides lactate?
Well, look at this.
They did a really cool experiment where they actually infused lactate without any exercise.
They even got concentrations twice as high as what
someone experienced at the highest intensity exercise.
And even down here, we saw even further of a decrease
in these free fatty acid levels in the blood.
So from this experiment, they pretty much identified some mechanisms,
but they have kind of gave us this information of this
piece here, where we are not producing as many free fatty acids inside of the body.
If anything, we are producing more triglycerides, or we
are encouraging the formation of those triglycerides.
It's pretty cool.
OK.
We doing okay on factors one and two?
All right, let's go to three and four.
Three, inadequate blood flow to the adipose tissue, which one of your classmates had mentioned.
And then number four, if I, let's just theoretically say
I release all the free fatty acids from the triglycerides, well,
We still cannot go against the fact that these free fatty acids are hydrophilic, right?
They don't like water, and so they need some sort of
transport or protein to get it down to the muscle.
If I don't have enough albumin to transport the free fatty acids in the plasma,
well, then that's gonna be a really big problem when
we're trying to use free fatty acids for energy production.
And because of that, we see this trend here, where
as we increase in exercise intensity, we see free fatty acid mobilization and utilization go down.
This is in addition to what we talked about before.
where it just takes much longer.
So the amount of energy we can generate per second from fats is much slower.
And the RER concept, where the caloric equivalent is much lower in fats.
So now we kind of have a good database of mechanisms that are explaining this decrease here.
If there are no questions then we can move on
from substrate utilization and get into plasma volume during exercise.
Okay, just as a reminder, because I know for some of
you it might have been a little bit since you've had physiology,
but if I take a blood sample, a venous blood sample from you,
you would see whole blood, and then I put that in
a centrifuge, spin it down, you eventually will get a solution that looks like this.
You'll have blood, that white, buffy coat, which will
have the platelets, white blood cells, and then you would have your plasma here.
So during exercise, we see decreases in plasma volume.
Yes, blood volume also goes down, but we're actually not losing the red blood cells.
We're losing this plasma here.
One of the biggest kind of drivers in that decrease in
plasma volume is due to this increase in hydrostatic pressure and tissue osmotic pressure.
Now, I know they have this in physiology.
So can someone explain to me what this is?
What's hydrostatic pressure and tissue osmotic pressure?
I know it's going way back to physiology, but.
Is it hydrostatic pressure?
I think it's like the pressure of the blood, again,
Yeah, yeah, so it's the pressure of the blood itself
against the epithelial cells and the blood vessels.
You can think of it if I have a balloon and I
just squeeze on that balloon and the water's kind of expanding the balloon, that's that hydrostatic pressure.
It's the actual pressure of the water itself exerting on the blood vessel walls.
Okay, what about osmotic pressure?
Whoa, haven't heard that word in a while.
Osmotic pressure.
Any ideas?
Yeah.
Yeah, yeah, it's basically, you notice the word, it's very close to osmosis.
Water likes to move from high concentration, right, from low concentration to high concentration.
So typically you have an imbalance in the number of
ions and molecules in your blood versus the interstitial fluid.
And so water kind of seeps out in that manner.
Both of these things kind of change as we exercise and we lose some plasma volume.
Sweating, this one's a little controversial.
So I know the idea is that we always lose plasma volume or blood volume from sweating.
That might not be the most accurate statement.
We lose a lot of total body water, but
because of this hydrostatic pressure tissue, osmotic pressure, sometimes
we can kind of protect it a little bit.
So total body water changes for sure.
If I hadn't put an asterisk on one of these three, you'd be on this sweating piece.
And then the last one is heat strain and decrease in blood pressure.
So these two kind of go hand in hand here.
Okay, so we don't want that decrease in plasma volume.
If we decrease plasma volume or blood volume, we're getting
a decrease in the cardiac output or the stroke volume.
If I decrease stroke volume from the Fick equation, what else goes down?
Or how about what is the Fick equation?
Yeah, stroke volume times heart rate equals cardiac output times what?
So close.
That gets into mean RTL pressure, but we're looking more
on the AVO2 difference, which gives us VO2 max.
Right.
So for reducing the amount of blood flow that's being pumped
out of the heart or blood in the body, then we're reducing
the amount of blood that's kind of being pumped out of the heart.
And so we don't want this drop in plasma volume because
we want to be able to deliver more oxygen to the tissues, especially during exercise.
So hormones then can correct this fluid imbalance.
Let's start with the first hormone vasopressin.
Sometimes we call this antidiuretic hormone or AVP arginine vasopressin.
You basically really just kinda need to focus on in
the hypothalamus we are sending some type of signal to the
brain which then causes the release of this hormone.
This signal in the brain is typically a drop in plasma volume.
Yes, you have some other ones like drop in blood pressure and things like that.
But essentially, you're sending that signal to the hypothalamus.
Don't worry about all these steps here.
And of course, these are accessory organs for other hormones.
So drop in mean arterial pressure, drop in blood volume
is going to cause the release of this hormone, vasopressin,
and then hopefully we're gonna get this water retention or reabsorption
in the kidneys, and we can get this conservation of blood volume.
Okay, so what is the mechanism?
What do these hormones actually target?
Which cells do they target?
And in particular, they are targeting some cells in the kidney.
So vasopression is enhancing water reabsorption by the kidneys.
So we've already kind of filtered this out, and then we're gonna reabsorb that water back in.
It's a pretty cool way that vasopressin does this.
So we have this vasopressin, or anti-diuretic hormone, that's what it's labeled right here.
It's gonna bind on this receptor.
This receptor is gonna cause some type of signaling
cascade, which is gonna result in the translocation of these water transporters.
They are called aquaporin.
So these specialized transporters called aquaporin allow for the
movement of water from one area to the other.
So again, vasopressin or anti-diuretic hormone is targeting cells
in the kidney to cause the aquaporin to allow for reabsorption of water back into the bloodstream.
Any questions here?
During acute created exercise, no surprise, as we increase
in exercise intensity, we see a large increase in the secretion or the concentration of vasopressin.
Okay, hormone number two, aldosterone.
Aldosterone is secreted in the adrenal glands or from the adrenal glands.
It is also produced in response to a drop in blood volume.
That drop in blood volume causes the release of aldosterone
and then eventually we are gonna try to increase this plasma volume and blood volume.
Okay, how is it doing it?
Also targeting cells in the kidney.
But aldosterone is a little different than antidiuretic hormone.
Instead of causing the translocation of these aquaporin
transporters, it actually increases the uptake of sodium.
If I move a bunch of sodium across the membrane,
the osmotic pressure inside of this interstitial fluid in the blood start to increase.
Well, water's gonna follow that change or that increase
in osmotic pressure, and you have that movement of water osmosis.
Similarly, with acute
Graded exercise, so as exercise intensity increases, we get a large increase in aldosterone.
So if I were to summarize this during high intensity
exercise as well as duration, I get aldosterone and antidiuretic hormone increases.
Both of those hormones are gonna increase the retention or kind of the reabsorption of water.
But they do it in two different ways.
Antidiuretic hormone does it by aquapor.
And then aldosterone is doing it by sodium kind of reabsorption and osmosis that way.
Okay.
Ultimately, these hormones going up during exercise, what is the goal again?
What are we trying to increase?
Plasma volume.
So during exercise, when we see the highest concentration
of these two hormones, what should we expect to see
again with exercise as duration increases in plasma volume?
It should go, if I have a high concentration of
aldosterone and vasopressin in the body based on what we
just talked about during exercise, what should we see happen with plasma volume?
Yeah, balance or even go up, right?
Because the whole goal of all of these is to reabsorb water.
It's never that simple though, right?
Okay, let's look at this graph.
Change in plasma volume on the Y, left Y. Change
in aldosterone concentration, but we also know that vasopressin does the same thing.
on the why we're looking at the duration, so change in duration.
Aldosterone is this blue one.
No surprise, aldosterone's going up.
We've already established that.
Wait a minute.
Plasma volume goes down, still going down, still going down, and still going down.
That's weird.
Does that just mean aldosterone's useless?
Say again?
Does it have to do with anything with sweating?
Is that what you were thinking?
A little bit, right, like that first slide I
showed you, everything's going down because of potentially
maybe sweating or hydrostatic pressure and things like that.
But the whole job of these two hormones is to bring it
back up or maybe even prevent it from going down.
Why isn't it working?
It's kind of the same thing.
Where does all the blood wanna go during exercise?
the muscles.
The only way you could produce urine is if I send
blood to the kidneys so the kidneys can filter out the urine.
If it then filters out the blood to produce urine, well,
now I need to pull back whatever water I can in there.
During exercise, you actually don't produce a lot of urine.
So there's nothing really to get back in that process.
So we have a huge limitation as far as the ability
to reabsorb something that doesn't even have a high concentration or a high mountain in the first place.
And you've probably noticed this, right?
Unless you chug two liters of water before you exercise.
But typically, if you're in a comfortable state and
you go exercise, you could probably exercise for quite a long time without having to use the bathroom.
And then afterwards, though, that's when maybe things start to change.
And so the question would be, well, why do we secrete all of these things?
Well, the body does not kind of
determine what situation you're in.
The hypothalamus is just reacting to the decrease in
plasma volume, so it's just gonna keep secreting it until plasma volume goes back up.
So you have these high concentration of these hormones when you're exercising.
And the most important piece for these would be
after you're done exercising and you start rehydrating.
That's when you're going to start really getting this impact for these type of hormones.
During exercise, they do very little to no change in plasma point, as we saw before.
Are we OK with this concept?
So during exercise, aldosterone, basopressin,
not really helping too much with the plasma volume retention or kind of attenuation of that drop.
However, after exercise, when we start rehydrating, that's
when it's gonna really help increase blood volume.
This is why, after repeated bouts of endurance training, there are other factors too.
Athletes typically have a higher blood volume compared
to recreationally active individuals of sedentary.
because they are continuously undergoing this peace and
your body's starting to increase blood volume over time.
No, yeah, yeah, it's just because, yeah, there's nothing to reabsorb from the kidneys, yeah.
So as you are filtering, once it's in the bladder, it's in the bladder, it's gone.
Like, if you already have urine in the bladder, you're done.
But as you are producing the urine, before it gets to
the bladder, you're kind of pulling as much water out as possible.
But if I'm not even sending blood to the kidneys for
it to be filtered in the first place, there's not a whole lot you can do from there.
Yeah.
How does that work with, like, fueling the blood?
Yeah, so that gets into a different conversation, which we'll get into in thermoregulation.
But typically, when you sweat, you lose a lot of electrolytes.
And that's where you get this idea of, hey, we
need to replenish some of those electrolytes, as well as total body water.
So total body water is much different than blood volume.
And that becomes a big problem if we become dehydrated.
So dehydration is usually reserved for total body water
loss, not necessarily blood volume loss, although they sometimes go hand in hand.
Great question.
Yeah.
Yeah, so the question was, does your body struggle to take on water?
Not necessarily if it gets into your body, but most
people can't handle drinking water and the discomfort that comes with it.
So if you drink water, as long as the environment is
good, you will absorb that water into the body.
However, if I start
Like drinking 500 milliliters of fluid at high intensity
exercise, most people will not enjoy that feeling and maybe sometimes throw up or they have to slow down.
Yeah.
OK.
That moves us on to chapter six.
This will be the last chapter that you will see on your lecture exam next Thursday.
Just a quick update on that.
So it's, I haven't finished it just yet, but there's around 33 questions, all multiple choice.
I highly recommend you bring a calculator because there will be calculations on this lecture exam.
You don't necessarily need the calculator, but in my opinion
I would, like why deal with that stress of mental math when you have a calculator?
If it requires an equation, it will be on the front page of the exam.
You do not need to memorize any equations.
So I have this, not everyone agrees with me, but I
have a school of thought of nowadays you can look up any equation on Google.
So I feel like I shouldn't really test you to memorize those equations.
You just need to know how to use them.
Because in life, you can just Google, like, what's the equation for this?
But not everyone knows how to use it.
Conversion factors will also be given if we use it, right?
Yeah, yeah.
But like, I mean, I'm not going to give you like minutes to seconds.
But like, yeah, like feet to meters or something like that or things.
Yeah, like some of the non-basic ones.
Yeah, no practice exam, but the learning goals and
the clicker questions are probably the best way.
I have a few review clicker questions that we'll use
on Tuesday, because I don't think we're going to get through all of this.
So obviously, we're not going to have a full lecture on
Tuesday, but I will reserve the end of class for some
review clicker questions that are a little bit harder than what you've normally seen.
Plus, I'm happy to answer any questions for the previous materials.
As far as mechanisms go, you've obviously introduced a lot of mechanisms,
but I feel like for the majority of them, you said
that you don't really expect us to know the certain mechanisms.
Which ones would you say we should prioritize?
So a good example would be the hormones in some of these immune mechanisms.
You don't need to know how the secondary messenger
system or secondary cascade is responding or reacting to the hormone to get the response.
Instead, you need to know hormone, what the response
is, and then what implications should you know for exercise.
But mechanisms like hormones impacting substrate utilization, you should know that.
So I could theoretically ask you a question on why
certain hormones or certain processes are causing fat
utilization to decrease during intense exercise.
And we just talked about those four factors, hydrogen,
lactate, blood flow, transport proteins of human.
But all multiple choice.
Sometimes that's good, sometimes that's bad.
Okay, exercise and the immune system, very similar to endocrinology.
We don't go into depth at all.
We just cover a basic, broad overview of what the immune
system is and does, and then we relate a lot of the exercise pieces.
So details on the immune system, those are things that
I would recommend not spending a ton of time on, but you
still need to understand the basics so we can apply them to exercise physiology.
Okay, overview of the immune system is where we're
gonna start, then exercise in the immune system, acute versus chronic.
We'll talk about upper respiratory tract infections,
and then exercising in environmental extremes.
And of course, we'll start and end with this common
question, should you exercise when you have a cold?
So again, we'll start with this.
I'm curious what we think here, and then we'll go through the material and ask it again.
And sometimes we get changes, sometimes we don't.
Okay, let's take 15 seconds or so, just so you can get an answer in.
Anyone need more time getting set up with their clicker?
Okay, I'll close this up in five seconds.
Three, two, one.
Okay, we'll come back to this after we go over all of the slides here.
But overview of the immune system.
So just to add, if you're curious, we're actually split 50-50 down there, yes and no.
But let's see, because it kinda depends.
But overview of the immune system.
The immune system, again in a broad context, is just
a mechanism for the body to protect against invasions or foreign particles, pathogens.
These pathogens or foreign agents can be parasites, viruses, bacteria, fungi.
There are a lot of them, but these are some examples.
We as humans have three major levels of defense.
We have anatomical barriers, which is the physical barriers
that are kind of separating the environment from the internal body.
Skin mucus membranes are great examples.
Some of those membranes would be found even in the respiratory tract.
So sometimes we forget that inside the alveoli of our lungs,
There's a fluid that helps protect against pathogens.
Then we have two other levels of defense.
We have something called the innate immunity.
And so for this one, we kind of are born with it.
And these are some cells that are associated with the innate immune system.
You do not need to memorize these, but the natural
killer cell, as well as these cells, are associated with the innate immune system.
The reason why I bring this up is if I talk about
macrophages, then you can kind of go back and be like, oh, wait, is that innate or adaptive?
And then you can come back to here and be like, oh, OK, it's innate.
What the innate system does pretty much, there are a few
things it does, but one of them is something called phagocytosis.
And so what it's doing is I have a macrophage
that pretty much ingests your pathogen, kind of breaks it down and discards it for kind of waste removal.
Macrophages and neutrophils are the ones that undergo phagocytosis.
Another innate immune system cell would be or kind of
mechanism to deal with pathogens would be apoptosis.
So natural killer cells can actually go to these infected
cells and cause it to undergo apoptosis with his like a programmed cell death.
It basically tells it to self-destruct.
This is kind of important because we're going to talk about
this later on when we get into muscle physiology.
But apoptosis is the kind of programmed cell death that happens naturally inside of our cells.
Another system would be the complement system.
So this one's actually pretty cool.
So we get some complement proteins that tag the surface of the pathogen.
In this example, we're looking at a bacteria.
Once you tag these, then you get some other
innate immune system cells to go in there.
In this example here, it's causing, it's like poking holes in
the cell, and then it causes it to kind of destroy.
The next one would be acute inflammation.
So this is usually in response to injury.
So we get a cut on our finger.
We get exposed to some type of pathogen from the environment.
Once that happens, the immune cells are kind of activated within that injured tissue.
And a bunch of immune cells kind of rush to that
site and cause some damage as well as some swelling.
So we get this innate acute inflammation.
And so when we talk about inflammation, the Latin word
like inflamar is basically to ignite or burn.
And so that's why typically you get that sensation and that's why they call it inflammation.
So let's look at this in a little bit more detail.
Again, you have some type of break in that physical barrier.
You introduce some type of pathogen or bacteria, you get
the swelling, and all of these cells are trying to come in in response to the external pathogen.
Some cardinal signs of inflammation would be redness, swelling, heat, pain, and loss of function.
OK, so this inflammation that we're talking about usually
is associated with some type of exposure to the external environment where the pathogen comes in.
You also can get something called sterile inflammation.
So sterile inflammation occurs in the absence of a pathogen.
And you might be thinking, oh, well, when does that happen?
Well, I could sprain my ankle here.
or tear a muscle, which can cause some inflammation.
So besides ankle sprains, let's take some time to
chat with your neighbor, besides some ankle sprains, when
else might sterile inflammation occur after exercise?
So after exercise.
Okay, take a few minutes and we'll come back.
Okay, what are we thinking here?
Besides like an injury where I sprained my ankle, how
else do you think someone might experience some sterile inflammation after exercise?
Yeah, yeah, yeah, we'll get into that.
Again, we'll get into that, but if you tear some of those muscles,
Your body undergoes a lot of these interesting
steps and processes that eventually cause inflammation.
That's a good one.
What's another one?
This one I'd be really surprised if someone got it.
Yeah, yeah, no that's the same kind of concept as
the hypertrophy pieces, but this is actually getting really close to what I'm about to mention.
If I cause damage to the muscle fibers because fighters
are kicking things to strengthen up some bone, then yeah, that's gonna cause some inflammation.
On that same line, what about runners?
Obviously they're not going around kicking trees while they're
running, but what else kind of happens?
Yeah, so stress fractures, and not necessarily stress factors
in the injury sense, but there's actually something called foot strike hemolysis.
So as I am running, you actually cause a lot of
stress on the muscles and you can actually break some of the red blood cells.
And in response to that, you have a little bit of an inflammation.
So there's some, I guess,
areas where there's not like a full consensus that foot strike hemolysis is causing this.
But I think most people who have run or ran long
distance events have experienced this in one form or another.
Here's what I mean.
So this is a volunteered photo here, but we have
a foot that looks perfectly normal here before 100 miles of running.
There was no acute injury, so no ankle sprain or anything like that.
After 100 miles running, that same foot is now swollen.
Now, not everyone has run 100 miles, but believe it or
not, even if you ran close to a marathon, your foot swells up
as you are doing this, and it is undergoing some
sort of acute kind of sterile inflammation in that area, a lot
of this is believed due to some of this foot strike hemolysis that's going on.
I think his daughter was like painting his toenails, but that's why that's there.
Okay.
So then let me ask you this, we don't need to spend too much time here,
because I think we already have a good idea of this,
but so then how can we reduce inflammation after acute exercise or after exercise?
Ice is one, yeah.
Elevate.
Oh, so I like where you're going with that, but let's
just assume after the exercise you have the inflammation, how can we reduce it?
Compression, good.
I think people are, yeah, someone said it.
Rice, yeah, and so what's the E?
Elevation, right, so that's typically what they recommend.
They're saying rest, ice, compress, and elevate.
However, it's interesting with this.
The inflammation process gets a really bad rap because all
the time you're hearing, oh, we gotta take care of this inflammation.
Inflammation is bad, right?
But insufficient evidence is available from randomized control
trials to determine the relative effectiveness of rice therapy
for acute ankle sprains as well as sterile inflammation.
There's two sides to this.
Right?
Inflammation is good in a sense that it's helping deal with some sort of issue.
Clearly it becomes bad if it gets out of control.
So I'm on the school of thought that we shouldn't always try to eliminate inflammation.
There was a really good paper published in 2022 that
kind of outlined this idea of acute versus chronic inflammation.
we have some sort of initiation phase where inflammation goes up.
In the resolution phase, meaning we're trying to manage this inflammation, it starts to go down.
But every now and then, we don't get it to return.
And so this chronic inflammation is the big problem in my opinion.
Whereas if we don't allow the body to kind of have that natural inflammation
or if I'm always after exercise going in and doing these ice cold baths
or doing these cryotherapies, you might not always be getting
the benefit that you think you are because inflammation in a broad sense is actually pretty good to have.
It's kind of nice that our body responds to this and then we adapt and build back up.
So we need to have some of this stress or this damage.
But this chronic piece is where it becomes a problem.
Okay, so chronic inflammation.
This is due to persistent infection or prolonged immune response.
Again, low grade inflammation can occur due to inactivity, obesity, and aging.
High-grade inflammation with the chronic aspect to it
are usually associated with certain cancers and rheumatoid arthritis.
So I know we're always quick to reduce that inflammation.
If I have some sort of injury and I'm having
swelling that's damaging other tissue, yeah, let's get that under control.
But if it's a relatively mild acute inflammation, sometimes
it's good to let it undergo its natural process.
Okay, number three, the adaptive or acquired immunity.
Acquired is good because we build this over time.
Those cells are the B cells and the T cells.
Because they're adaptive, they recognize and remember certain pathogens.
So if I'm exposed to a certain antigen, this lymphocyte
will then start to produce a bunch of memory cells.
That way, if you're exposed to that same pathogen or antigen in the future,
you can respond and try to take care of it in a much faster time frame.
I kind of like this piece here, this memory T cell, and we have some E. coli.
And the memory T cell says, I will never forget you.
It's not too bad.
Okay, so if you have some sort of response to
a pathogen and you are mobilizing your adaptive immune system,
typically you get a swelling inside of some of your lymph nodes.
And that usually is a really good indication that you're fighting something off.
So that's why sometimes people would feel their lymph nodes
when they're not feeling great to see if they were
swollen, because that might give an indication that you're mobilizing some of those adaptive immune cells.
So there are a lot of these cells, B cells, cytotoxic T cells, helper cells, regulatory T cells.
You don't need to know the details or memorize these, but we are gonna talk about some of these.
So again, when you see maybe a killer T cell or B
cell on the improvements due to exercise, or if I'm getting
some type of inhibition, then you know we're looking at the adaptive immune system.
Okay, so let's get into this.
Exercise and the immune system.
Acute, moderate intensity, short duration aerobic exercise
has shown to improve immunosurveillance in the body.
When we're talking about moderate exercise, less than 60 minutes,
we're looking at 40 to 60% of VO2 max.
This helps boost the innate and the adaptive immune
system and those cells associated with those systems.
However, this is kind of transitory, right?
It returns back to normal in about three hours.
There is this idea, though, that you can
potentially enhance your antibody-specific response with vaccinations
with exercise, meaning if I am boosting or improving
the immunosurveillance due to this moderate exercise and I'm due
for a vaccine, it's possible that you can improve the
innate or boost the innate and adaptive immune system.
So then when you get the vaccine, you get a more
kind of robust response and that your body kind of gets a little bit stronger to that.
antigen or whatever you were exposed to in that vaccine.
Again, it needs a little bit more research, but there's
a lot of suggestions that have kind of indicated that this might be the case.
Okay, acute high-intensity, long-duration aerobic exercise.
prolonged exercise greater than 90 minutes has a temporary depressive effect on the immune system.
That means we are decreasing the levels of the B, T, and the natural killer cells.
We're decreasing the activity as well as the function of the cells that are there.
and we're decreasing the sites as well, so in the nasal pathway.
We're also increasing the pro and anti-inflammatory cytokines.
That's interesting, because if I'm decreasing the
immunosurveillance or decreasing our immune system functions,
And that should put that individual at a little
bit more risk, especially in this respiratory tract area.
So then chronic exercise has an impact on infection,
especially if it's kind of this higher intensity, longer duration exercise.
This introduces something called the J-curve model.
This is very similar to a lot of the models we've talked about.
But if this over here on the y-axis is the upper respiratory tract infection risk,
where above one is a higher risk to get an upper
respiratory tract infection, and below zero is a kind of lower risk to get an infection.
Here we have kind of two categories, but they span
along a continuous spectrum where we can go from sedentary all the way to heavy exertion.
So this could be exercise workload here.
So if we start on normal where we're sedentary or not exercising, we're here.
We're at our baseline risk.
If I start to exercise, I get a depressive effect
Or, sorry, it's not depressing, but you reduce the risk
that you're gonna get a upper respiratory tract infection.
That's a good thing.
As I increase in the exercise intensity, I start to
increase the risk that I'm going to experience an upper respiratory tract infection.
And you might have seen this.
If you have friends or you are a kind
of competitive endurance athlete, sometimes those individuals are constantly fighting something.
They might be fighting a cold or things like that, and that's not always the case,
but they are putting themselves at a little bit of
a higher risk for getting an upper respiratory tract infection.
We'll talk about some of the other factors as to
what's contributing to that, but in general, this J-curve model is explaining some of it.
So what you can take away from this is if
I'm engaging in this constant moderate exercise over long periods of time, I can help reduce
the risk of getting an upper respiratory tract infection.
If I'm always kind of going 100% all the
time, maximum exercise intensity, you actually are putting yourself at
a little bit of a higher risk for getting an infection.
No, that's, so the data are mostly
on this upper respiratory tract infection, but they go all the way throughout.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, because you're just putting your body at a really high stress point,
and so now the body's fighting, fighting, it's recovering from all that stress you just put on it,
and it has less energy or time to maybe fight off
pathogens, as opposed to this piece here, like increasing that immunosurveillance.
How are we doing?
Not too bad.
I feel like if I keep going, we're going to have nothing for Tuesday.
So have a great weekend.
I'll see you on Tuesday.
So just a quick recap on like the...