All right.
Welcome back, everyone.
I hope you had a good weekend.
We are gonna get started with the next unit.
So just as a reminder, chapters physiology of training, 13, 14,
and 20 will not be on your exam on Thursday.
So it's just eight through 11.
We okay with that?
But I have to go through this or else we're gonna fall way behind.
So originally this was supposed to be on your second exam,
but I wanted to make sure to take some time through the
other materials and give you some time to study for that chapter 11.
So that's why we're pushing this material to the final.
Any questions on that?
Okay, cool, so this is the Physiology of Training.
It starts to, all of it's pretty fun in my opinion,
but it starts to all come together where we can start applying this maybe to training principles.
So we'll start with that concept, training principles.
or principles of training.
Then we'll go to the physiological effects of
endurance training, detraining following endurance training.
And then links between muscle and systemic physiology.
We'll talk a little bit about resistance training or strength training.
And then some interesting things with detraining in resistance training as well.
And then concurrent strength and endurance training.
So sometimes,
There's this idea, and we'll show some mechanisms, that if you do both strain training
and you do endurance training at the same time,
that that could potentially have some interactions going on.
And then some common training mistakes that we'll kind of discuss very briefly.
Okay, so principles of training.
What are the principles of training?
No surprise, in order to have some type of adaptation, you need to overload the system.
You need to stress the body in some way so the body adapts.
That is this concept of overload.
So this is an increased capacity of a system in response
to training above the level of which it is accustomed to.
So if I am stressing the body beyond what you do
on a normal basis, the body will make adaptations in order to
try to deal with that same stress again at another time.
We can alter the different, I guess, control systems as
far as like am I altering intensity, duration, and frequency.
Most of the time, they are very commonly linked.
If you are training at a high intensity, by default, your duration will always come down.
But you can imagine that I could do something like
heavy exercise and I can vary the duration quite easily.
And then frequency is the same deal.
So typically, on this graph over here, on the x-axis, we have time.
On the y, we have performance.
So as we are going up on the y-axis, we are improving in performance.
When we have one training bout, we see a temporary or an acute dip in performance.
But then that comes back up because our body is making some adaptations.
Over time,
If this time over here is weeks or months, this decrement will then come up.
And then you'll apply some stress or you'll overload the system.
It'll come back down.
You'll recover, overload, recover, overload, recover.
And as time progresses, you will see an improvement in performance.
Now there's two kind of pieces to this where we need to be careful about.
One, if you train too much, or if you stop training.
If you do either of those things, then you can experience reversibility.
So you can reverse some of the gains that you've now experienced.
So when training is stopped, the effect is quickly lost.
The body's actually really good at conserving energy.
If you make all these adaptations to deal with extra stress and then you never apply
that stress anymore, the body's gonna be like, okay, cool, now
I don't have to spend the energy to keep these things alive and we'll go ahead and rotate this off.
And so this is the same concept that we saw
before in blue as you progressively overload the system and increase in performance.
However, if you stop training in this black, dark line right here,
no surprise that your fitness level will start to decrease.
The concerning piece to this graph is if you are
seeing improvements in performance, most tend to think, well, if I
and gaining these performances with this type of stress, the
only way I can improve even more would be to apply more stress and overload the body even more.
But we need to be careful with that because now
you're not giving yourself enough recovery time and you start to trend downwards.
And we'll talk about overtraining syndrome a little bit later in the semester,
but this is a serious issue where a lot of elite
endurance athletes are just maybe people who are engaging in exercise.
very frequently at high intensities, they'll start to see a decrease in their performance
and it becomes very problematic as far as on an individual's mental ability,
or not ability, but just their mentality on things
because they're like, well, I don't understand why I'm not
getting better when I'm training all the time and training even harder.
And so sometimes they are experiencing this overtraining syndrome.
And depending on how severe it gets, you can even get pretty severe down here.
And it takes years to recover from.
Most of the time, it doesn't take that long.
But if it becomes that severe, sometimes you'll see
athletes on the highest Olympic caliber athletes where they'll need years to recover from some of this.
But we'll get into overtraining syndrome a little bit later.
But just know that if you apply an appropriate amount
of overload with an appropriate amount of recovery, we
will see this progressive overload and an improvement in performance.
If you stop this progressive overload, then you'll see a decrease in performance.
If you don't let the body recover enough, then
you could potentially see this overtraining where you see a decrease in performance.
Any questions on this?
Okay.
Specificity is another principle of training.
This is basically saying, if I am a runner, I probably
want to train the muscles and the movement involved in running to get better at running.
I think we all are pretty familiar with this.
Some of them do cross over.
If I am a cyclist, I might not be the best runner, but
it might take less time for me to become a very successful runner than if I'm sedentary.
So there's some crossover, but specificity is really important.
We need to train the muscles and the type of movements
and the activities that we are trying to be applying that to the given race.
Okay, with the data that we do have right now, it
appears that men and women do respond similarly to training programs.
However, exercise prescriptions should be individualized, although it is very hard to do.
In the American College of Sports Medicine, if you look at any other training programs,
it's like, oh, three to five days a week, maybe around 50
to 60% of your VO2 max and try to do that for an hour a day.
that is very broad and that will help everyone.
But if you are primarily trying to improve performance,
there's a lot of individual variability and we should probably
try and make things a little bit more individualized to
certain groups as opposed to just saying everybody must adhere to
this training program if you want to get better.
Okay, what about
pre-existing fitness level.
So your initial fitness level does impact the percent gain that I might experience after training.
So if we look at this figure here, we have
three groups, sedentary, active, and trained, and we have VO2 max
as a relative component here on the Y axis.
Sedentary individuals, they start typically at a lower VO2 max.
And so when they go through training, they have a larger relative increase.
They have a 50% increase in this example.
That increase is much smaller as we get to individuals who are more fit.
So active individuals, because they start at a higher initial baseline VO2,
they only get maybe like a 20% increase.
And then for trained individuals, it's actually really,
really hard to improve your maximum aerobic capacity.
And so 5% is probably generous, but that wouldn't be out
of the ordinary if we saw a 5% increase in someone who
was even like a collegiate athlete or a sub-elite athlete.
So it is possible to increase maximum aerobic fitness,
But the relative change does depend on the initial fitness level.
Yeah.
Yeah, and so I think there's a big debate on this, where
they used to say, OK, we should no longer use VO2 max, we just need to use VO2 peak.
And so there was like, maybe this is your peak
performance, but we'll never actually know what someone's max is, because
how do I know I can't apply the correct stressors to get that individual max?
The short answer is we don't really know, besides like, OK,
what are you doing on a normal basis, and how long have you been doing that?
So if I can put you in one of these categories,
or sometimes we can expand this to like five different
categories, then it'll be a better indication of maybe how much room that person has to grow.
Yeah, that's a really good question.
The other problem with trying to see how much we can grow is genetics.
So there's a large influence of genetics.
And this should not be super surprising here, but this is a pretty cool study
where they looked at the increase in VO2 max for one twin,
so it was a twin study, compared to the increase in VO2 max for another twin.
And 10 pairs of identical twins, they did have an increase in VO2 max.
And they did have it relatively linearly.
And if you look at the R here, it's 0.82.
So the R squared's around 6.6.
So it's about 60% of the variation.
And the improvements in VO2 max due to training are potentially from genetics here.
That's kind of what this is telling me.
That's 40% that we're not really accounting for.
So it's not only genetics, but genetics does play a
relatively large role in how an individual can become trained or not trained.
They have kind of labeled the influence of genetics on this genotyping.
And it's not maybe the same genotyping that you would kind
of expect as far as like a particular gene.
But they have these different genotypes here.
And they took these different individuals and had them train for about 30 months.
And they looked at the improvements in VO2max.
One of the biggest things they found is their baseline VO2max
was different between all sedentary individuals.
So these are individuals who were not active.
And you took their baseline VO2 Maxis and they were all a little bit different.
And it looks like there are some non-responders and there are some very strong responders.
And this is where this comes into play where it's like, okay, well, maybe it's,
how you were born that's going to determine maybe what
sport you might be a little bit more successful at.
And so some of the high responders genotype E possess a relatively high untrained VO2 max.
And if you thought about this, some of these things do make sense.
If I was just born with larger lungs and a larger heart, and I was a little bit taller
and I had more blood volume, then I'd probably have a little bit more to grow,
and so the absolute kind of VO2 max that I
could potentially achieve would be much higher compared to if I
had a smaller heart, smaller lungs, and so forth.
So that's kind of what this is getting at here, this genotyping.
So some people can really
have more of the ideal genetic makeup to help their success in a particular endurance event.
So with that aerobic or anaerobic capacity is more genetically determined than aerobic capacity.
So we said VO2 max in particular, that's maybe accounting for 64% of the variability.
Well, resistance training or
anaerobic type of events, maybe it's Olympic weight lifting
or some of the shorter sprints, those have a lot more of
a genetic component to it as far as an individual's ability to be successful.
And if you've taken biomechanics, even the insertion of a muscle on the bone
If the distance is changing from the joint, that could
make a very, very large change in the amount of leverage you can generate from that muscle.
And so even though the muscle is generating the same
amount of force, depending on where it inserts on the bone, well, you have more or less leverage.
So I would say this does kind of check off where the anaerobic capacity
or your ability to do some of these short
duration high intensity exercises are more genetically determined than the endurance capacity.
Type two fibers have been theorized to be a very large component of this as well.
So then there's this very famous quote here, if you
want to become a world-class athlete, you must choose your parents wisely, right?
Obviously, you can't choose your parents, but I think you
understand what they are trying to say, so.
Okay.
Physiological effects of endurance training.
So we kind of looked at a few of these tests, mainly
running economy and VO2 max, but there are a few other things that we touched on.
One would be the ventilatory threshold or lactate threshold.
The one concept that we have not talked about or will not talk about is critical power.
That's another piece that's really important in performance.
And that kind of ties in as well with like VO2 kinetics.
And so that's one piece that we don't really talk about.
That's a little bit more for advanced exercise phys, but there are multiple components.
And I think I mentioned no one individual, not no, but very few individuals have
Great values for all of these.
Most have maybe two of them.
And then they end up being very successful in their professional athletes.
And then if you have all four or all three, then
we would say those are the ones that every Olympic you're seeing them kind of perform at a high level.
So just because you don't have a high VO2 max does
not mean you can never become a successful endurance athlete.
Maybe you have a better running economy and a higher lactate threshold.
Some adaptations in the muscle.
If you had this repeated overload, repeated excitation and
contraction of the muscle fibers during endurance training, that
will stimulate the body to make some adaptations.
Some of the main adaptations that we'll talk about
would be muscle fiber type, capillary density, myoglobin content, and mitochondrial function.
All right, so let's talk about this first one then, muscle fiber type.
If we are talking about endurance training, we typically are
seeing the shift from fast to slow fibers or muscle fiber types.
And it's not necessarily saying,
we are eliminating a certain muscle fiber type.
That's not what we're talking about or even gaining a certain muscle fiber type.
This is saying a reduction in the cross-sectional area for
the fast fibers and an increase in the cross-sectional area for the slow fibers.
So you are adding those sarcomeres in parallel to make
the muscle fiber, the single muscle fiber a little bit bigger.
The magnitude of the change is determined by the type of training that you are doing.
And if you remember, we briefly talked about this in
chapter 8 with muscle physiology, but there are these hybrid types.
So sometimes there's a type 1, type 2a, type 2a, type 2x.
You don't need to know this, but just know there is
this kind of shift where they start to become, you see some hybrid fiber types.
But in general, you're increasing the cross-sectional area of the fiber type of interest.
All right.
Capillary density would be the next one.
So we see an increase in the number of capillaries surrounding the muscle fibers.
This should also track with everything that we talked about.
If I can deliver more blood to the tissues, well, that means
more oxygen is going to be able to be delivered to those tissues.
And so the best way to do that would be to
increase the number of capillaries that are surrounding those muscle fibers.
So it's going to enhance diffusion of oxygen and improve the removal of waste.
This table 11.2 down here, if you decided to ignore it, that's OK with me.
This is just something to show as far as
the number of capillaries increasing, the capillary density.
So the one way, so someone might ask, OK, well,
if I'm just increasing the number of capillaries, yeah, I'm sending more blood.
But the other thing that does is if you send the same amount of blood,
but now you have more capillaries for the blood to
spread out, you are slowing down the blood that's kind of
flowing past the muscle fibers and allows for a better diffusion time.
So you're increasing the time it takes for the blood to
move across the muscle bed because now you have all these
capillaries that are distributing the blood in a better way.
And then it also, not in a big piece, but it could potentially change the diffusion distance if
This is not what happens.
But if you only had muscle fibers on the top of,
or capillaries on the top of the muscle fiber, then it would
be really hard to diffuse the oxygen all the way to the bottom.
And so if you surround it, then it's a little bit easier for the oxygen to get through.
That's not exactly what happens, but that's a good way to kind of think of it.
Any questions on this one?
Myoglobin content, endurance training increases muscle myoglobin by approximately 70 to 80%.
This then helps increase the O2 reserve in the muscles,
but it also supports a muscle's increased capacity for oxidative metabolism after training.
So after I train, if I'm increasing the number of
myoglobin, well now the hemoglobin molecules can drop off more
oxygen to the muscles and they have somewhere to go, right?
They're going to the myoglobin so the myoglobin can pick it up and deliver it to the mitochondria.
All right, muscle mitochondria, those also increase or change.
We'll start with the time course.
It's relatively quick.
It's not the fastest thing that changes.
But within five weeks, so about a month of training,
we can see almost a doubling in the mitochondrial density.
And so we can say that it's pretty like the
plasticity of mitochondrial density changes is quite high.
So you might be thinking like, OK, where are these mitochondria changing?
And if you remember again from chapter 8, we have two locations for muscle mitochondria.
We have the subcircle lemma, or the SS, and then we have the IMF.
So in between the muscle fibers and then kind of on top of the muscle fibers.
Same deal, if we have increase in the number or
the volume of mitochondria, that's gonna help our oxidative capacity.
And that's also going to help us utilize fat as a fuel source.
With training, we also see an increased turnover rate of mitochondria.
And this is a good thing because we want our
mitochondria to be functioning at a high efficiency or a good rate.
And so any time we have damaged mitochondria, if
the turnover is high, we're not really experiencing any of those problems.
And so that happens when we are undergoing consistent training for long periods of time.
If we talk about the breakdown of damaged mitochondria, mitophagy would be the term.
And you don't need to know this, but sometimes the
free radicals or the free radical productions or the electrons
are causing damage to the cytochromes, and sometimes you can get some damage in the mitochondria.
So it's nice to turn those over.
Okay, so if we're increasing the number here, so the
density, the next piece would be talking about maybe the size of each individual mitochondria.
If we increase the volume of the mitochondria, that just
means you're able to kind of spread out the workload a little bit easier for that particular mitochondria.
The density also does that, right?
If you have two things doing the same thing, well,
now you can maybe split the workload between the two mitochondria to produce the same amount of ATP.
That same concept happens here, where it can handle
Like different portions or areas of the mitochondria can handle
maybe units of ADP, so then you can get the same amount of oxygen consumption.
So instead of making the individual pieces of the mitochondria
work harder, you now can spread out the work amongst one mitochondria if the volume gets bigger.
And then if you increase in density, you're spreading it across multiple mitochondria.
Increase in mitochondria volume also decreases cytosolic ADP
concentrations due to increased ADP transporters.
If you can do that, if you can increase the number of ADP concentration
or change the ADP concentration, then you are
encouraging oxidative phosphorylation inside of the mitochondria.
OK, all of these things are nice to see, especially they're going to improve, say, VO2 max.
They're also going to improve
some of the kinetics that are involved with submaximal exercise.
And we see this with the O2 deficit.
So if we go back one slide, sorry about that.
If we see less phosphocreatine depletion, so we're using
less of the immediate energy stores, well that should be seen in this O2 debt shading curve.
So like if I shaded from this teal line over to here, this O2 debt here,
is much smaller than if I shaded from the end of this blue line all the way over.
So again, same picture, less phosphocreatine depletion.
O2 kinetics kind of talks about how quickly this line rises.
They're kind of saying the same thing.
And so the faster we get the oxygen consumption to
rise, typically that's a little bit better for individuals
who are conducting or performing some maximal exercise or endurance exercise.
Okay, so this is great, right?
Like we have this increase in mitochondrial density, increase in myoglobin.
We're having all these types of nice changes here.
What are the mechanisms
or what are the signals that the body is sending to increase all of these things?
So this would be the exercise-induced signaling that we're seeing here.
You really just need to focus on the six secondary signaling molecules which are here.
So this row here.
Now, when I say that, I would not memorize these.
You definitely can.
But I'll tell you right now, I'm not going to say list the six secondary signaling molecules.
I'm just saying you should focus on this piece.
And if there's one, not to memorize, but there's one to
kind of keep in the back of your mind, would be this PGC1 alpha.
That's because a lot of these signaling molecules kind of also influence the PGC1 alpha.
But the whole point is if I increase the number
or concentration of calcium here, the calcium in itself acts as like a myokine.
And then it increases some type of secondary signaling molecule
to help shift the fiber type from fast to slow or
increase the cross-sectional area of those kind of slower fiber types or those type I fibers.
That also activates PGC1 alpha, which would do the same
thing for this fiber type shift, but it also encourages mitochondrial biogenesis.
So increasing the number and the density of the mitochondria.
And same with these ones over here.
NF kappa beta here is going to increase the synthesis of antioxidant enzymes.
So when we're looking at this PGC1 alpha, it's kind of
funny, where you would think it's only like three words.
But I don't know if you know this, but
PGC1 alpha is paroxysome proliferator activated receptor gamma co-activator.
That's crazy, right?
You would think it would be a little shorter than that, but that's what PGC1 alpha is.
You don't need to know that, but OK.
Any questions on this?
Oh, and then this one here, you don't, again, it's nice
to see these, but the AMP ATP ratio, this is just an indication that you have low ATP.
So if you have more AMP than ATP, well, that just
means you're converting the ATP to ADP and ADP to AMP, right?
So you're reducing the ATP levels.
So if you see,
an increase in this ratio, well those are gonna send signals
to try to activate some of the things that we've just been talking about.
And then same with the free radical production.
If you get those free radicals produced, you're gonna
try to increase the antioxidant enzymes involved with trying to help defend against that.
So big picture, there's some primary signaling.
You don't need to know the details of the primary
signaling, but they lead to secondary kind of responses.
One of the big response is PGC1 alpha.
But all of them kind of together are increasing
the adaptations that we're seeing with endurance training.
OK.
So we talked about training in itself, but it's interesting
because if we look at this here, this AMP-ATP ratio, that's
saying if I'm low on energy, it's going to stimulate some adaptations.
Well, that concept, when this paper came out, then you
got a bunch of researchers and coaches kind of saying,
Well, if I can induce a low energy state and have
my athletes train, then potentially I could get even further adaptations.
So that's why this kind of concept came in where
you have low muscle glycogen is a positive influence on endurance training induced adaptations.
So that decrease in that ratio, that AMP-ATP ratio,
is going to promote increased protein synthesis and mitochondrial formation.
And that's, again, due to higher activation of PCG1 alpha.
And that's because of that AMP-ATP ratio.
So this word got out, and now there's two approaches here.
Maybe restrict dietary carbohydrates to try to reduce the energy that is available.
One thing we have to be careful about is it's
definitely going to cause fatigue and limit training.
Or I can do two a days, and the second training session would have lower muscle glycogen.
So maybe it's going to stimulate things.
So there was this big, and it still might be
there, where sometimes there's this big idea where you would just
wake up right away, not eat anything, and then go for some type of training session.
Yeah, you're going to feel kind of miserable and it
might limit your training, but the idea behind that is trying to increase or activate PGC 1 alpha.
Now that's a little bit of a double-edged sword, right?
So maybe I'm increasing protein synthesis and mitochondrial
density, but now my workouts are suffering.
And so there is a little bit of a balance, and so I'm not saying you can't do this
or shouldn't do this, or you should only do this,
but eventually you need to have high-quality workout sessions.
And so, yeah, if you can sprinkle this in strategically, that it could be a good way to train.
Any questions on this concept?
Nice.
I feel like most of you are like checked out, right?
Like, it's not on this exam.
We don't care about this.
That's OK.
I understand.
All right.
Effective exercise duration on muscle fuel source.
You've already seen this, so we don't need to go through it.
But just know as you increase in exercise duration, the
oxidation of fat or the reliance on fat starts to increase.
And that's because we're really starting to deplete some of these muscle glycogen levels.
OK, so for training, we learned that as you increase
with duration, the training effect has this kind of like up into the left shift.
And so we're shifting it this way.
This should be reviewed, so I'm not gonna spend a whole lot of time on it.
Instead, we're gonna talk about a few other details.
Based on what we just talked about, we saw
that endurance exercise training increases capillary density and
also increases the mitochondrial density and size, right?
The number of mitochondria as well as the size.
All of those things are going to improve your ability to kind of
like utilize some of these substrates.
In particular, capillary density is going to slow down the
blood flow in the muscles and increase the number of free fatty acid transporters.
That's going to allow for the muscles to take up more free fatty acids.
and then utilize them more.
But we can't just utilize them more, because if I deliver
more free fatty acids, they need to have maybe more mitochondria.
Well, nice thing about this is we do have that increased number in mitochondria.
We also have this kind of increase in beta oxidation and the enzymes involved in beta oxidation.
All of this is going to help spare some of the glucose, plasma glucose.
So that's why we're shifting things up into the left.
And if you shift that up into the left, then that
means carbohydrates are going down, which is a good thing for endurance exercise.
OK, what about the acid-base balance?
We've talked about kind of this concept of acid-base balance in chapter 11.
Well, if we increase the number of mitochondria and we
can increase the free fatty acid oxidation, we're going to decrease PFK activity.
Well, that's kind of nice, because maybe we're going
to decrease pyruvate formation and form less lactate.
And potentially, we're going to help reduce some of the hydrogen formation.
This piece here, I wouldn't worry about it too much, but H4.
So this is that lactate dehydrogenase.
There's an enzyme.
And there's just a different isoform that kind of
encourages the formation of pyruvate as opposed to the formation of lactate, for example.
All of that is going to help maintain some of that blood pH and that muscle pH as well.
So if we're decreasing the lactate that is being formed, no surprise that
when we do a lactate test, we see the kind
of rate of appearance versus rate of disappearance, that fluctuation happened at a much higher intensity.
So that's why we get this shift to the
right with lactate threshold in trained individuals compared to the untrained individuals.
Hopefully this is a lot of review here and you're not thinking that this is brand new information.
We're just kinda putting things together a little bit.
Okay, cardiovascular adaptations to training.
We get multiple cardiovascular adaptations during endurance training.
Maximal cardiac output, heart size, heart rate, stroke volume, blood volume, and AVO2 difference.
We're going to kind of walk through some of these things here.
You've probably seen the range of VO2 max between
maybe untrained and trained individuals between sex, and this is just a reminder here.
This is not necessarily for you to memorize, but it is nice to know that on average the
for different groups.
You have women who are kind of lower on average than men.
Obviously, there are some women who are higher than males,
but in general, the men are usually on average a little bit higher than the women.
And then athletes on average are higher than the non-athletes.
And so you can kind of see this trend go through.
OK, I don't know if anyone knows this.
We don't have to break out into a group thought question here.
But does anyone have an idea of what the highest recorded VO2 max is for male and female, around?
So we showed from 30 to about 71 was the averages, or the range from 30 to 71.
Does anyone have an idea?
That's OK if you don't.
I'm just curious.
Sometimes people are like, oh, I know.
I know this individual because it was very polarized.
OK, so the highest value.
So if we go back here, remember, so at 38 here, 44,
55, and 71, this kind of 10 milliliters per kilogram per minute stepwise increase is quite normal.
Oscar was a professional cyclist who had a VO2 max recorded of 96.7, and then Joanne had 78.6.
So that was quite surprising to see, and this was on a consistent basis.
So this was...
Oscar has a very interesting story, and there are a
lot of things kind of circulating about his kind of potential to be successful.
And so you would imagine that this individual, this is
kind of old, very old now data-wise, that you would imagine that this individual would be
kind of everywhere, and you'd hear about him being a very successful cyclist.
And that did not turn out to be the case.
And that's not necessarily to say that he wasn't very successful.
It's just there were other things kind of surrounding the area.
But a VO2 max is not the only thing that makes someone a good athlete.
But this case study that was published in 2019, obviously
the data were collected much earlier, so 2011, 2012, 2012, and 2013.
But this was the case study for Oscar here.
And he had a VO2 max across these two years, 85, 96.7, 92.8, and 86.5.
The nice thing about saying this is, number one, once
you have, like, if you record one really high VO2 max, it's not like you're just set there forever, right?
Things fluctuate.
One of the biggest things that do fluctuate would be body mass changes.
a decent amount of body mass changes, and that doesn't necessarily mean that's bad.
If he had a two kilogram increase in body mass, and it was all lean muscle mass,
I would say that was probably a really good increase
in body mass, even though the relative VOT max went down.
Here's the other thing that was pretty impressive.
What was on average the five second peak power for Wingate?
Does anyone remember?
Like what was like a pretty average or decent power output
that was being put out for your five second windgate max?
Like I saw a few at 700 maybe.
Yeah, like 600, 500, right?
I think that's most people were around that range.
And yeah, they were a little lower and a little bit above.
But what's interesting about Oscar here is at all of these tests,
500, 525, 537, 525.
So he's just kind of cruising, not cruising, obviously it's a
little bit hard, but at 500 watts at his VO2 max.
And obviously, he had a higher VO2 max.
So if you take 90% of that, he can easily press like 450 watts for two, four, six hours.
So it's quite impressive.
They don't have a high VO2 max.
They don't have a very high, or sorry, a high power output, but they can hold
a very high power output for long periods of time.
So this is quite impressive.
OK, so does that mean we can always do something to get up to that point?
No.
But if you wanted to increase your VO2 max,
What might we want to do?
Well, I would say that these three pieces would need to come into play.
So maybe chat with your neighbors for just a minute or two and talk about genetics aside.
So if we can remove genetics, how much do you need to work out to improve your VO2 max?
And try to think about the concepts of intensity, duration, and frequency.
And then we'll come back and see what you're feeling on these ones here.
OK, what are we thinking?
Let's start with intensity.
Seems like the easiest one to go at.
If someone came up to you and like, oh man, I heard you took exercise physiology
and I want to increase my VO2 max because I want
something near 90, what kind of training should I be doing as far as intensity?
Yeah, so I'd say modern intensity is pretty good.
And they said, okay, well, why is modern intensity good for me?
What would you say?
Or what would anyone say?
Sorry, I don't mean to put you on the spot, but
modern intensity, I could see where that's coming from because
Yeah, you could do it for longer durations.
And maybe you're going to get some of that activation of some of those pieces
where you're going to get mitochondria biogenesis or
increase in capillary density and then increase in protein synthesis.
And I would totally agree that over time, those are all going to improve VO2 max.
But if I'm thinking about the
the overload principle, and you need to apply a certain
amount of stress beyond what you're used to, and we're just trying to improve VO2 max.
What type of intensity do you think we should be doing?
Yeah, probably intensities at VO2 max, right?
Just at or just above VO2 max.
What's the problem with that?
Yeah, if I tried to do that multiple times a
day and tried to increase the duration, eventually something's going to go wrong, right?
Then you need to give yourself enough recovery to deal with that type of intensity.
And so you might not be having the same stimulus as
you would want, or you're having these huge gaps where you do
that exercise and then you have to wait four days before you can exercise again.
So there is this kind of,
problem where if I am doing these VO2 max workouts,
which you should sprinkle in with moderate exercise intensity, the
duration needs to come way down because we need to give ourselves a little bit of time to recover.
Frequency, same thing.
If I'm trying to improve VO2 max, yeah, I want to focus on maybe those higher intensity exercises.
But now I have to do less of them per week compared to some of the easier exercises.
So if I'm doing a VO2 max workout or a workout
at VO2 max power, then the subsequent exercises might need to
be relatively low to give myself a little bit of time to recover before I start that again.
Good.
And so there's always a balance between high intensity to exercise and moderate
where we want to stay at or above lactate threshold right
in that area to get some of the adaptations that we see with PCG1 alpha, right?
OK, so changes in VO2 max over 12 months.
We definitely can get that increase in VO2 max.
Keep in mind, though, that the initial starting level does
determine how far or how much someone can change.
And as we just talked about, exercise intensities closer to
100% is going to show the greatest improvement.
So at very close to 100%, we're going to see the most improvement.
But as soon as you start going a little bit above
that for longer periods of time, well, we need to be really careful about overtraining.
So this balance of staying up here is very difficult, but it can be done.
So intensity, not duration.
And that's just because you can't maintain this high intensity
for long periods of time is more important for improving the O2 max.
So kind of going right back onto that, if you want some kind of
overall arching figure on intensity, duration, and frequency, this would be a really good figure.
If we're saying percent improvement in VO2 max on
this y-axis, and then we have frequency, intensity, and duration down
here, we can see that if you are getting some gains here,
typically we can get them at certain intensities and frequencies and durations.
And yes, we will get the most optimal or the
highest improvements at the highest intensity with the highest
frequency and the most duration, but now you are exponentially
increasing the risk for injury as well as other complications.
So there's a little bit of a trade off where we
probably don't want to have the most optimal improvements in
VO2Max because we don't want these types of risks.
And we need to stay kind of in this, I guess, middle zone over here.
OK.
One thing we have trouble doing is most of us, if not
all of us, cannot get on a treadmill and then say like, okay, I'm gonna be at 50% VO2 max, right?
We just don't have the ability to always consistently know
where we're at with VO2 or oxygen consumption.
So what's another way that most of us may use or most
individuals may use to try to get an idea of how hard we are working, like how hard your body's working?
Yeah, someone say that again?
Heart rate, right?
So heart rate's a really good one.
So we usually use measurements of heart rate to get an idea of exercise intensity.
This table down here is not something you would ever need to memorize.
But if you ever wanted to look, this is very
common where people break things out in intensity zones.
So zone one, zone two, zone three, zone four, zone five.
And then they break these things down into percentage of your heart rate max.
And just like you did in class, they use VO2 reserve,
move those over to heart rate reserve, and then get them to heart rate values.
So then we can get a good idea of how hard an individual should be exercising.
Yeah, so it depends.
The more data you give the Garmin program, the closer it starts to approach on a good number.
Not that I want to bring stats in here, but the central limit theorem does prove that.
The higher the number of samples, eventually you're going to
get that curve to come very close to what your true VO2 max is.
But the problem is now you need to give it enough
data that's spread out, so low intensity and really high intensity, and a lot of those data points.
But as someone is doing that,
Now your VO2 max might be changing at the same time.
So I would say it depends on when you're capturing it.
It could be really close or it could be way off.
But the technology has gotten a lot better though.
And on that same concept,
you might be asking, well, which is more accurate at estimating heart rate?
Because you probably all have seen in lab maybe some
difficulties getting the chest strap to maybe get a good reading or fit very well.
And so more commonly, most individuals have some type of
watch that reads heart rate or gets some estimation of intensity.
We don't have to go through this question because you
probably all are going to say the watch because you probably hate the chest strap from Lab,
but in general, the chest straps are always going to be
a little bit more, not a little bit more, but significantly more accurate.
Here's the problem, though, with heart rate straps or heart
rate watches and VO2 or any other metric that you're getting from the watch.
On average, the accuracy of the heart rate is actually pretty good.
So the way to read this study would be, so they did
a polar strap, the ones that you guys use in class, and they
also did an EKG here to get the actual heart rate from EKG measurements.
And it looks like the average is right on there.
So this difference of zero meaning is the watch gets, or
the heart rate strap gets 100, and the EKG is getting 100.
As you start to spread out here, that just means some
of these values are not as accurate from the EKG.
And so the polar strap is going to be the most accurate, or the chest strap.
And if you look at the averages for everything, though,
They're all on this zero.
So if you took the averages for every single one, the overall arching conclusion might be
that using one of these Fitbits or a Garmin watch or
an Apple watch would be the same because the averages are all the same.
Anyone who's taken, no, you all have taken stats, but
if you remember from stats, what's the problem then?
Just looking at this data or these data.
And you probably experienced this once or twice, if you ever
looked down at your watch and got a heart rate.
But looking at these data, what's the concerning piece to how this is displayed?
Yeah, not necessarily outliers, but the spread.
The spread is really, really wide.
So at any point in time, for this particular watch here,
you could have a ton of these data points that are 20%
different, 20% lower than what your actual heart rate is.
And the more spread you have, the more chances you look
down at your watch, and it's going to be way off.
But if you were to average all the values or record every single value
and then average them, yeah, I would agree you have just
as many below and above the line, and you probably would
get a decent measurement if you averaged your heart rate over five minutes.
And so that's why we need to be careful with some of these heart rate
measurements on a watch if we're just taking these like point values.
And I would agree the chest strap also has that but at
least the range is a little bit lower or the variance is a little bit lower.
So just something to kind of keep in mind when you're
using some of those straps or straps and watches.
Gold standard, obviously we want to do this EKG here.
We cannot run with an EKG machine all the time on a treadmill so we have to use some type of
heart rate monitor on the wrist or the chest.
But typically, if you're getting that measurement from the chest strap, it's a lot better.
OK.
All right.
I'm thinking this might be a good place to stop,
not necessarily to like, you're more than welcome to take off.
But I also think, one, because you're checked out, but two,
I'm happy to go over any last minute questions on chapter eight through 11.
So if you want to, you can hang around and we can go through that.
The one thing I will ask, though, is if you do hang around
or if you do take off, just try not to be too disturbing
as far as noise level, because it's hard for me to hear everybody.
But the exam on, oh, actually, really quick.
I know you already have this, but the exam,
It's 33 questions.
Let me pull this up really quick.
33 questions, multiple choice.
You have that one extra one here.
And then these are some of the pieces that I've already shown you.
But just keep this in mind.
Just don't forget your exams on Thursday.
And yeah.
The question that you got right will be question 33.
I put it at the very end.
Any other questions, logistics or content related?
And you don't have to stay around, so enjoy the day.
If not, I'm here.