Okay, welcome back everybody.
Good to see you, good to see you.
I hope you had a nice weekend.
We're gonna go ahead and get started by reviewing the
lab exam scores or the average or the histogram.
So for the Monday group and tonight and obviously tomorrow,
you'll be able to see your lab exam scores.
Please take a look at those scores for your written as well as the multiple choice.
If you have any questions, ask your TA.
If you feel like you would like to meet with me as
well on those lab exams, I'm more than happy to do that as well.
So here's the averages.
And I think you already know my feeling on how to explain some of these things.
But if you did relatively well, I wouldn't think that it was too easy of an exam.
So there were several people who got hundreds or a
handful of individuals, quite a few people who were in the high 90s as well.
So if you did well, great.
But don't think it was too easy because there were individuals who definitely
maybe didn't get as high of a score, and then same with the individuals who are down here.
So yeah, it was a difficult exam, but just know
that it wasn't impossible because there were people who still did quite well.
So again, if you are down over here, I would hope that you reach out to me sooner rather
than later so we can try and make some adjustments
or make some strategies to help finish strong for the rest of the semester.
So on that note, next week, we do have your second lecture exam on March 20th.
It will be from chapters eight through 11.
So if you remember last week, I had moved chapters 13, 14, and 20 to the final exam.
And then we're just working through eight through 11.
So we should be able to get through
the majority if not all of the material by Thursday.
On Tuesday we'll start the chapters 13, but that won't be part of your second exam.
So you'll have plenty of time to kind of prepare for the second lecture exam.
Any questions on that piece?
Yeah.
Yes, that is correct, yeah, yeah.
So we'll start the next set of slides will be the physiology of training.
And I will post those closer to Thursday.
If you haven't heard from me and you have some
sort of accommodation with exams, I would probably come up to
me after class and just check in with me really quick.
Because, yeah, if you haven't heard from me, I think it
would be good to just check in with me really quick to make sure we're on track.
So, okay.
I'm also holding quite a few office hours this week.
I'll post some office hours next week, but I will say this Friday section
or this Friday time slot from 12.30 to 2.30 in
Claire 111 and those back tables, that's pretty much I'm gonna be
there for the rest of the semester, so I know that slot is gonna be open.
But again, I'll try to sprinkle in some hours every now
and then, especially as we get closer to exams.
But this will be my permanent hours, and I've updated
that on the Canvas website, especially on that grid.
So if you ever want to look for my office hours, I'll be on here.
But I'll have some hours tomorrow as well as Thursday morning.
So if you would like to meet then, talk about
the upcoming material or the current material that we're in
for lecture exam two, I would highly recommend that.
OK, any questions on this stuff?
Nice.
OK, so we're going to finish respiration during exercise,
and then we'll move on to acid-base balance for chapter 11.
But on Thursday, we left off this concept on the oxygen hemoglobin dissociation curve.
Some of the big pieces here would be this is indicating
this arterial partial pressure of oxygen, and by default, meaning what we kind of know
for the partial pressure, or maybe the partial pressure of
oxygen in the blood, we kind of know where or what location we're talking about inside of the body.
So if we're looking at a partial pressure around 100,
Well, we know that's closer to the lungs and it's
arterial PO2 because that's when the red blood cells or the
hemoglobin molecules are doing the most of the oxygen loading.
And we know down by 40, well, this is a partial
pressure closer to what we would experience at rest.
And so this is kind of that mixed venous tissue partial pressure.
And so typically this location is first changing from 100 to 40 closer to the tissues.
The flat portion is really important or the sigmoidal curve is really important
because the flat portion helps defend against large changes
in pressure, meaning we only get small changes in saturation.
The steep portion is kind of flipped around.
We wanna encourage offloading of oxygen to the tissues.
So small changes in pressure, pressure results in large changes in saturation.
We then can look at kind of the difference or from the loading to the offloading.
So from this portion to this portion, we can kind of look
at how much O2 was delivered or the O2 content to the blood would give us this AVO2 difference over here.
I know I just,
reviewed it, but does anyone have any general questions about this graph?
OK.
So this is kind of base, right?
This is standard.
At rest, we're expecting, in general, like a pH of 7.4.
And our core body temperature is around 37 degrees Celsius.
And this is how
For most individuals, this is how everyone's graph or
hemoglobin dissociation curve is going to look.
Obviously, there's going to be some differences.
We'll talk about some, especially some genetic differences that might change this curve.
But in general, we can kind of say this is what we'd experience at rest.
But there are certain factors, specifically three factors,
that can modulate this oxygen hemoglobin dissociation curve.
The first one will be pH.
So if you increase the acidity or increase the
hydrogen ion concentration, it will decrease the pH.
If you decrease the pH, it lowers or reduces the affinity of oxygen to the hemoglobin molecules.
If it reduces the affinity, it favors offloading.
So it's easier for the oxygen molecules to kind of
leave the hemoglobin.
It also kind of makes it a little bit hard for
loading, but not in the magnitude that we would expect because of the flat portion.
And we'll take a look at that in just a second.
But any time you are changing the hemoglobin oxygen dissociation
curve due to pH, we call that the Bohr effect.
That's from the researcher who developed or discovered
this change in oxygen affinity to hemoglobin with pH.
OK, no surprise.
During intense exercise, there's an increase in the hydrogen
ion concentration, which is going to decrease the pH or make the blood a little bit more acidic.
And so that's going to be this curve here.
So the middle curve that we're looking at is the normal curve during rest or at normal pH levels.
And if we have a decrease in this pH or an
increase in acidity, then we're going to shift the curve to the right.
If it becomes more basic or an increase in pH, it's going
to shift the curve a little bit to the left.
The hydrogen ions or the acidity
is kind of interfering or binding or causing the ability
for the hemoglobin molecules to bind to the oxygen to reduce.
So the hydrogen ions are reducing the hemoglobin's ability to transport O2.
A nice way to look at what kind of happens
with shifts in your hemoglobin dissociation curve would be to just
pick one of these points that we've been talking about.
So at 40, at rest, if I all of a sudden was
kind of experiencing some type of decrease in pH or acidity, then at
40, all I'm going to do is just draw a line up
and it looks like I'm around 60% saturation.
Compared to, if I keep going up, well maybe 75% saturation at rest.
So you saw that there was a decrease in the saturation
with an increase in acidity or decrease in pH.
And then same if we go all the way up.
So if I start at 40 and I'm working my way up
here and then I get to this more basic concentration here, it's around 85.
And then you can do the same for a given saturation.
So at 50% saturation, what is the partial pressure needed to achieve that saturation?
So you can go from the y-axis over and then drop lines down.
Another factor or an effect on the oxygen hemoglobin dissociation curve would be temperature.
If you have an increase in blood temperature, that also
lowers the affinity of oxygen to the hemoglobin molecule, which
then would also shift the curve to the right.
As expected during exercise, we have an increase in core body temperature.
The increase in temperature weakens the bond between
the oxygen and the hemoglobin molecules, which then assists in
the unloading of oxygen to the working tissues.
Same deal, right?
Like 37 degrees is this middle graph or the middle sigmoidal curve.
I'll just take one point.
You can do any point on here.
Just draw a line up.
As soon as you hit one of the graphs, move it
over to the y-axis and see what happened to saturation.
So as we mentioned, the interesting thing or the nice
thing about the sigmoidal curve, on the steep portion, we're getting these large changes in saturation.
But on the flat portion,
At 100, this is a very minor change.
And so even 32, if you started drawing this line all
the way over, we're seeing deltas of like two or
three percentage point differences between those different curves.
So very small changes here, but very large changes here.
Although I will mention 42 degrees is a little extreme.
So hyperthermia is around 40 degrees C. So we typically would
not see this a whole lot in vivo, in the human.
A lot of this is done in a Petri dish where they heat it up.
But you can kind of see how the curve still shifts.
Any questions on temperature?
OK, the last one is 2,3-DPG, diphosphoglycerate.
Sometimes it's BPG as well as bifospho, so DPG, BPG.
It's a byproduct of red blood cell glycolysis.
So there are no mitochondria inside the red blood cells.
So they need to undergo glycolysis to produce energy.
And one of those byproducts is 2,3-DPG.
2,3-DPG also causes a rightward shift of the curve.
Here's one thing to note, though.
It's not a major cause of the rightward shift during exercise at sea level.
We just don't produce enough of this at sea level, especially during exercise.
during both acute exposure to high altitude in rest and
ice, we do see a relatively large increase in this 2,3-DPG.
So when we get to altitude, the altitude chapters will
briefly touch on how this kind of shifts the hemoglobin dissociation curve.
But,
Regardless, this does increase with exercise.
So the one thing that we've kind of picked up where I
guess, yeah, the one thing that we picked up for all
of these three things, what direction are they changing with exercise?
Say again?
Yeah, everything's shifting to the right because all of these things are maybe like
pH is a tricky one, it's not really increasing,
but you're increasing the acidity, you're increasing the temperature, and you're increasing 2,3-BPG.
All of those should make sense to you when you exercise.
Your body gets warmer when you exercise, it becomes a little bit more acidic due to exercise,
and you're kind of undergoing glycolysis a little bit more,
but again, that's more inside of the red blood cell,
but still, all of those are increasing during exercise, so you can just think,
During exercise, there's a rightward shift to the oxygen hemoglobin dissociation curve.
You don't need to worry about which one's more, which one's less, except for maybe this one.
This is not a major cause of a rightward shift
during exercise at sea level, but during altitude it is.
But regardless, they all shift the curve to the right.
So even if you forget, oh, man, what happened to temperature?
Does it shift it left, or does it shift it right?
Just think about what happens during exercise, and
anything that happens during exercise, it shifts it to the right.
And then reverse is to the left, right?
Cold, basic, less two, three DPGs to the left.
Okay.
So yeah, this is the normal curve on here.
Oh, sorry, the dotted line here is the normal curve.
All of those three things that we talked about shifts it to the right.
So it shifts this curve to the right.
And the nice thing about that is now we're encouraging and offloading
of the oxygen and molecules, so we get a larger AVO2 difference compared to at rest.
So this line or this arrow right here is indicating the AVO2 difference at rest,
and then now this line right here is indicating the
AVO2 difference at exercise, and that's due to a shift
in the oxygen hemoglobin dissociation curve to the right.
Yeah, so it's just we're able to deliver more oxygen to the tissues.
Yeah, yeah, no, that's a good question.
Okay.
Any other questions on this?
All right, that means you are so ready for this clicker question.
What is the result of a rightward shift in
the oxygen hemoglobin dissociation curve during exercise?
Oh man.
Okay, let's get something in here.
I'll close this down in 15 seconds.
Does anyone need more time getting their clicker set up?
Okay, about five seconds.
Three, two, one.
Okay, how did we do?
Nice job, nice job.
This is the correct answer.
oxygen on unloading becomes easier at the muscles, right?
We wanna be able to deliver more oxygen to the
tissues because during exercise, there's a larger decrease or demand in oxygen.
So there's a decrease in that pressure of oxygen.
So we wanna deliver more oxygen to create energy for exercise.
Any questions on this clicker question?
You've probably noticed that some of these clicker questions,
at least in these last past slide decks for the second
unit, hopefully they're looking more familiar to an exam question.
They're worded, in my opinion, a little bit more familiar.
But this one was really, well, I don't want to say easy, but it was a little more straightforward.
Okay, changes in arterial venous O2 content during exercise.
We've already touched on this, that as you increase
in intensity, there's a larger AVO2 difference, and that's
because, again, cellular respiration at the muscles, that is increasing,
so we wanna be able to deliver more oxygen.
So no surprise that the AVO2 difference is greater.
So we've already seen this slide here.
But one of the things we kind of not skipped over, but saved for now would be,
okay, well, if the hemoglobin molecules are now delivering
the oxygen, the oxygen has to now diffuse across the membrane and then find its way to the muscle.
Well, oxygen doesn't really diffuse in liquid very well, so it needs some sort of carrier.
And so in the blood we have hemoglobin,
In the muscles we have myoglobin, or in the tissues for the muscles.
So here you have your capillary, you have your endothelium,
and then we have the myoglobin that are kind of over here
capturing the oxygen, so then we can deliver it to the mitochondria.
So myoglobin helps shuttle the oxygen from the cell
membrane to the mitochondria of the skeletal and cardiac muscle fibers.
One thing to keep in mind, and we'll see a
different curve here, but the partial pressure of oxygen
in the mitochondria for contracting skeletal muscle, that can get all
the way down to like one or two, as far as the partial pressure of oxygen.
So it's getting way down there.
Even though our mixed venous blood is around 40,
while the mitochondria are experiencing some pretty low partial pressures of oxygen.
Okay, myoglobin content is high in type I fibers and lower
in type IIX fibers and then a moderate amount or in between for those type IIA fibers.
And this should make sense, right?
Like we have a higher density of myoglobin and
the ones that are undergoing oxidative phosphorylation at the highest rate.
The only way this transport system works is if myoglobin
has a higher affinity for oxygen than hemoglobin.
In particular, it can bind to oxygen at very low partial pressures.
So if that's the case, then myoglobin has its own oxygen dissociation curve.
This one is not very sigmoidal.
Mono-exponential, you could probably call this, but here you still
see a steep portion and a flat portion.
The one thing to note would be that the flat portion
or the flatter portion for the myoglobin are over the steep portion of the hemoglobin.
so that when the hemoglobin are offloading oxygen, that
is the partial pressure where myoglobin is loading.
So again, saturation with oxygen is on the y-axis, the
partial pressure of oxygen is on the x here, the blue,
is myoglobin and the red is hemoglobin.
So this would be the unloading portion or the steep
portion here for the hemoglobin and then the flatter loading portion for the hemoglobin on this side.
So when the hemoglobin molecules are unloading, they are offloading to the myoglobin
and then the myoglobin, their steep portion is more
closely associated with the partial pressures that we experience in the mitochondria.
That way the myoglobin can easily release oxygen to
the tissues, or particularly the mitochondria, at these lower partial pressures.
Yeah.
Why is the hemoglobin curve still increasing its oxygen?
It's unloaded.
Say that one more time.
So why?
Why is the hemoglobin curve still increasing its oxygen?
Yeah, maybe I'm still not quite understanding that, but you
could almost think of it going from right to left.
Does that help a little bit?
So like over here, we're in the arterial blood.
And then when we get to the venous blood, this piece here, the steeper portion is offloading.
And so the hemoglobin themselves are decreasing in saturation here.
And then you can almost think of it as the saturation
on the myoglobin are remaining high or going back to high or picking up the oxygen here.
And then,
This location, this region right here, if I were to
put another dotted line, I could put another dotted line
right here and say like mitochondria partial pressure.
Does that help a little bit?
Okay.
Any questions on this curve or these curves?
Okay, let's get some practice here.
When the partial pressure of oxygen is approximately 25
millimeters of mercury, what are myoglobin and hemoglobin doing respectively?
Go about a minute longer.
Feel free to chat with your classmates.
Convince them otherwise or support their.
Okay, we'll go maybe 15 seconds from now, unless someone needs a little more time than that.
Okay, I'll close it down in five seconds.
I think we have everybody in.
All right, three, two, one.
Okay, nice.
Nice job.
It is C.
So here's my pointer down here.
If we are looking closer to this 20, 25, so maybe 25
is just barely over here because 30 is over here, so maybe 25 is here.
I bring it up.
If saturation of the hemoglobin molecules are at 25 and
they just came from the lungs at around 100, what has just happened
I guess, yeah, what has just happened?
I mean, it says it on there, but.
So we're at the lungs and the arterial blood.
The oxygen gets pumped to the muscle.
And then down over here, the oxygen, is it still on the hemoglobin molecules?
No, yeah, so it gets released.
So it's basically at this point in time unloading.
And then the myoglobin are picking up the oxygen.
So those are the ones loading.
So if we're looking at myoglobin at this partial pressure here, we're seeing that it is loading.
So that's loading over here.
And then the hemoglobin molecules are unloading.
Questions on this?
Okay.
One thing to note, too, since we touched on this
before, oxygen deficit and EPOC, the myoglobin O2 store serve as an O2 reserve.
So even at rest, we have kind of all the
myoglobin molecules 100% saturated or close to 100% saturated.
And so they help kind of deliver some of
that oxygen relatively quickly during the transitory period from rest to exercise.
After exercise, if you remember those five factors that were contributing to EPOC,
well, we need to replenish those oxygen stores, and so
we kind of have that elevated oxygen consumption after exercise, or EPOC.
We okay here?
Nice, all right.
Okay, CO2 transport in the blood.
So now we're still over here, but now we're talking about CO2, almost on this side of things.
Carbon dioxide is a little bit different than oxygen in the
fact that it can dissolve a lot better into fluid or liquids like water compared to oxygen.
Because of that, we actually do get a relatively
substantial amount of CO2 that dissolves into plasma.
In particular, approximately 10%.
This is a relatively wide range, especially as we shift
on this curve, which we'll talk about in just a little bit.
But we can get a lot of CO2 dissolved into the plasma.
On average, at rest, maybe 10% is dissolved into the plasma.
We can get a little bit bound to hemoglobin.
The rest travels inside of the blood as bicarbonate.
We're gonna go through this curve or at least this kind of reaction a couple times.
The one thing to note, it goes both ways, right?
So if I have carbon dioxide, it combines relatively
quickly or dissociates relatively quickly into carbonic acid.
We typically don't like carbonic acid in fluids.
And so just like lactic acid, it dissociates into
bicarbonate and a hydrogen ion relatively quickly.
So if we have high concentrations of CO2, it generally pushes the curve towards the right.
And then if we have higher concentrations of hydrogens,
they generally push the curve towards the left.
And you may have remembered the bicarb buffering system here.
pairs relatively well with the chloride shift.
So we have an increase.
So this is at the tissues.
So we're looking at the tissues here.
We have an increase in CO2 production from cellular metabolism.
We then have some of that CO2 dissolve into the plasma.
Some of it binds with hemoglobin, as we mentioned before.
The rest undergoes that bicarb buffering, and then we
have that chloride shift where a chloride comes in and the bicarb comes out.
Then the blood moves through the systemic circuit, reaches
the pulmonary circuit to the lungs, so we can then exhale.
a carbon dioxide.
So then we have the chloride shift again that converts your bicarb back to CO2.
The CO2 also kind of unbinds from the hemoglobin as well
as the dissolved CO2 in the plasma are encouraged to enter the alveoli so then we can exhale.
What do we think is the cause that is allowing for
this shift of CO2 in the direction that favors us at the tissues and the lungs?
What's encouraging that?
What's the only way this can happen?
Say again?
Yeah, the partial pressure.
The partial pressure of CO2 is extremely, not extremely, but it's very high.
at the tissues, especially the muscles, because again, they're undergoing cellular respiration.
So there's this high concentration of CO2 in the mitochondria.
It gets pushed out into the blood.
And so naturally, it's going to favor this type of reaction.
Anyone remember what the partial pressure of CO2 is in the air, in the environment?
Yeah, I think I heard someone say it, but 0.03%, so 0.000.
I think I added one more.
But it's a very, very small fraction of CO2 inside
of the alveoli, because we're breathing that low concentration of CO2 in.
Well, we're sending a high concentration or a higher partial pressure of CO2 to the lungs.
And so naturally, it's going to want to diffuse into the alveoli.
Are you okay there?
All right.
So then that should make this next part relatively straightforward.
The pulmonary ventilation removes hydrogen from the blood by the bicarb reaction.
So it's gonna encourage the movement towards CO2 so we can exhale that out.
So the lung is gonna move it towards this way.
The muscle goes the other way because we have a
higher concentration of CO2 in the muscle compared to the blood.
If you increase ventilation, then we are increasing the amount
of CO2 that we are exhaling into the environment.
This helps reduce the partial pressure of CO2 as well as reduce the hydrogen concentration.
If you reduce the hydrogen concentration, pH increases.
If you decrease, yeah.
So this counteracts the hydrogen ion increase you were talking about earlier?
Yes.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
So this helps us deal with this large increase in hydrogen ion concentration or this drop in pH.
and you all have probably felt this before if you hold your breath, but
if you decrease ventilation, this then causes a buildup
of CO2, increases the pressure pressure of CO2, as well
as increases the number of hydrogen ions, which then decreases the pH.
Okay.
So if you ever
kind of forget about which direction this reaction is going.
Just think about the two locations, lung and the muscle.
What's the partial pressure or what's the percentage of CO2 in the air that we breathe in?
What's the percentage of CO2 at the mitochondria
when we're living because it's undergoing cellular respiration, so it's producing a lot of CO2?
And that should help determine which way this reaction
drives, either over towards bicarb or over towards CO2.
Okay, so then we're gonna move on to this next
question of does the pulmonary system limit exercise performance?
Before we answer that question, we're gonna do a
little bit of background about changes in ventilation and
arterial gases during the transition from rest to moderate exercise.
So if we have submaximal exercise where steady state is achieved, so if we're looking here,
we have submaximal exercise for six minutes, and we
have ventilation PCO2 and PO2, partial pressure of O2 and partial pressure of CO2.
During this transition, we then reach steady state of ventilation.
And we can see that the partial pressure of oxygen
and the partial pressure of CO2 are stable throughout steady state for submaximal exercise.
OK.
One little caveat that I'll put to this is if
we have this submaximal exercise and we're achieving steady state
with ventilation and I heat up the room, what do you think will happen?
Any ideas?
If you heat up the room, do you think it'll get easier or harder to do the exercise?
Harder, yeah.
And so we typically would see this kind of drift
So same kind of graph, but we have exercise duration for 50 minutes.
The blue line is for cool environment.
The red line is for a hot environment.
And we have ventilation and partial pressure of CO2.
The interesting thing here, if I have ventilation not
changing in a cool environment, then it increases
in a hot environment, what would we expect to see as far as the exhalation of CO2?
Should we generate increase?
Yeah, that's what I would expect too based on what we just talked about.
If you increase ventilation, you're exhaling more CO2 molecules.
But look at the top graph.
The partial pressure of CO2 is not different between hot and cool conditions.
Well, that's weird.
How does that happen?
Any thoughts on that?
Only because I mentioned this very briefly last week.
Is there a way we can increase ventilation without
actually changing the concentration of some of these molecules?
No guesses?
So if you remember, there's something called an anatomical dead space.
And when you hyperventilate, due to increases in temperature,
your breathing frequency typically increases, but your tidal volume
starts to either stay the same or get a little bit lower.
So you're actually not taking deeper breaths, you're just increasing the frequency.
And so it's believed that most individuals, unless
you actively think about changing your breathing, if I all heat
up, or heat up this room and everyone starts to hyperventilate a little bit, it'll be due mainly
to this exchange of this anatomical dead space which is
not interacting with the alveoli inside of the lungs.
And so it's believed that this increase in ventilation
or this panting or this increase in frequency is just to exhale more heat out.
So I kind of mentioned like certain animals do this
because a lot of animals don't actually sweat like humans.
And so the main way they release heat is to pant.
And so again, this is really theorized to be a thermoregulatory behavior.
But it's quite interesting.
Okay, but at a certain point in time with graded exercise,
if we get to a high enough intensity, we see there is a substantial change in the slope of ventilation.
So it doesn't increase linearly across all speeds.
We hit this ventilatory threshold, which is very closely
linked to lactate threshold, and we see this exponential increase in ventilation.
Well, once we get past that, in this area,
we are seeing some changes in the partial pressure of CO2.
And so we do see arterial PCO2 drop a little
bit with this kind of exponential increase in ventilation.
But if we're just talking about untrained individuals,
so graded exercise in untrained individuals, the pulmonary system
is not seen as a limitation during submaximal exercise.
The biggest support for this would be even during
hyperventilation, these individuals are able to maintain their arterial PO2.
So there's no drop in the partial pressure of oxygen in the lungs.
So in that manner, we're thinking at least the lungs
are able to maintain the partial pressure of oxygen and be
able to encourage diffusion of oxygen into the blood.
And then now there are other problems with delivering that
blood to the tissue, but at least the lungs are doing their job.
No surprise here though, even in untrained individuals, we
are seeing a dramatic drop in the arterial pH.
Okay, so if this is untrained individuals, let's look at trained individuals.
So for untrained individuals, we don't believe there's a limitation for the pulmonary system,
but we do have some evidence that suggests that
highly trained elite endurance athletes during maximal exercise
might have some type of mechanical limitation for the lung, right?
Even these individuals,
their lung is as big as it's going to get.
And so eventually when they're trying to move enough
air into the lungs, there's just mechanical limitations.
We just can't push any more air into the lungs.
And so therefore at that point in time, it becomes a little bit problematic.
We also see in these highly trained individuals where they're
the ones who are able to fatigue out their muscles
on a more regular basis compared to untrained individuals.
Typically if you took a sedentary individual or someone
who's even recreationally active and you got them to do
a high intensity exercise, their legs will give out before their lungs.
And that's just because they're just, they're not very active
at that point in time and so they're really not pushing their lungs to the max.
But we do see some respiratory muscle fatigue during
prolonged high intensity exercise for these highly trained athletes.
Another interesting concept here.
40% to 50% of these elite endurance athletes
experience something called exercise-induced arterial hypoxemia, where
If on this graph we have partial pressure of oxygen on the Y and work rate on the X axis,
that as we increase intensity, there's usually a certain
point around lactate threshold where all of a sudden we get
this dramatic drop in the partial pressure of oxygen.
Any ideas as to why this might happen in these elite athletes?
Yeah.
Yeah, what was that last part?
So yeah, I agree that they're working so hard.
Sorry.
I got the lab part, but there's a high partial pressure oxygen.
Yeah, so I agree with you that at a high
intensity exercise, they are unable to maintain this partial
pressure of oxygen inside of the arteries, right?
So typically, we're at 100, and we want to see
this 100 all the way throughout all exercise intensities like we see it with the untrained individuals.
But what's unique that we've talked about earlier in this slide
deck, as well as some of the other slides, about the trained hands.
Yeah, so the transit time is one of the biggest players that are contributing to this piece here.
And so I guess I should have let you all talk about it, but the transit time.
Well, then let me ask you this.
What is causing this substantial decrease in transit time?
Why isn't transit time an issue for the untrained individuals?
has to do something with cardiac output.
What's cardiac output kind of made of?
How can we calculate cardiac output based on the FIC equation?
Heart rate times stroke volume.
Does heart rate typically go up with endurance training?
Or do we see maximum heart rate higher in endurance trained athletes versus untrained?
Yeah, I agree, no.
So it has to be then.
Stroke volume, right?
So untrained individuals, we see a plateau in that stroke volume.
Then when we see some of the elite groups, we see
either no plateau or very late plateau in stroke volume,
which means they have a relatively high cardiac output.
If they have a high cardiac output or stroke volume, then
this blood is gonna be moving past this alveoli much
faster at these higher intensities compared to untrained individuals.
So this is one of the theories as to why we're getting a decrease in this saturation.
There's another one, and that has to do with the oxygen hemoglobin dissociation curve.
Any ideas there?
Yeah, yeah, I think, yep, and I think I, yeah, there we go, yeah, yeah, yeah.
So it's a decrease in pH or increase in acidity, and
typically we see that a little bit of a higher rate compared to these.
untrained individuals, and yeah, there's a small change at
the lungs, at that flat portion, but that also contributes to this piece.
So now you have a little bit of a drop or shift to the right in the partial pressure,
or shift to the right in the oxygen hemoglobin dissociation curve, so then
that partial pressure starts to become a little bit more
of an impact, plus we have this decrease in transit
time, which is really causing this exercise-induced desaturation.
There's some other parameters that we'll talk about
during altitude, but sometimes there's mixing of oxygenated and
deoxygenated blood in the heart due to some anatomical differences,
as well as transit time in other areas.
So we'll touch on this in altitude.
This is more for fun.
OK, any questions up to this point?
All right.
Let's move on to Chapter 11 then.
Acid base balance during exercise.
Okay, so for this one, I feel like it's a really good segue because we just talked about
how the ventilatory system is very good at helping us
balance some of these high increases in CO2 and subsequent
increases in hydrogen ions, so we can exhale that and try to defend against those as long as possible.
So it's gonna be a relatively short kind of spec here, but we're gonna go
through the hydrogen, let me get my pointer out, the hydrogen ion production during exercise,
and then how we regulate that balance during exercise, and how
the kidneys play a role in this, as well as what happens after exercise.
Okay, hydrogen ion production during exercise.
No surprise because we just saw this, hydrogen production
does depend on exercise intensity and the amount of muscle
mass involved as well as the duration of exercise.
You guys getting a buzzing?
Is that bothersome?
Okay, hopefully that's better.
Okay, duration of exercise, exercise intensity, as well as the amount
or number of muscles that are involved are going to
increase or change the amount of hydrogen ions that are produced.
It should make sense that the location where these hydrogen
ions are being produced in the highest concentration or the most
amounts would be at the muscle and a different concentration than the blood.
So muscle pH declines more dramatically than blood pH.
And we can see that over here on the x-axis that has work rate.
Arterial blood pH, so what's in the blood, and muscle pH here.
So they look like they have the same kind of decline.
But one of the big things would be muscle pH drops first, much earlier in the exercise intensity.
And second, the magnitude of decline is much different.
So here we're going from 6.99, or basically 7 here.
And we're going all the way down to 6.2.
So almost a delta of 0.8, whereas here we're going from 7.4 to 7.
It's almost double.
So then you might ask yourself, what are the sources
that are contributing to this hydrogen ion production in the skeletal muscle?
No surprise here, because we just already talked about it.
Carbonic acid or that CO2 production, that's going to move
or shift the curve down, get carbonic acid, bicarb, then the hydrogen ions.
So you get these hydrogen ions.
Any time you go or undergo glycolysis, you create pyruvate.
Pyruvate might bump into lactate dehydrogenase and that's gonna create lactate.
As soon as you get lactic acid, it immediately
dissociates into lactate and hydrogen ions, so those hydrogen ions are contributing.
Any time you break down ATP, you also are releasing hydrogen ions.
So these are all contributing to this kind of pool
of hydrogen ions that are increasing the acidity or decreasing the pH.
Okay, so let's look at all three of these pieces here in a little bit more detail,
not a whole lot more, but production of carbon dioxide comes
from the Krebs cycle, as well as the movement of pyruvate to acetyl-CoA.
So any time you move a three carbon to a two carbon,
not anytime, but at least in cellular respiration, you are exhaling a CO2,
and then through the Krebs cycle here, you are releasing,
you are kind of breaking down and building up those
carbon chains, and you're releasing those CO2 molecules.
Again, if you're creating more CO2, you're gonna push this
curve to the right, which then causes an increase in these hydrogen ions.
I just mentioned this production of lactic acid quickly
dissociates into lactate as well as this hydrogen.
ATP breakdown.
Well, this also results in a release of a hydrogen ion.
So we have ATP hydrolyzes with water.
You get your ADP, your phosphate over here, and then you get your hydrogen ion.
Are we OK here?
All right.
So you might be thinking, okay, yes, increase in hydrogen
ions are decreasing the pH, creating a more acidic environment, which could be problematic.
But how would, or what would the mechanism be for hydrogen ions to maybe impair performance?
One of those would be the inhibition of enzymes anaerobic and anaerobic ATP production.
specifically PFK.
So it is a little interesting that PFK, the rate
limiting enzyme for glycolysis, is inhibited or kind of damaged
or unable to function at its normal capacity with a decrease in pH.
So it inhibits enzymes in both the oxidative and non-oxidative formation of ATP.
The second piece here, I don't know if I'm gonna be
able to do this, the second one, hydrogen ions can also bind to troponin.
Well, that's a spot for calcium.
If you take up the same spot for calcium, well, now we're not gonna get the conformational change.
So you're not gonna be able to move tropomycin and
open those binding sites for actin to now connect with the myosin head.
So now we're preventing the cross-bridge from forming and
muscles to contract at their full capability if we have too high of a hydrogen ion concentration.
So yeah, independent of pH changes, we can impair performance
through this binding of the troponin.
So it takes up a spot that calcium otherwise would take.
There are other things that
kind of are out of the scope of this class,
but high hydrogen ion concentration also disturbs the sarcoplasmic
reticulum from kind of releasing and uptaking calcium.
So that kind of impairs that area as well.
So these are not the only two areas that hydrogen
ions or a decrease in pH are impairing performance.
These are just the two major ones that you will need to know for this course.
Any questions here?
And I feel like I'm gonna get through all of this today, which isn't necessarily bad.
Okay, regulation of acid-base balance during exercise here.
Okay, changes in arterial concentrations of bicarbonate, lactate,
and pH changes during graded exercise tests.
A little bit more of the same story.
If I have a baseline kind of bicarb level here,
then that should be enough to maintain pH across some of these easier workloads.
As soon as we have a decrease in pH or substantial
increase in the number of hydrogen ions, we are then going
to utilize the bicarb to then buffer those hydrogen ions.
And so the bicarb is going to decrease.
We don't have unlimited amount of bicarb, so the bicarb is
going to decrease, and so the pH is going to continue to decrease.
So the acid-base balance is maintained by buffers.
It releases hydrogen ions when pH is high, so it's a
little too basic, and we need to bring that pH back down to that normal set point.
and it accepts hydrogen ions when pH is low.
So if there are too many hydrogen ions, the buffer will
then try to grab onto one of those hydrogens to try to help increase the pH or reduce the acidity.
We are more familiar with bicarb, but there are other buffers.
We're gonna talk about those lines of defense against pH changes during exercise.
in particular, high intensity exercise.
Because during these lower intensity exercises, maybe submaximal
exercises, we're usually able to maintain the pH relatively well.
It's not until we get to these higher intensity exercises, especially at maximum.
Okay, so the first line of defense.
We're gonna go over two pieces here.
One, the cellular buffer system.
This is inside of the muscle cell or the cell themselves.
It's not until later that we have maybe some blood buffer systems.
So once we get spillover into the blood, then we have the second kind of piece to deal with.
So the first line of defense against the muscle pH
changes will be these four major classes of intracellular chemical buffers.
So bicarb, phosphates, proteins, and carnosine.
You don't really need to know the magnitude, but in general,
bicarbonate is about 20 to 30% of the buffering capacity inside of the cell.
And then if we're looking at some of these phosphates, they're around 10 to 20%.
And the phosphates are basically converting a strong acid into a weaker acid.
So it doesn't eliminate them, but it definitely attenuates
some of the acidity inside of the solution.
Proteins and carnosine here, they accept
Hydrogen ions, in inside of the cell, they are
responsible for about 60% of the buffering capacity.
So carnosine is quite important in accepting some of those hydrogen ions.
Well, like most things, right, if we have just too much
We have an excess inside of the room.
What's the best way to get rid of it?
Let's just throw it out, right?
Like transport the hydrogen ions out of the muscle.
Let's get these hydrogen ions out.
We can't buffer it inside of the cell because our
chemical buffering mechanisms are just kind of maxed out.
We can't really handle it anymore.
Time to ship it off.
How do we ship those off?
Well, we have two major transporters.
So we have hydrogen ion transporters in the skeletal muscle.
So here we have the interstitial space and then we
have the skeletal muscle where the majority of the hydrogen ions are being produced.
This one over here is a sodium.
So the N is for sodium.
The H is for hydrogen.
And the E is for exchangers.
This is a sodium-hydrogen exchanger.
And so you are, as it sounds, exchanging a sodium for a hydrogen molecule.
So you bring a sodium ion in.
You send the hydrogen molecule out.
This is a mono carboxylate transporter or an MCT transporter.
This one moves lactate as well as hydrogen out at the same time.
Okay, compared to slow type one fibers, fast or type two fibers have a higher buffering capacity.
So on all or both of those, both chemical and the
transporting of the hydrogen ions are a little bit better than some of the type two fibers.
If you undergo high intensity training for prolonged periods
of time, you are improving the chemical kind of buffering capacity.
In particular, you are improving the carnosine as well as the hydrogen ion transporters.
So if you remember, the carnosine was 60% of the chemical buffering capacity.
Well, if you undergo high intensity training, or just
training in general, you are improving the carnosine as well as these transporters here.
Are we good there?
All right.
So we'll start with the second line of defense on Thursday.
We'll finish this up.
We'll probably start the physiology of training slides, but just
know that that's not part of your second lecture exam.
Again, if you haven't heard from me and you have exam accommodations, please come talk to me.