Thank you.
Okay, let's get started.
Welcome back, everyone.
So we're gonna finish up chapter six, exercise in the immune system.
So this is the last slide deck that will be on your exam this Thursday.
At the end of this, I'll give some more details on the
exam as well as we'll have plenty of time for some questions if you have any.
So like review type questions.
I'll even have a few clicker questions that might be
more closely worded to how the exam might be worded and
potentially at a little bit of a closer difficulty level
compared to some of the previous clicker questions we've had.
So if you have any questions about the exam, we'll go over that towards the end of lecture.
Sound okay?
All right.
So we left off on this concept of the J-curve
And this is basically just giving us an idea if we
have a risk for an upper respiratory tract infection.
No exercise or being sedentary will put us at the normal baseline risk.
And even though we're depressing this, this is a decrease
in the risk of experiencing an upper respiratory tract infection
if you have some sort of moderate exercise activity.
And then as you get into heavier exertion, then that
becomes a little bit more problematic and you're increasing
the risk of experiencing upper respiratory tract infection.
So this is a pretty good model, but.
I wanna start us off today with thinking about
some potential factors that may influence the J-curve model.
And especially if we're looking at those elite endurance
athletes or elite athletes who are maybe consistently on the further end of the J-curve.
So let's take a couple minutes, chat with your
classmates, and we'll come back together after that.
Okay, what are we thinking here?
Can I get some thoughts of what you kind of touched on?
So there's this idea, right?
As you increase in exercise intensity and duration, right,
the heavier you're exerting yourself to do exercise consistently
over time, you're increasing the risk for experiencing an upper respiratory tract infection.
But maybe there's something else going on that might influence the J curve.
What do we think might also be influencing this curve?
With elite athletes, especially, they're used to a higher
level of exercise or higher intensity of exercise.
So their bodies may be more
Yeah, so that is true that as we continue to
exercise regularly, you do improve your immune system.
But I guess the other side to that is let's just
assume that even though they have an improved immune system,
that as they continue to exert themselves a little bit
more than a recreationally active individual, they start to
increase the number of upper respiratory tract infections.
And so the question maybe is, is it just intensity
and duration, or is there something else maybe contributing to this?
Yeah, so there's a lot of different maybe psychological
stresses associated with being an elite athlete, and that might contribute to a depressed immune system.
We will later talk about how cortisol release does
depress the immune system function a little bit, so that's a good one.
What else?
Yeah, yeah.
So depending on when you're exercising or some of these
teams, they have to wake up really, really early.
And maybe they're not getting as much sleep as they should be getting in the first place.
And then you wake them up really early, and then you
have them train one or two times throughout the day.
And their sleep is being impacted.
In addition, if they're traveling a lot and they're
crossing all these time zones, maybe their sleep is becoming a little bit more disrupted.
That's a good one.
Anything else?
Yeah, there are a few others.
Same with the travel piece.
If I'm always traveling, maybe you're just exposing or I'm being exposed to more pathogens.
I'm going to, maybe I'm on a bus or I'm at the
airport, and there are just more chances for me to get exposed to certain pathogens.
Mental stress, like someone had mentioned earlier.
Diet could be a little bit of an issue because they're always training.
There are some reported differences between sex.
So they saw that elite females preparing or competing in
the Olympics had an increased risk for an upper respiratory tract infection.
These are just all some other factors to think about when we're looking at that J-curve model.
So yes, elite endurance athletes are typically towards that
end of high intensity exercise all the time, but some of these
other factors could also be in play, and we just need to kind of keep that in mind.
But regular exercise reduces the risk of an upper
respiratory tract infection approximately 16 to 67% and less than
60 minutes of exercise at around 50% VO2 max is all you
really need to help improve or reduce the risk of an upper respiratory tract infection.
Some of the mechanisms explaining that, we touched on a few of these on Thursday,
but if we're improving immunosurveillance or kind of hiding,
like our immune system is a little bit heightened, so we can better fight off some pathogens.
If we have that regular kind of submaximal exercise,
sometimes we see some associations with less emotional stress.
If I'm active,
Sometimes that makes individuals want to eat a little
bit better, so better nutrition has also been reported.
And then adequate sleep, sort of the reverse side, right?
If I'm not always doing two a days, early in the
morning, late at night, then the likelihood of you getting
maybe a little bit better sleep with some regular exercise is possible.
Okay, so this is a moderate exercise.
and we're protecting against infection.
If we go back to the high intensity, long duration
aerobic exercise, this increases the risk for infection like we had mentioned or saw on the J-curve model.
The reason for this is something called the open window.
This open window is an increased risk of infection.
One of the mechanisms to potentially explain this would be
that we see some higher cortisol levels in these individuals
who are experiencing this type of exercise activity.
Like we touched on, there are other factors that might be in play.
But as far as cortisol and some of the other suppressive
effects of the immune system, if we have time on the x-axis
and then the baseline is kind of that dotted line,
And then on the top of it, we have this kind of improved immune function or system.
And then below it is immunosuppression or you're decreasing the immunosurveillance.
As you're exercising over here, there happens to be a little bit of an improvement.
But if we keep getting into this kind of increase in duration or after the exercise,
we see this acute depression in our immune function.
And so if you do an intense high intensity exercise
here, as you are recovering, there's this window where you
have potentially an increased risk for getting some type of infection.
Again, this is with that high intensity exercise.
So there's a pretty good paper kind of supporting this model or this idea of the open window.
So in 2019, a paper was published on the temporary immune dysfunction after heavy exercise.
So if we're looking in the dark blue lines here, these
are a marathon race where the light blue are walking bouts.
So you don't need to know all of these over here, but essentially,
If we are on the left side of this line right here,
this is a negative change or a depression of the immune system.
This over here for these ones are inflammatory markers.
So they're getting a greater change in inflammation due to
the marathon race compared to a walking bout.
So definitely something's going on, especially after
a high-intensity, long-duration kind of exercise event.
But luckily, it is an acute kind of depression.
So it will kind of come back up.
So then this idea of increasing the risk, if you have an intense exercise bout
and then right after that, maybe you're traveling or you're meeting with individuals
or you're having some type of press conference and you're in a crowded room,
it's possible that now they are just in this kind
of depressive state for their immune system and they're more likely to get an infection.
Say again?
Number of hours kind of like post-exercise.
Oh, well, yeah, so I guess it depends, because they always go hand in hand.
Like in this one, they're kind of saying, OK, we're exercising over here for one to two hours.
Is that kind of what you're asking?
Yeah, yeah.
Well, every day.
No, per day.
Yeah, so if I undergo one exercise bout,
After that, I'll see that open window.
Then the next day, if I have another exercise bowel, I'll just have another open window.
And so if I'm exercising every day at that type
of intensity, I'm just having this window that's open for
me to have an increased risk for upper respiratory tract infection or any type of infection.
Okay, with that being said though, overall,
We have these temporary depressions of the immune system and temporary increases in inflammation.
But on a whole, if you look at a resting athlete versus a sedentary athlete,
or not a sedentary athlete, but a sedentary individual
or an obese individual, we actually see that the resting
levels of inflammatory markers are much higher in the sedentary group compared to the athletic group.
So the idea here is that moderate exercise training
in general is unlikely to maybe eliminate inflammation.
But we can slowly try to change the body composition
and undergo some chronic exercise to help us decrease the risk of maybe having these
chronic inflammatory, I guess, states or areas or inflammatory markers in our blood.
Any questions on this one here?
Again, these pieces right here are more for your information, like on these grayed out slides.
I mean, they do help you with some of the other
pieces, but I never directly test you on these figures.
Okay, so let's try a review question right here based on what we've talked about so far.
Which statement or statements below
is or are true.
Let's go 30 more seconds on this.
Does anyone need a little more time?
Okay.
Okay, 15 more seconds.
All right, I'll close it down in three, two, one.
All right, how did we do?
Oh, pretty close, almost, almost.
That was close, that was close, it's okay.
All right, so.
D is the correct answer.
The J-curve model is the relationship that identifies
potential benefits and drawbacks between different chronic exercise workloads.
We can go through a few of these, but sometimes when you
see a question, a lot of the times I like to
just double check that everything's okay, but moderate exercise, less
than 60 minutes will have a negative effect on the immune function.
What's wrong with this one?
Yeah, yeah, we see some benefits to moderate exercise less than 60 minutes.
B, long duration intense exercise can temporarily boost the immune system.
Yeah, I see some people going down.
No, it doesn't boost it, but it'll temporarily drop it
down, which is basically the open window here.
And so the open window increases the risk of
infection due to the increased, well, decreased immunoseveral.
So we have these two words that kind of flipped here.
Any questions on this?
Okay, I thought I was gonna have to add that one, but that's okay.
Okay, factors affecting susceptibility to infection in athletes.
We talked about this, but increased exposure to pathogens, whether that's due to travel,
or maybe because I'm always, if I'm a team-based sport, I'm
always with my team, and so if one individual gets sick,
then it's more likely that everyone else may be exposed to that same pathogen.
Inadequate diet, we'll get into this concept of reds or the athlete triad as well.
Mental stress, lack of sleep, and exercise-induced immune suppression.
So that open window as well as the J-curve concept here.
All of these are gonna increase the risk for infection.
Okay, exercise in the aging immune system.
Don't worry about memorizing anything on this figure.
This is more for you just to kind of take a look at.
But the big kind of concept we're trying to take away
from this is aging is associated with the decline in the function of our immune system.
And we call it immunosenescence.
And so again, aging is associated with a decline in
the immune system or the function of the immune system.
So regular moderate exercise, just like for individuals who
are younger, will help individuals who are older.
So regular moderate exercise can improve the immune function via these pathways here.
So not a whole lot there.
We just know that as we age, we have that decline in immune function.
We can try to reduce the rate of decline
by keeping up with moderate exercise activity.
Okay, what about different environments?
We'll start with the top one, exercise in the hot environment or in a hot environment.
We typically see elevated levels of cortisol compared to cool environments.
However, the difference or that delta in that cortisol level
is not enough to impair the immune function.
So if you exercise in a hot room compared to a
cool room, you are not in a significantly greater risk of an upper respiratory tract infection.
Yeah, yeah, that definitely impacts performance, but as far
as immune function, you're not at more risk.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
The delta, it's just because, like, let's say your
increase in cortisol levels is here during normal exercise in
a cool environment, and maybe it's like right here.
There is a significant difference, but it's just not enough to impact the immune system.
from the literature that we have for right now.
Okay, exercise in the cold.
Same deal, does not have negative effects on the immune system.
So it appears that exercising purely in the cold is not
gonna give you an increased risk for an infection.
It just so happens that we have a higher rate
of individuals who are experiencing some type of infection, like a cold, in the winter months.
And then if you're exercising in the winter and you have that kind of open window,
Well, then you're increasing the risk of infection, but it's not due to the cold itself.
It just so happens to be you're potentially having an
open window around a lot of other individuals who may or may not have an infection.
Okay, exercise at high altitude.
This one we do see a significant increase in the cortisol levels.
And that increase in those cortisol levels are enough at
higher altitudes to increase the risk of an upper respiratory tract infection or an infection in general.
This one's a little interesting.
I would, if you want to like ignore one of these points on the slide, this one would be it here.
So it is interesting because there were some, I
guess, inflicting results in a paper published after they looked
at individuals who were living or I guess acutely went to a high altitude.
They then did a similar study with individuals in a lab.
and they put them on hypoxic gas, and they didn't see
the same depression in the immune system as this up here.
But there was a little bit of a disagreement that
maybe the investigators in this study didn't replicate the
same, I guess, stress, altitude exposure stress as going to,
say, Pike's Peak, for example, or maybe a little bit higher than that.
So that's why there's a little bit of a conflicting result there.
But at least for this course and in general, if you
go to high altitude, we do see an increased risk for an upper respiratory tract infection.
So is this with people who just like me frequently go
up to high altitude or like if somebody was like born
Yeah, even people who live at higher altitudes in general are
at a little bit of a higher risk compared to individuals who are not at that high altitude.
Over time, it does get better, but they are at a higher risk.
Yeah.
And so that does remind me on another piece here.
Some people, actually the majority of the exercise
physiology community, considers Denver or Boulder area as not even moderate altitude.
They would consider it low altitude.
So sometimes when they're doing lab studies, they don't
actually simulate a high enough altitude to maybe get the
same exposure that people are getting at these actual places they're living in.
So for example, if you went up to Pike's Peak,
Well, that decrease in partial pressure needs to be matched in
the lab in that we just need some follow-up studies to confirm that.
Okay, any questions on this one here?
Yeah, so for this one they were at 14, 10 and
14,000 feet and they found depression in the immune system.
So basically like,
I think maybe Dillon area, like Keystone, that's like really
close to that, and then Pike's Peak, anything above that starts to become problematic.
Okay.
Okay, so then,
that question we started off this kind of slide deck with.
Should you exercise when you have a cold?
I think most of us kind of said, well, it depends.
I know we were on yes or no, but it does depend.
In general, it is okay to exercise if you have symptoms above the neck.
And what we're talking about above the neck, we're
talking about runny nose, maybe some congestion or a mild sore throat.
But no matter what, the intensity and duration should be reduced.
if that individual starts the exercise.
We should not exercise if the symptoms are below
the neck, meaning something's inside of the lungs.
You have some chest congestion, or you have some type
of cough inside the lungs, or you have muscle aches, or fevers, or stomach pain, right?
So that's kind of what we're looking at here.
I think one of the biggest problems, not problems, but I guess negative
with elite athletes who are trying to train is if you are taking them away from training.
In general, if someone gets sick, you usually recover a lot
faster if you take it really easy in the subsequent day or
two, as opposed to just trying to hammer it every single
time, and then you're just gonna prolong the recovery.
And it's those multiple days without training that
become problematic for these elite endurance athletes.
For recreationally active individuals, it's not that big of a
deal because a lot of times we're only exercising three, four times a week, maybe five times.
But in general, it's okay if it's above the neck.
Should be really kind of cautious if it's below the neck.
And then if we're having fever, muscle aches, or
any type of fatigue like that, definitely probably should stay away from exercise.
Any questions?
Oh yeah.
It's okay.
Yeah, are you saying up here?
Yeah, so it's fine to do it.
I think there's two areas of thought.
One, you do temporarily improve the immune system with that moderate exercise.
But if you're adding extra stress on the body to
recover from that exercise, that's less energy you're able to fight off the pathogens.
So maybe it's a wash, and that's why it's OK.
But we definitely should not be doing it if we're dealing with something else.
One, if it's in the lungs, because then you could potentially cause it to become more problematic.
Yeah, that's a good question.
Any other questions?
OK.
I mean, that's pretty straightforward, right?
Not too bad for the immune and endocrine, I guess, slides.
The bulk of the material is coming from slides or chapters three and four as well as chapters one.
But that doesn't necessarily mean all of the questions are gonna be coming from those chapters.
So I would spend your time appropriately throughout all of the slides.
There's going to be 32.
I thought it was going to be 33 with the added question.
But you'll have maybe some other opportunities in a little bit here.
But 32 multiple choice questions.
I would use the lecture notes and the learning goals to study.
The learning goals are a great place to start.
I wouldn't say that's the only thing you need to learn or know.
Calculator, number two pencil, highlighter can be really helpful
because half the battle is just making sure you understand what the question is asking.
Sometimes students will answer a question but it's actually,
it's not wrong what they're trying to say but it's not really answering the question at hand.
You can't use your phone as a calculator and I'll
give you formulas and conversion factors and you can write on the exam.
Any general question?
Oh, if you have accommodations, you should have emails.
I sent a reminder email to everybody today, I believe.
But if you have not got an email and you have
accommodations, you need to see me today, like after lecture.
For the formulas, are you able to place that
No, only because only the formulas that are posted
on there are applicable to the questions themselves.
So that kind of gives away maybe what you would need
to know and what you wouldn't need to know sometimes.
So I don't want to push you in one direction or
the other just because only a certain number of formulas are listed.
And I don't wanna post like three pages of formulas to have everything.
Yeah, good question.
Anything else on the exam?
Format.
Okay, cool.
So let's do a few review questions.
Again, you're more than welcome to chat with your neighbors,
but in my opinion, when I show some of these clicker questions,
I would take some time, read it on your own, try to answer it on your own,
and then after you're kind of done with that, maybe then chat with your neighbor,
because you've got to really challenge yourself to see
whether you actually understand what the question is asking, one,
and number two, maybe why it's wrong and why it's correct.
Okay, so these are clicker questions.
I'll open them up just because then you'll have access to them later.
So I would like you to click in on these.
Plus, I'll still do it.
If we get 100, we're in good shape.
Okay, two athletes of the same size and same VO2 max are cycling at 100 watts.
One individual is expending 5.2 kcal per minute and the other is expending 4.7 kcal per minute.
Which statement below is true?
Okay, let's go maybe 30 more seconds.
Do you feel like you need a little bit more time than that?
And we'll go through this one as well.
So double check you have something clicked in.
Okay, 10 seconds.
I think we're missing one clicker, so double check you have something in.
Close it down in five.
Three, two, one, nice.
Okay, that last person is in.
Okay.
How did we do?
We did great here.
There was a point in time though, where I think we were almost 50-50 on these ones here.
So let me ask the group here, why can you not say,
so that's correct that D is right and C is wrong, but why
can you say, why can you not say the economies are different?
Because the exercise economy is about oxygen consumption,
Yeah, yeah.
So that is true.
So we need VO2, we need oxygen consumption.
But would you agree we need oxygen consumption to get to Kcals?
So what else would we need in order to solve this problem?
Or to determine economy?
Yeah, so you would need substrate utilization.
So you would need the RER chart.
And on the RER chart, you'd have to go to the caloric equivalent.
And then after that, you can multiply the oxygen consumption.
But depending on whether it's given to you in
normalized, milliliters per kilogram per minute or liters per minute, then you would need body mass.
So there's a lot missing here that we can't back
calculate and determine whether someone is more economical or
not based on these two energy expenditures here.
Because it's possible someone could be on the low end
burning more fats than carbs and that does change energy expenditure.
Good.
The other piece, you would have to kind of understand what efficiency is.
Who wants to help me out with what efficiency is in
the context of this problem or what we've talked about in exercise physiology?
You can even list the formula.
Achieving maximum productivity.
Good, yeah, so that's a great definition.
Can someone else help me out with the formula?
Yeah, yeah, so mechanical work over kind of metabolic work or mechanical power or metabolic power.
And you are trying to achieve kind of the maximum amount
of work done with the least amount of energy used.
We have energy here in kcals per minute, so we're in good shape.
So the reason the economy, just to recap real quick,
the reason the economies are the same is because they both have the same VO2.
So we don't know whether the economies are the same or different.
Yeah, so I cannot determine that information.
So I don't know if economies are the same or if economies are different.
So BNC, I don't really know.
What would we need in this case?
Yeah, so we would need oxygen consumption.
And then we would also need RER, or the caloric equivalent,
and then body mass if it was given to you in a relative.
Then you could back calculate to oxygen consumption.
So VO2 max is not a reasonable, like,
Knowing that someone is at VO2 max or some percentage of
VO2 max or that an individual has the same VO2 max is not a good indication of this.
Yeah.
I was going to put it here, but I could have
easily on E put both exercise economy and efficiency are the same.
And I have a feeling a lot of you would have selected E,
but I was trying to make it a little more straightforward than that.
Any other questions on why we got to where the correct answer is here?
Okay, let's try another one.
Joanne is running on a treadmill starting at miles per hour.
She then increases the treadmill speed.
Shouldn't be an S there.
Speed to seven miles per hour.
When comparing the increase in speed, which of the following would we not expect to occur?
Let's try another minute or so, 45 seconds.
Okay, let's make sure we got something in.
How are we doing?
We're doing great.
Missing that one clicker.
I'll close it down in 10 seconds.
Oh, perfect.
Anyone need more time?
Okay, three, two, one.
Nice, this is great.
I know it's not fun that we didn't get the hundred,
but if you truly read this question and answered it and got the correct answer,
I mean, you don't need that free question.
96% average on the exam.
It's going to be great.
You can't chat with each other.
It is kind of funny watching the trend where it's like spread out amongst A
through E, and then they all slowly kind of go
towards the correct answer, which means you're probably chatting with your neighbors, which is great.
Don't get that false sense of security because you can't ask,
you can't phone a friend or ask your neighbor on the exam.
Okay, so if we're going from five miles per hour to
seven miles per hour, that is an increase in exercise intensity.
If we are looking at the increase in intensity and
we see a decrease in the relative fat utilization, would we say that's true?
Yeah, I would agree.
So as intensity increases, carbohydrates go up, fats go down.
B, an increase in the relative carbohydrate utilization.
Well, that's just the opposite of that.
So OK, we're in good shape here.
C, increase in glucagon and insulin concentration.
This is the one everyone selected.
Which one is the issue here?
Or is there an issue with both of them?
So as you can see, it's probably the correct, because yes, you can have all of these.
Right, right, so there is an increase in glucagon,
but insulin concentration decreases as we increase with exercise intensity.
So we should not see insulin on there.
Increase in aldosterone and ADH concentration.
What's aldosterone and ADH?
What are their goals?
So that's true, they do go up, but why?
Yeah, yeah, so they both stimulate water reabsorption in the
kidneys in response to a drop in plasma volume.
So we would expect that to go up as exercise intensity increases.
But you can also ask yourself a few other pieces as
far as what implications does that have for plasma volume.
And then a decrease in exercise efficiency.
So we're thinking yes here.
Why?
I'll come back to you in a second.
Anyone else?
So why is that one okay?
Yeah, so that's one of the three factors.
that can influence exercise efficiency.
So if you go back to those slides, which you were kind of around there
since we were doing efficiency, but like workload, cadence,
or step count, and then recruitment of type two fibers,
so increasing that intensity, does impact or decrease efficiency.
Yeah.
Oh, that's a good one.
Yeah, so even if I put a decrease in absolute
fat utilization, could we say for sure that's happening?
No, we can't.
Yeah, that's a good response.
So like that was on your lab question too.
In some situations, your absolute fat oxidation would be
higher, and in some situations, it would be lower.
So we couldn't even answer that question.
What if I put,
Oh, I guess we couldn't do that, but when does relative fat utilization not decrease?
Not necessarily with intensity, but when does it increase?
When we're looking at substrate utilization.
With duration.
So if it was flipped and we said this individual is
running for four hours, well then that could probably be
both A and B would be incorrect.
Okay, good.
Let's try one more here.
Two individuals exercise at a submaximal intensity for
10 minutes, reaching an oxygen consumption of two liters per minute.
You look back at the first minute of data collection and
notice individual A had a VO2 of 0.75 liters per minute and individual B was at 1.15 liters per minute.
At minute one, both individuals are at or in what?
OK, how are we doing here?
We good?
Let's close this down.
Missing two clickers.
We'll wait 10 seconds here, one clicker.
OK, closing it down in three, two, one.
So I haven't even seen this, so I don't even know.
Oh, but I think you know before me.
Ooh, nice, nice.
I'll take it, I'll take it.
So yes, B is the correct answer here.
Can we tell whether they're at lactate threshold?
No.
What would you need to determine whether someone is even
at lactate threshold based off the tools that we've learned in class?
Yeah, we'd have to graph it out, right?
And then we'd have to see where it starts to exponentially increase.
Okay, so we don't have that information.
We can't tell whether they're at lactate threshold.
Oxygen deficit.
We're thinking yes, but why?
I agree with you.
Yeah, but you are correct in that, but what in
the problem is telling you, confirming what you just said?
Yeah.
Good.
So they're exercising for 10 minutes.
They reach two liters per minute of oxygen consumption.
We would consider that potentially steady state.
So they're kind of hanging out there.
But at the start of exercise, they're at a much lower oxygen consumption, .75 and 1.15.
And so that gives us an indication that they are kind of in that rest to exercise transition.
And because they are still exercising, they're not like
falling off the treadmill, some other pathway is creating or generating ATP.
What other pathway would that be, or pathways?
Yeah, yeah, those immediate energy stores or non-oxidative
glycolysis or the phosphocreatine kind of pathway, so the ATP-PCR pathway.
All right, ketosis.
Technically, we didn't even talk about this term, so that was kind of just the filler answer.
EPOC, what's EPOC?
Yeah, yeah, so if I saw these values at minute 11,
So if I just added one extra one here, then we
could potentially think this is the best option here for epoch.
And then what would make E correct?
What would I have to change in the problem to maybe make E correct?
Good, good.
So the biggest thing that he mentioned was not just at minute 10, but
if in the problem it said from minutes five to 10,
the VO2 or the oxygen consumption was at two liters per minute,
what state are they in at minute nine or something like that?
Any minute in between there, and it would be a steady state.
Any other questions on this one?
OK.
So we definitely have a little bit more time, but I'm
gonna open it up to the class for any questions that you have.
So if you have any questions on the learning goals or
slides, I'm more than happy to help you out with them.
If you're just like, too easy, I'm good, I would take no offense if you took off.
But sometimes it's nice hearing other people's questions if they have any.
But again, I would not be offended if you took off, yeah.
Say that one more time.