All right, welcome back.
Let's get started here.
All right.
So today we're gonna start the new chapter, chapter five.
We're gonna be looking at some hormonal responses to exercise.
We should be able to get a decent amount through this today.
We'll finish it up on Thursday.
And then Thursday, as well as Tuesday, we will get into immunology.
Your exam will be on Thursday.
next Thursday.
I'll go over a few more details about the exam on Thursday.
But essentially, you're looking at multiple choice questions around 30 or so.
But I'll give you some more details on that on Thursday.
OK.
So let's go ahead and get started with chapter five.
We're going to be talking about a little bit about endocrinology.
I know we have a fantastic faculty group here that teaches endocrinology.
So we're not going into details.
With this unit, all we are trying to do is get a
broad overview and then see how we can relate the hormonal response to exercise.
In particular, we're going to be looking at
substrate mobilization or substrate utilization and how different hormones impact substrate utilization.
And then we'll quickly talk about changes in plasma
volume during exercise and how vasopressin and aldosterone are influencing changes in plasma volume.
Okay, so let's get started.
Endocrinology.
If we were to just make a broad kind of summary
of it, we're just saying endocrinology is a communication system.
There are two major ways our body communicates with other cells.
One would be a nervous system, and so that's sending
electrical signals from one cell to the other.
And then we have the endocrine system, which is a chemical communication.
Sometimes I like making the analogy of communication when
comparing nervous and endocrine as like how you would communicate anyone who's maybe further away.
So if you had a friend in a different state and you
wanted to get a hold of that friend, you probably would pick up the telephone and call them.
So that's usually an electrical signal sent through, well, old school telephone lines.
Endocrine would be like you writing a letter and putting it
into the mail and having that get sent out.
So it's a little bit slower, still gets the message
across, but there could be better use cases for one versus the
other, but it's just one thing to kind of think about when we're looking at endocrine versus nervous.
Okay, well, if I'm sending a letter out or if
I'm sending a chemical communication, something has to receive that letter.
You have to have a mailbox.
If there's no mailbox, that person is not gonna get that letter.
So we have this hormone receptor interaction where there has
to be some sort of receptor on the target cell.
So if the hormone can't attach to the cell, then the cell doesn't really get that message.
And so we need to have a receptor to have the hormonal effect or that physiological response.
We can coordinate these systems during rest and exercise.
This really helps us maintain homeostasis or steady state during exercise
because we can control substrate metabolism, which is this
big piece here, and then regulate fluid and electrolyte balance.
So the big take-home picture is it doesn't matter if I
flood the body with hormones if the cell does not have that receptor
take on that chemical message, there's no response.
Chemical class of hormones are here, peptides, amino acids, and steroids.
You do not really need to know the distinction between these three.
As far as chemical distinction, you just need to
know that there are peptides and polypeptides that act as
hormones, amino acid derivatives, as well as steroids.
it will be helpful to know that steroids do not need a
receptor outside of the cell or in the cell membrane.
They can freely cross the cell membrane, but then they
eventually need a receptor inside of the cell.
So the receptor's inside of the cell here.
Amino acids and peptides, they need to attach to a receptor on the surface of the cell membrane.
So that's the, if you were to just take home a
picture from here or the message, it's just maybe where the receptors are in the different classes.
Okay, so if you get a hormone to bind to a
certain receptor, it's in the mailbox, well, something has to kind of respond to it.
Well, these receptors typically activate something called secondary
messengers, and they do that via a G protein.
once they activate these secondary messengers, now that causes the cell to respond.
and they can then modify existing proteins.
So there are a lot of different secondary messengers.
You would not necessarily need to memorize this or reproduce this on an exam,
but if you saw that there is DAG, you should know that that's a secondary messenger,
or if I told you the secondary messenger DAG, you
should realize how that might impact certain cellular responses later on.
So if you activate genes to synthesize new proteins, those proteins can then go do something.
For example, if I am activating some type of
transporter protein, then those proteins would then translocate to
the surface of the membrane and allow for the movement of certain molecules.
And we'll get into an example of that a little bit later on.
OK, so far, big picture.
We get a hormone released into the blood.
It binds to a receptor.
The receptor causes some sort of response inside of the cell.
One example would be altering transport inside of the cell
or on the outside of the cell, the membrane, to allow for movement of molecules.
OK, so far, again, that was the
the quick summary or the extent of endocrinology background that
you'll need for the rest of these slides.
Okay, so substrate mobilization during exercise.
There are some major endocrine glands that we're gonna be focusing on
for metabolic regulation, anterior pituitary gland, the
thyroid gland, adrenal gland, and pancreas.
We're gonna focus on which or what kind of hormones
are being released by these glands and how they impact carbohydrate and fat utilization during exercise.
So how they impact different substrates during exercise.
Okay, let's start with hormone number one, growth hormone.
Growth hormone is synthesized in the anterior pituitary.
Basically, again, don't worry too much about the details in here.
This is more for your information, but anterior pituitary
gland secretes growth hormone that then acts on different tissues.
That could be the entire body or maybe the adrenal cortex.
They're just happening to act, or you can think of it as different cells in the body
have receptors for growth hormone.
Why would we want to secrete growth hormone?
Well, this would be a good kind of
area to see why we would or what causes that secretion.
So here, the control of growth hormone release, exercise sleep, stress,
and low plasma glucose are going to result in the
secretion of growth hormone from the anterior pituitary.
Once you get the growth hormone produced, it's going to cause some actions here.
The actions that we're going to kind of focus on would be the stimulation of protein synthesis
and growth, as well as a little bit of gluconeogenesis
in the liver and blocks glucose entry in the adipose cell to favor fat mobilization.
There are some negative feedback loops,
Essentially, we're looking at exercise, because exercise physiology,
how that is being secreted to impact some of these things down here.
So the level of detail that I'm kind of explaining to
you on these slides is the level of detail that you need to focus on for maybe the exam.
So not a whole lot.
Okay, here's when we get into a few things as far as growth hormone.
It's a potent anabolic hormone, builds tissues and
organs, and promotes hypertrophy or muscle growth.
We'll get into kind of this hyperplasia, hypertrophy, but
for now we're just saying promotes muscle growth.
This is for your information.
If you completely ignored this figure down here, you'd
be okay, but it's just for your information, if you wanted to
see a little bit more detail on how that's happening.
But no surprise, there's a receptor for growth hormone
here that's causing some type of secondary reaction over here, and that's gonna lead to hypertrophy.
The one piece, you don't need to know this for this exam,
but keep in the back of your mind later on, this mTOR, this mTOR pathway.
So this will come up when we get into muscle physiology,
but that might be something to keep in the back of your mind.
Okay, so during exercise then, what do we normally see with the growth hormone concentration?
If we have some individuals undergoing prolonged and graded exercise,
as time increases, we see growth hormone also increase
in the release or concentration in the blood.
If I increase intensity, we also see growth hormone increase.
Pretty easy with this one, right?
Prolonged exercise,
growth hormone increases.
Graded exercise for increasing intensity, growth hormone increases.
In this course, we're not really focusing too much on
the magnitude of increase or comparing the two.
You just need to know that if I increase intensity, growth hormone goes up.
If I increase duration at the same intensity, growth hormone goes up.
Okay, so then why is this important?
True or false here?
Give me a second on this.
Okay, should be open now.
True or false, human growth hormone is effective
at increasing resistance training induced hypertrophy and strength
in young adults with normal growth hormone levels.
Okay, does anyone need a little more time getting set up here?
Okay, I'll close this down in, I don't know, five seconds or so.
Okay, three, two, one.
Okay, yeah, most of us are saying true.
With these true and falses, you can almost think of that the questions are almost
a little too broad where you could argue a little bit for and against.
But in this instance, there are some good studies that kind of looked into this.
They have some limitations.
But in general, increases in circulating anabolic hormones is not required.
for resistance-induced hypertrophy, meaning you don't necessarily need it to have muscle growth,
but it looks like high circulating levels
of these hormones can support resistance-training-induced hypertrophy.
So although it's not required, it definitely can maybe help,
so we need to be careful about pushing the two where
It might be good to get someone to get a
muscle mass increase after they plateau, but you definitely
don't need growth hormone necessarily to have hypertrophy.
So normal adults show an increase in lead body mass, but this is a lot of the studies
that kind of looked into this growth hormone supplementation
saw a lot of water retention as opposed to the increase in cell mass in itself.
So they weren't necessarily increasing the sarcomeres in
parallel, but they were just increasing the existing sarcomere that
was there, maybe by putting on a little bit more water mass.
To this point, there's no direct evidence that growth hormone promotes strength gains.
So there are minimal strength gains compared to resistance training alone.
Now, the one thing we have to keep in mind, or I
guess two things, if we go back to this prompt here,
or the question, they already have normal growth hormone levels.
So we have to keep that in mind.
If someone's maybe a little bit lower than normal, well,
yeah, of course, if we give them some growth hormone, that might actually help.
Number two, we'll touch on this a little bit, but most of the studies
are only using growth hormone, where I'm not saying this always happens,
but people are usually stacking with other type of
steroids, or they're using other things, or they're using different doses.
But at higher doses,
This typically results in more adverse effects than benefits.
So you can get some water retention and edema.
You can get joint and muscle aches and then increase risk of infected injection-related diseases.
So you can get some infections from some of the use of, say, needles.
So again, you kind of have to take this in the context of some of these studies.
They don't necessarily use maybe the strategies that everyone
is using to date, mainly because we have internal review boards that oversee ethics.
And so you wouldn't necessarily be able to give them the doses that maybe people are using.
outside of research.
And then two, most people don't just use growth hormone alone.
You kind of have to pair it with some other things like testosterone and other things like that.
Not that I'm encouraging this at all, but I'm just saying
we have to be careful about how we interpret some of these studies.
OK, the physiology of growth hormone and sport.
So if we're looking over here, we see some
baseline levels in short-term growth hormone excretion, we can say, and long-term.
So protein remodeling, we're seeing some changes here,
but net protein synthesis over the long-term or the long periods
of time, we're not seeing a really big difference.
Maybe short-term there is a benefit and then we start to plateau off because
It kind of makes sense that there are some
adverse effects with long-term steroid or growth hormones.
Body protein mass looks like once you get to a
certain point, your body can't really produce more than what it already has.
And it appears to be some type of plateau or leveling off.
And then strength gains are a little bit controversial
because if we're just getting more water retention and it
appears that an individual is getting bigger, that doesn't necessarily mean that they're getting stronger.
Again, if I have some long-term use and I have
some adverse effects, that can even impair strength.
So that's why there's a lot of kind of back and
forth on some of the growth, I guess, growth hormone use.
And then do keep in mind that the study, all these results are a little bit older.
I know there's some newer results, but they all kind of are saying the same thing.
We briefly touched on a little bit about this idea of maybe evidence is limited.
But yeah, although there is limited available evidence
to suggest that growth hormone increases lean body mass, it may not improve strength.
In addition, it may worsen exercise capacity and increase adverse events.
So essentially, it's kind of left in this little gray area.
Because if you just saw this, then you would think, oh,
well, growth hormone's not that big of a deal.
It's not really helping or improving performance.
But I know everybody here has access to the internet.
There are very, very successful Olympic athletes who
have been caught using these performance enhancing drugs.
And they have been shown to do quite well in certain instances.
So I guess my take home is just in certain situations, maybe they're not good.
In certain situations, maybe people are taking advantage of it.
So I just kind of wanted to give both sides to the story here.
And we'll get into ergogenic aids a little bit later.
But again, there are different strategies that people sometimes
take on to get better, more benefits.
Any questions on the growth hormone?
Okay, let's move on to catecholamines.
A lot of the times, so in endocrinology, we
do make a big distinction between norepinephrine epinephrine,
but especially inside of exercise physiology, we're basically
just gonna say catecholamines or adrenaline, this is
being secreted, norepinephrine epinephrine is what we're looking at here.
So here you have sympathetic,
on a stimulus causing the release of this norepinephrine epinephrine,
and then you have some alpha and beta adrenergic receptors
on the tissue or the cells, and they're gonna respond to the catecholamine.
Most of you have probably heard of this before, but
in general, what does catecholamines do, or what response should
we expect, or what term saying have you heard with catecholamines?
I think people are, I heard some people say it, yeah.
Yeah, fight or flight, right?
So you have the fight or flight response here.
You can get some hypothalamus activation of the
sympathetic division of nervous system that results in an increase in heart rate blood pressure.
And then you get an increased blood flow of the
skeletal muscles and then you reduce the activity of the inactive muscles.
So in this situation, you got a bear chasing somebody.
Does anyone notice something pretty interesting about this photo here?
What's a little odd about what's going on?
Yeah, the guy's smiling, right?
Like, I don't know about you, but if I'm running from
a bear, I don't know if I'm smiling, but yeah.
So essentially, you can either fight or flight.
The other thing is, anyone know the saying with different bears?
Yeah, yeah.
So you typically don't want to run.
Well, the suggestion is that you don't run from a black bear.
You try to fight a black bear.
And then, yeah, you lie down with brown bears.
Or you definitely don't run from a bear in general.
But if I was in that situation, I don't think I'm thinking about these things.
I'm just maybe panicking and running.
But yeah.
The point though still gets across, right?
There's some type of stimulus causing a fight or
flight response that is the secretion of catecholamines that are
gonna result in some of these responses here.
So in a table form, we have these physiological responses.
I would not suggest memorizing these, but if you were
starting to review this, all of these should make sense after we get through the rest of the slides here.
So you can come back here and say, oh, okay,
it's gonna increase fatty acid mobilization from the adipose tissue
if I have an increase in catecholamine secretion.
Okay, so same deal like growth hormone.
Let's look at catecholamines and see how they increase during prolonged and graded exercise.
No surprise, both prolonged and graded exercise, we see an increase in catecholamines secretion.
So both norepinephrine and epinephrine increase as duration
gets longer and as intensity gets higher.
And we see that across all intensities of exercise here.
This slide gets a little more interesting.
The one kind of asterisk that you need to put on this slide is this is at the same workload.
So we wanna see how plasma epinephrine concentrations change after training.
If I am at the same workload pre-post training, I
should expect to see a lower concentration of epinephrine in my blood.
Rationally thinking about this, I think it makes sense.
As I train, the same exercise intensity gets easier.
Well, if it gets easier, then we're going kind of backwards.
on this one here, on this graded exercise intensity.
So instead of going up, we're kind of going down.
So yeah, I would expect to see after several weeks
of training, say seven weeks of training, the same exercise
intensity should result in a lower epinephrine, norepinephrine secretion.
Are we okay here?
Yeah.
So both epinephrine and norepinephrine are lower?
Yeah, yeah.
And so a lot of times if I say epinephrine, we're also talking about norepinephrine.
It's catecholamines on a whole.
For exercise physiology.
Okay.
Next one, cortisol.
What do we usually kind of associate cortisol with?
Stress, yeah, stress response.
So the synthesis of cortisol occurs in the adrenal cortex.
If these are our kidneys, we have an adrenal gland
right above them, and these adrenal glands are secreting cortisol.
Just like you had mentioned, stress causes the release
of cortisol, which then acts on different tissues.
Note that I skipped everything in between here because you don't need to know this piece, right?
We have endocrinology for you to learn all this.
So exercise, I like how they've put bone break, right?
Like it's so severe.
Break your bone, of course.
Injury, burns, and stress are gonna cause the release of cortisol.
Of course, we're gonna focus more on the exercise piece.
So changes in plasma cortisol during acute graded exercise.
As we increase exercise intensity, we see plasma cortisol increase.
I know there's a little bit going on here where we
see a decrease over here and this percent change.
But the overall picture here is as we increase intensity, cortisol increases.
That's the take-home picture for here.
So far we're doing pretty good though, right?
It looks like growth hormone, catecholamines, as well as cortisol, all increased during exercise.
Should be pretty straightforward.
Not too bad here, right?
All right, let's move on to glucagon then.
This one is a little interesting.
Does anyone remember from endocrinology or physiology what glucagon
is or does or gets what situation?
Promotes glucose uptake?
Yeah, so then what about, well,
Yeah, that's okay.
Let's just get into it then here.
So really quick, the synthesis of glucagon occurs in the pancreas.
And so we're looking over here at the alpha cells.
So the alpha cells in the pancreas produce glucagon.
The beta cells produce something called insulin and we'll get to that in a second.
So the alpha cells produce glucagon.
and those alpha cells are located in the pancreas.
Okay, so if we have a low blood sugar, that is
kind of a disturbance or an imbalance in homeostasis, so the
body wants to raise the blood sugar, and so we're going to produce some of this glucagon.
So a decrease in plasma glucose is gonna cause an increase in the glucagon secretion,
that ultimately is going to cause an increase in plasma glucose.
If the increase gets too high, there's a negative feedback that then kind of stops this.
Glucogon acts on the liver as well as the adipose tissue.
and then it results in these responses here.
So one, liver is going to produce glucose.
It's also going to increase lipolysis and increase free fatty acids.
That way we can try to spare glucose utilization.
So it's kind of two-fold.
Produce more glucose and then maybe make some other
substrates readily available so we can spare glucose.
Glucose actions.
Well, or glucagon action, sorry.
Just increasing blood glucose levels.
Highlighted a few of these areas.
Again, I wouldn't memorize this because in general, this
table does a good job, but essentially you're increasing glucose levels.
Okay, so changes in plasma glucagon during prolonged
exercise in trained and untrained individuals.
Let's look at the untrained first.
So prolonged exercise results in an increase, sorry, an
increase in duration causes an increase in glucagon secretion.
This is also a little,
A little tricky, but it goes to the same concept
as when we talked about training with epinephrine or catecholamine secretion.
If I'm at the same exercise intensity and then I
take it throughout the duration, we are not seeing the
same increase in glucagon because again, that exercise is much easier.
But on a whole,
If we are increasing duration or intensity, we're seeing that glucagon come up.
The big thing you have to kind of think about as far as intensity and duration would be
if I am starting to deplete glucose levels because I'm
exercising too long, the body will release glucagon, trained or
not trained, to get the glucose levels back up.
Are we OK there?
So sometimes it gets a little tricky thinking about at the same exercise intensity
after eight weeks of training, well yeah, we don't see
a big change because this intensity is not really causing
any large changes in glucose levels because we're able to
sustain it with the glycogen that we already have.
I think I saw a question, yeah.
Yeah, so you're basically trying to spare the glucose
molecules by maybe relying on beta oxidation a little bit, yeah.
If you undergo glycolysis, you're gonna break down glucose and then make it even worse.
So you kinda wanna spare the glucose and use something else.
Yeah, good question.
Okay, so the flip side to this would be insulin.
Synthesis of insulin in the pancreas again happens in the beta cells.
And the beta cells are releasing insulin.
Insulin then binds to its target receptor and causes plasma glucose to go down.
So it's the opposite effect.
So let's say we have low blood glucose.
Glucagon gets secreted.
We then kind of overshoot a little bit so plasma glucose gets too high.
Then the body maybe responds to that by releasing some insulin to bring those levels back down.
So we have an increase in plasma glucose.
That means you get an increase in insulin secretion.
You get an increase in kind of glucose uptake in all of the cells.
You also get a change or decrease in the gluconeogenesis as far as in the liver.
You don't want to be producing more glucose if you have a surplus.
You kind of want to decrease this over here.
Same with breaking down glycogen.
You want to build it up, you don't want to break it down here.
All of those are going to cause a decrease in plasma glucose here.
This is kind of important because if I get a spike
in blood glucose during exercise, you are going to maybe do
the opposite effect of what you might want during exercise.
So kind of keep that in the back of your mind when we talk about some other things.
Same deal with these tables.
Make sure you understand what's going on here.
Don't worry too much about memorizing them.
I would, however, spend some time on this slide here.
OK, so we're going to bring on a few other hormones and the interactions.
So we have epinephrine and norepinephrine.
So we have catecholamine stimulation or secretion, as well as glucagon and insulin responses.
So it's going to inhibit insulin.
Okay, so let's start over here on the left.
We have epinephrine or epinephrine.
If we get those to be stimulated or secreted, and we look
this way at the beta cells, or sorry, at the alpha cells
in the pancreas, that's gonna cause an increase in glucagon.
Glucagon then increases plasma glucagon, or the release
causes an increase in plasma glucagon, which then increases the glucose concentration in the blood.
Yeah?
The orange beta symbol on the redone cap, is that just like the receptor?
Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
This is a receptor.
Beta adrenergic alpha 2.
Good.
Catochole means then,
act on the beta cells of the pancreas, which causes a decrease in insulin secretion.
That means plasma insulin goes down, and that's gonna
help the glucose levels or concentrations in the blood to go up.
So make sure we're feeling good here as far as understanding what's going on here.
Any questions on the slide?
Okay.
Catecholamines, increased plasma glucagon, decreased plasma insulin, net
result is an increase in glucose.
So that means plasma and insulin during acute exercise
in both trained and untrained individuals go down, both in prolonged and graded exercise.
So as I increase exercise duration, insulin levels go down.
As I increase exercise intensity, insulin levels go down.
And I know there's like a little bit of a rebound
over here, so it's starting to look like a U-curve.
It actually kind of flattens out because that's not significant.
But for the purposes of this course, you're just saying down with graded exercise.
Okay, so that makes things pretty easy then.
If I have cortisol, glucagon, growth hormone,
and catecholamines, with prolonged exercise, everything goes up.
Insulin is the only one that goes down.
With graded exercise, so as intensity increases, everything still
goes up, and insulin is the only one that goes down.
So if there's one slide you just had to memorize, this
one might be a good one to memorize then, right?
Because it's, or I guess you just need to memorize one.
Insulin is the only one that goes down, everything else goes up.
Okay.
Questions so far?
Nice.
Okay, regulation of carbohydrate metabolism during exercise.
I don't think we need to chat about this, maybe we
do, maybe we don't, but someone wanna help me out.
What happens to carbohydrate utilization during prolonged submaximal exercise?
I guess the why piece maybe you'll have to chat about.
But does anyone want to volunteer?
If I have prolonged submaximal exercise, what happens to carbohydrate utilization?
Yeah.
It decreases, right?
So what happens then to?
Well, I guess we could before we, well, we'll just go on the second one since I showed it.
So what happens to carbohydrate utilization during graded exercise?
Yeah, it goes up, right?
And then this is where we see the crossover effect.
I'm telling you right now for both lab and lecture
exam, if you see anything with substrate utilization, I draw
these two graphs with the appropriate axes, right?
Duration, time.
intensity over there, draw these two, and then always reference
these two to make sure you're on the right track.
Because it's pretty simple right now, but sometimes when you are
in an exam and you have some test anxiety, maybe you accidentally flip them.
But if you just draw it correctly, you're gonna have
to fight yourself pretty hard to get the wrong answer here.
Okay, so what's causing this decrease?
Anyone remember the mechanisms?
Why are we decreasing this carbohydrate utilization?
If I'm a marathon runner and I'm exercising a certain intensity, I prefer carbohydrates.
Yeah, so I like that idea, but let's just assume that this is primarily oxidative or aerobic.
I like that idea.
Yeah, you have a limited capacity or a limited supply bank for glycogen.
Eventually you're gonna run out here.
We also talked about the increase of epinephrine and how
maybe that's going to free up more free fatty acids.
But in general, the biggest piece here is you're starting to decrease the capacity for glycogen.
OK, what about the reasons here?
Why are we increasing?
Why does our body prefer carbohydrates during intense exercise?
It's faster, right?
Yeah, it's faster.
So there are less steps.
Here we have glycogen.
Break it down to G6P, glycolysis, Krebs cycle, ETC.
Yeah, that's a lot of steps.
But compare it to fat.
Adipose tissue is not even, the main triglyceride sources are not in the muscle.
We gotta break down the triglycerides into free fatty acids away from the muscle.
Then we gotta bring those free fatty acids closer to
the muscle, undergo beta oxidation, and then they get into a Krebs cycle, and then they go to ETC.
So more steps.
So that's one good reason.
What's the second one?
Yeah, yeah, so this caloric equivalent that you've been doing in lab, all this hard work
that you've been doing with the RER chart, you
are more efficient at burning carbohydrates compared to fats.
So you get the RER1.
So you get around 5 kcals per liter of oxygen
when you're burning carbohydrates, and then closer to like 4.7 when you're dealing with fats.
Great, nice, nice.
OK, so we're good here then.
So then carbohydrate metabolism, one adequate glucose during
exercise requires glucose release by the liver, as well as glucose uptake by the muscles.
The amount we release from the liver does depend on intensity and duration.
The one thing we have to kind of keep in the back
of our mind is as I increase exercise intensity, I am
almost decreasing the blood flow to these accessory organs.
That makes it harder for the liver to maybe release glucose
in the same fashion at a submaximal or resting state.
Okay, hormones that increase circulating glucose, no surprise,
because we already talked about it, growth hormone,
cortisol, glucagon, and the catecholamines, epinephrine or epinephrine.
This causes glycogenolysis, which means we're gonna break down glycogen into glucose.
We're also gonna undergo gluconeogenesis, this typically happens in
the liver, where we take free fatty acids and proteins and create glucose molecules.
OK, so catecholamines, if we look at each one of these
here, we're going to go through each one of these hormones.
Catecholamines stimulate muscle and liver glycogenolysis, meaning we
are going to take glycogen, break it down to glucose, and have that release into the blood system.
So when we're talking about catecholamines, we're looking over here as far as carbohydrates.
So this happens by stimulating the beta-1 adrenergic receptor.
And again, glucose levels go up.
We typically use muscle glycogen before liver glycogen, only because of this blood flow issue.
OK, so what about glucagon?
Well, glucagon also stimulates the liver.
for glycogenolysis and gluconeogenesis.
So the liver here is going to cause this creation of glucose here.
Plasma glucose goes up.
I think you're noticing a theme here.
They're all kind of doing the same thing.
But here we talked about how catecholamines are meeting at the liver and the muscle.
Glucagon here are kind of stimulating the liver.
Same picture here, basically, with epinephrine
glucagon stimulates liver glycogenolysis gluconeogenesis to cause
an increase in glucose concentration in the blood.
Okay, what about growth hormone?
Well, growth hormone is also meeting at the liver and causing gluconeogenesis.
If we are looking at gluconeogenesis with growth hormone, glucose levels also increase.
Same story here.
Cortisol doesn't wanna be left out, so it's joining club liver over here,
and it's gonna meet at the liver, and it's also gonna
do the same thing, stimulate the liver to increase glucose secretion.
So circulating glucose during exercise also is impacted by
increasing in free fatty oxidation and decrease glucose uptake.
If I am uptaking free fatty acids and not uptaking
as many glucose molecules, then by default glucose will increase inside of the blood.
Okay, so far?
All right, let's talk about this one.
We'll take a few minutes here, talk with your neighbors.
Growth hormone, epinephrine or epinephrine, and cortisol
all inhibit glucose uptake during exercise, causing the body to rely more on free fatty acids.
Which tissues do we want to inhibit glucose uptake during
exercise, and which tissues do we not want to inhibit glucose uptake during exercise?
So just a minute or two, and then we'll come back together here.
Okay, I think it's pretty straightforward, but who wants to help me out with this one?
Which tissues do we want to inhibit glucose uptake during exercise?
Any ideas?
Or maybe the easier one, which tissues do we not want to inhibit glucose uptake?
The brain, that would be a good one, yeah.
But in general, where else?
Where else do we want glucose uptake?
That is a good one, though.
The muscles, right?
We want the muscles to be able to uptake.
It's a little interesting with nervous tissue, especially during exercise.
They are a net uptake uptaker of lactate as
opposed to glucose, and they actually metabolize lactate.
So yes, they do increase glucose uptake and utilization,
but they primarily rely on lactate, especially during exercise.
What about the tissues we want to inhibit glucose uptake?
Kind of on that same point.
Yeah, yeah, tissues that aren't necessarily being used to do the mechanical work.
So inactive tissue is sometimes what we call it.
Because you have to think about it in the extreme way.
If I'm running from a bear, then I want all the
glucose to go to the muscle, not necessarily anywhere else.
Yes, that could be bad, especially if I'm reduced to, say, neural tissue.
But at that point, it's like,
Either you run away or you don't run away because you
don't have enough energy at the muscles and then your life is at stake.
OK, so let's look at the change in these hormone concentrations during three hours of cycling.
Interestingly enough, look at glucose down here.
So we have time on the x-axis and then percent change.
We actually see blood glucose levels remain quite steady here.
And then of course, we're seeing all of our hormones go up.
I just told you though, we're getting an increase in these hormones that result in what?
What should that, I guess, I just told you about all the party that was at the liver,
and the liver's trying to release all this glucose, so
we should expect glucose levels to be much higher, but it's not.
Why?
Yeah, yeah, it's kind of like a rate of appearance,
rate of disappearance, like we talked about on lactate.
glucose uptake by the muscles is occurring at the same time.
So during exercise, insulin enables glucose uptake in the
muscles, but what did we learn about insulin concentration?
It goes down.
Insulin concentrations go down.
The nice thing though, insulin sensitivity goes up,
but we get more glucose uptake into the cells, but use less insulin.
What is going on, right?
I thought we needed insulin.
Well, before we get into this, let's just talk about what insulin does.
Insulin stimulates glucose uptake in the muscle cells.
So if we are acting on the muscle with insulin, that's gonna cause glucose to enter that cell.
If we look at changes in plasma glucose and insulin during
prolonged cycling at 65, 70% of the O2 max, this is glucose on
the left Y, insulin on the right Y, and then time over here.
Just like I mentioned before, insulin goes down with prolonged exercise.
And again, this is a very small magnitude, but look at this.
Glucose is kind of going up.
That's weird.
Let's think about this.
Plasma insulin decreases with prolonged or the uptake of glucose is going up.
So here we're kind of uptaking it inside of the muscle here.
Plasma insulin decreases with prolonged so maximal exercise,
yet the exercising muscle takes up seven to 20 times faster than at rest.
How is this possible?
when the underlying hormone is going down.
So let's maybe talk for a couple minutes, come up with
some ideas, and we'll come back together on this.
Okay, how are we doing here?
So just as a recap, during exercise, prolonged
or graded, cortisol, glucagon, catecholamines, all of these hormones are going up.
What is the role of those hormones?
release glucose, so we should expect to see glucose to increase.
We don't necessarily see the increase, we see it steady.
That means something causing it to bring it into the cell.
But if I have all this excess glucose inside of
the blood, what's the only hormone that's gonna get it, get
the cells to respond to bring the glucose into the cell?
Insulin, what happens to insulin during graded?
It goes down.
What the heck?
Any ideas of what's causing this?
Yep, keep going.
Ooh, I see what you were saying.
So you're saying the insulin decreases due to the binding of the receptors.
Is that kind of where you're going at?
So that's not quite what's going on, but yeah, that does happen.
So we become a little bit more sensitive to the insulin that we do have on board.
So if we are increasing the insulin sensitivity, we almost need less insulin to do the same job.
But that still wouldn't explain maybe the 10-fold decrease,
and then we're having such a large uptake of glucose.
And it's nothing that we really talked about in lecture so far.
I'm just curious of anyone.
Yeah, so let's just assume the insulin levels are very minor.
And they're so low that it does not account for all of this.
So even if we have an increased insulin sensitivity, the decrease in insulin
would we would expect to see a decrease in glucose uptake?
Not quite because we still need those transporters on the cell.
So insulin binds to the receptor, causes a secondary messenger system.
You get the GLUT4 transporters inside of the cell.
They translocate to the surface and those GLUT4 transporters are what's bringing in the glucose.
Yeah, yeah, so you're pretty much right on there.
We get Glut4 translocation in the skeletal muscle.
So here on the left, we have insulin.
So insulin binds to the receptor, secondary cascade.
And then we get these Glut4 receptors or transporters.
They translocate to the membrane.
And then we can start bringing in glucose to the cell.
Independent of insulin.
Exercise causes
the same translocation of these Glut4 transporters to the
surface of the membrane, and allows for glucose to be entering the cell.
You may have heard this term, this term is a little
bit newer, but we have, well, you've heard of this, this term's not new, but cytokines, what are those?
Does anyone remember what those are?
What are cytokines?
Anyone?
Yeah, it's basically the immune system releasing out some chemicals to cause some immune response.
The muscle has something called myokines.
So these myokines are being released during contraction.
We don't really know
or have a, we have an idea, but we haven't really established what those are.
We just kind of termed them myokines.
And those myokines are then interacting with these Glut4 receptors to cause them to translocate.
Whoa, that's pretty cool, right?
Like now we have two separate pieces.
Yes, insulin goes down, so we still have a little bit of insulin.
and that's still doing its job, but that's not accounting
for the large uptake of glucose in the muscles.
Instead, we have these myokines being released due to
contraction and some other factors that are causing the Glut4 receptors to translocate.
Okay, so let's look at this study here, kind of following up on that.
Progressive increase in glucose transporter, Glut4, in human sarcolymum vesicles.
So basically on the muscles during five and 40 minutes of exercise.
So here we have zero, five, and 40.
So we're seeing the Glut4 transporters increase.
We are seeing this increase.
If I clamp insulin, so this was a pretty cool study, where we're trying to see
if I clamp insulin or I remove the impact of insulin,
how much glucose am I uptaking just from exercise alone?
And it's this much.
Insulin definitely does a better job, so insulin alone does
a better job, but exercise still does a really good job.
And the cool part is, is they have an additive effect.
So if I then add insulin plus exercise, so those
myokines and insulin, I get a much larger response, so we get a much larger glucose uptake.
So this is pretty cool because anyone know
something interesting about insulin sensitivity in certain disease populations?
Yeah, so type two diabetes, those individuals have insulin sensitivity issues.
Well, exercise can help with that.
So even though they're having trouble responding to the insulin,
exercise is one of the only other things that they can
do to really help with insulin sensitivity as well as regulating those glucose levels.
So with, and we'll get into this a little bit later, but with regular exercise training,
depending on the situation, obviously certain things can go
too far where you have physical disruption of organs.
But this is a really good reason why type 2
diabetic patients can improve insulin sensitivity and almost kind
of revert back to normality if they undergo a normal exercise regimen.
Okay the one thing we also have to keep in mind,
blood flow, increasing blood flow activity to the muscles
during exercise results in an increased delivery of insulin despite the lower concentration.
So I know someone had mentioned this too, it's like a concentration gradient.
So even though we have a small amount of insulin, well it's like the reverse effect.
of some of the other hormones acting on the liver.
Well, we're restricting blood flow to the liver, and we're sending a lot of blood to the muscles.
Well, even though I have a decreased insulin concentration, a
lot of blood's going to that area, so you kind of get this increase in insulin sensitivity.
So two pieces, right?
You get that increased insulin sensitivity, as well as
the GLUT4 translocation due to exercise in itself.
Those two are independent.
but they can be additive to get a much greater effect.
Pretty cool, right?
I think it's pretty cool.
OK, so we'll stop here.
We'll pick up for the rest of the slides on Thursday.
Please let me know if you have any questions.
Stay warm.
Enjoy the rest of your day.