All right, welcome back everyone.
Okay, today we're gonna get started or finish, or make
a pretty decent dent in the skeletal muscle chapter eight slides.
But before I do that, the moment you've probably been
waiting for, I have received the grades for lab exam one.
I do often like to show
So again, please, if you don't have questions now, you're more
than welcome to email or set up a meeting with me or talk
about it anytime next week or this week if you have any questions.
All right.
So let's, I'm gonna do a quick review because we kind of
left off in the middle of this concept of muscle cramps.
So we talked about muscle cramps being involuntary
muscle contractions that are often associated with prolonged high intensity exercise.
We touched on this kind of this old classical theory of electrolyte depletion and dehydration.
We then touched in as far as limitations to that theory.
We talked about how dehydration is systemic.
It's everywhere.
But these localized cramps are not really experiencing that
large of a difference between the whole body.
But we only have this localized cramp.
They've also done some studies looking at the difference
between individuals who are cramping and not cramping.
And if you get them to dehydrate, it's not inducing cramps in everyone.
So there's a little bit of an issue here going on where
If you were removing the equation of this
electrolyte depletion theory or dehydration, individuals still cramp.
And I do want to clarify one thing.
Electrolytes and fluid intake is extremely important.
So I know I mentioned something about manufacturers always.
Manufacturers are trying to increase profits.
We do need electrolytes, and we do need fluid intake.
A heat stroke is way more important, in my opinion, than a cramp.
I would rather avoid heat stroke or heat stress in that instance.
But the difference is those two pieces have no impact on muscle cramps.
So it's not necessarily that you shouldn't be drinking electrolytes and fluid.
It's just we're trying to say that it has no bearing on muscle cramps.
And I think another great point was brought up about
maybe like, OK, if I don't have enough calcium, calcium is really important in muscle contractions.
OK, let's break that down really quick.
Sarcoplasmic reticulum is releasing calcium.
The calcium then goes where?
binds to, I think someone said it, troponin moves tropomycin,
reveals the site, and then you get the cross-bridge.
Once you get the cross-bridge, you get a muscle contraction.
If I reduce the concentration of calcium because I
have an electrolyte depletion theory, what happens?
If I remove calcium, no contraction.
That's the opposite of a cramp.
You could do that for any of the electrolytes
involved in the excitation-contraction coupling, as well as the cross-bridge formation.
Anywhere on there that you remove the electrolytes, it would do the opposite effect.
Obviously, we'd be dead.
But you wouldn't have an electrical signal to cause it to contract.
So those are the things that we need to think about, like mechanistically.
There's nowhere in that process that really has
a bearing with this dehydration electrolyte theory.
We then touched on, OK, well, we obviously get cramps.
We like to do research, and we want to try to kind of piece out maybe potential mechanisms.
This is not the only mechanism.
One other piece that I like to talk about,
If you don't, or what is ATP's role in the cross-bridge cycle?
So if we don't have ATP, what problem do we run into?
Yeah, the myosin head won't release.
If the myosin head doesn't release, and if I make a
strong contraction right now and then all of a sudden I deplete all the ATP, could I open my hand up?
No.
And that's kind of the fundamental basis behind rigor mortis.
There are other potential areas that could cause some issues.
Maybe acetylcholine esterase is a really important piece in muscle cramps.
I'm not saying this is the only thing, but this
is the only piece where we've actually established some evidence to support contribution in cramps.
So we have an increased excitatory activity of the
muscle spindles, a reduced inhibitory effect of the Golgi tendon organs.
If we do that, then that's causing
the kind of, I guess the cards to a line
where you're increasing the chances of experiencing a muscle cramp.
Since the muscle spindle is really trying to get the
muscle to contract and if I increase the activity of that, then I can induce a cramp.
If the Golgi tendon organ is detecting some type of tension
and I remove the ability for the Golgi tendon to inhibit those signals to contract,
then the muscle spindle is kind of having free reign
to get it to contract and you might experience a cramp.
We briefly talked about how stretching appears to relieve the muscle cramp.
This activates the Golgi tendon organ to try to inhibit the motor neurons.
You are applying some type of tension, and then you're
sending that signal to the Golgi tendon organ to inhibit, inhibit,
and inhibit, and a lot of the times that signal is strong enough to get the muscles to try and relax.
In addition, some massaging has been speculated to potentially
try to help, not reset, but maybe help change the activation of
the muscle spindles to try to get it to relax.
They've also done studies where they've kind of cut the
signal from the muscle spindles, and that inherently reduces cramps.
There's another thing.
that you may have heard of that can send some signals to those same areas.
So ginger and capsaicin is in red peppers and
they can activate these transient receptor potential kind of channels.
So these TRP channels here.
And they then send an inhibitory signal to the spinal
cord that then helps maybe reduce the overactive motor neurons that are causing cramping.
So of course, they didn't start with ginger and capsaicin.
They started by activating these TRP receptors.
They did it in mice models, and then they tried to move on to human models.
And when they activated these, they realized they
were reducing cramps or reducing the contractions.
So of course, right, clever individuals, they were thinking,
okay, well, what in food triggers these receptors?
And it happens to be ginger and capsaicin.
We find capsaicin in like red peppers, so spicy food.
So temperature and spicy sensation has been known to
try to, well, activate these channels and reduce the sensation
or the signal or the overactive signal that's being sent to the muscles.
Yeah.
Yeah, a little bit, but the magnitude of stimulation from
that isn't good, isn't great enough to trigger this.
If I knew this, as young entrepreneurs, what do you think you're gonna go out and try to do?
Yeah, make a muscle cramp juice with spicy stuff.
Well, has anyone heard of hotshot?
So this is the idea behind hotshot.
Now, they've run some trials on it and they don't eliminate cramps.
But they've suggested, their data kind of suggests that it might reduce some of the cramps.
So I'm not saying that, I have no affiliation here, but I'm not saying you should go out
and drink those, but to be honest, that's probably
the closest thing that might trigger these receptors for some individuals.
They've noted that it doesn't work for everybody, but that's the kind of idea behind this.
It's pretty neat though.
Okay, fiber types is the next topic here.
There's a little table here that you can go through and
fill out, very similar to the previous, I guess, energy pathway
table that we looked at at chapters three and four.
I would say this is a great place, oh yeah, sorry, go ahead.
Well, yeah, and that's what I'm saying.
It could be speculated that if you didn't have enough
ATP to release the myosin head, it would stay in that contracted kind of state.
Well, so there's no evidence to support that.
I'm just saying you could imagine, besides this altered
neuromuscular theory, there could be other areas that are influencing
an individual's ability to cramp.
Because if it only was this, then theoretically, I could eliminate cramps
by maybe triggering these TRP receptors.
And you don't eliminate cramps.
People still getting cramps, but it seems to reduce the impact or reduce the length or magnitude.
But it doesn't eliminate them.
So this is the best theory to date that we have the most evidence on.
Right now, we don't have any other evidence to support other theories.
Yeah.
That's a great question.
Thank you.
Oh, man, I feel like it's, sorry.
I know it gets loud in the back.
I don't know what's going on with the mic, but okay.
So yeah, go ahead and fill this out.
It'll be a good resource.
Obviously, there's not enough room to put a lot of
stuff, but if something's saying slow, fast, faster, then that's pretty easy to put into here.
OK, so how are skeletal muscle fibers typed?
Well, they're typed by you first have to do a muscle biopsy.
You take a small piece of muscle, you remove that, you put
it in a Petri dish, and you start going through some techniques to determine muscle fiber type.
It's pretty complex.
If you look at this chart here, there are a lot
of different names that have been used in a variety of different papers.
One of the biggest, I guess, changes that have been made
that we need to be a little bit careful about when
we're reading literature that's relatively recent is this idea that we went from type 2b to d and x here.
We'll talk about type 2b in a second, but a true type 2b
muscle fiber is not really expressed the way we believe it is in humans.
So they switched this notation from type 2B to type 2X.
Sometimes it's seen as D. So I would say this top row
was determined immunohistochemically.
And this is the fiber typing that we kind of go off of today, would be this top row.
But you've probably heard of a lot of these here, slow Twitch, fast Twitch, colors as well.
Some people had said red, intermediate, and white.
Those are also used in the literature or even in maybe common terms.
But just know that those were based off of older typing methods.
And now this newer one using kind of antibodies is the best method right now.
So this top row is the row we're going to be using as far as categorizing different fiber types.
What does it look like when we stain adult skeletal muscle or just skeletal muscle in general?
If I'm looking at type 1 fibers, they kind of light up here.
So on the left, this would be mouse models.
And then this would be human muscle over here.
And so we're seeing that, indeed, both mice and humans have these type 1 fibers.
And then type 2a, those are also lighting up here.
and in the mouse model, and same with type 2X.
Type 2B, we don't see any proteins being formed that are of the type 2B,
but the mouse models, cats, other animals do express and
fold proteins that kind of create these type 2B fibers.
Type 2b fibers, they generate the most amount of power.
So I guess they can generate more force compared to a type 2x fiber.
So in this instance, we're going from kind of on a force spectrum lowest to highest here.
So today, we basically say humans
We actually have the gene, we contain the gene for type 2B fibers.
It's always believed though that we just don't express those fibers, right?
Like we don't actually translate them into RNA and we go through and then fold these proteins.
But we do have that gene inside of our DNA.
And interestingly enough, in some rare conditions, we actually
get some of these fibers to start or we get these proteins to express or these genes to express.
So this is myosin heavy chain type 2b mRNA expression.
These are control individuals.
And over here, we basically have muscular dystrophy on all of these.
But this is a very unique version of the muscular dystrophy.
It's the Duchenne muscular dystrophy.
And they actually express this protein or this gene.
What's odd though is that even though they're expressing
it, they don't really produce the protein itself.
So even when they stain for it, some of them, it seems like there might be something going on.
And a more recent study in 2020, individuals went
through some high intensity exercise and they saw over here that in normal individuals,
that they're getting a little bit of expression of this type 2b myosin heavy chain pre-mRNA.
But in these individuals, we can get it to express
it just never really gets into the protein folding stage.
Because I get the very common question before this 2020
study, it was always like, well, if we have the gene,
All we have to do is really activate it, right?
There is ongoing research right now that they're trying to
see if we can get these proteins to activate, express, and then fold.
Or this gene, sorry, to activate and then express and then fold.
So it's kind of a scary but exciting area to kind of be looking at.
However, for now, we're kind of stuck on this type 1, type 2a, and type 2x.
Type 2-1 fibers, slow twitch, slow oxidative fibers.
Type 2A are these immediate fibers.
They're fast, oxidative glycolytic fibers.
And type 2B are the fast twitch fibers or the fast glycolytic fibers.
If we could stain a muscle, you would see the different fiber types throughout.
Okay, so we have these different fiber types.
We need to develop some characteristics to kind of distinguish the two.
And we're gonna start with biochemical properties.
For the biochemical properties, it would be the oxidative capacity.
In this instance, we're looking at the number of
capillaries that surround these kind of fibers that we're looking at.
also the mitochondrial density inside of these fibers, and the amount of myoglobin.
So you can imagine the more blood flow because of capillaries is gonna help deliver the oxygen,
well, you also probably need more mitochondria to help
utilize that oxygen to undergo oxidative phosphorylation.
Myoglobin is extremely important in kind of moving oxygen from the hemoglobin into the muscles.
So here, this is, it's relatively easy as far as, you
just need to look on one end versus the other because they're
kind of opposite, and then the type 2a is always in between.
Number of mitochondria low versus high, low versus high.
Non-oxidative or anaerobic versus aerobic, or oxidative.
OK, we'll move on to biochemical property number two.
This would be the type of myosin ATPase isoform.
That's a lot.
What's an ATPase, first of all?
Myosin ATPase.
It's kind of in the name, but where do we find this and what does it do?
Yeah, it breaks down ATP and where?
In the name.
In the myosin heads, right?
So this helps kind of break down the ATP, it hydrolyzes
it and we kind of release some of that free energy and get
it ready or the myosin gets ready to be in that kind of high energy state.
When we're looking at different isoforms, there are different types of the ATPase.
Those different types of myosin ATPase help break down or
kind of hydrolyze those ATPs faster or slower.
You have the fastest
or highest or the most ATP degradation or energy releasing
isoforms in the type 2X and then the lowest in the type 1.
The third biochemical property would be the abundance of contractile proteins.
Those contractile proteins are the sarcomeres, which are actin and myosin in the muscle fiber.
So you just have more actin and myosin in different fibers.
More in the type 2X, less in the type 1.
OK, now that we've moved or we talked about
the biochemical properties, let's talk about the contractile properties.
So the first one would be the speed of contraction.
This is dependent on that myosin ATPase activity.
The faster that I can break down those ATPs and cycle
through them, then the faster I can get another one to go
on, release the myosin head, and then it can contract again.
The faster you can undergo that cross-bridge cycling.
If we're looking at the speed of contraction,
We're saying type one is the lowest, type two X
is the fastest as far as maximal shortening velocity.
What is the mechanism behind some of that speed besides the ATPase activity?
Well, in addition to that, we have the sarcoplasmic
reticulum release, releasing ability or the rate of release is faster.
We've already touched on the ATPase activity.
But the faster we can get the calcium to kind of
come out of the sarcoplasmic reticulum and bind to that
troponin, the faster you get that signal, the faster you can do the cross-bridge cycling.
Are we OK here?
All right, second one.
Maximal force production.
And when we're talking about maximal force production, we're
looking at the force per unit of cross-sectional area.
We don't really get into the biomechanics of certain things, like penny angle,
if we're talking about the anatomical or physiological
cross-sectional area versus just the cross-sectional area.
We're not going to get into that.
All we're going to talk about here is just you're
able to produce more force per given cross-sectional area with the type 2x fibers versus the type 1.
Here's another figure that's depicting the same thing here.
Maximal specific force, type 1, type 2a, type 2x.
The reason, or why do we want to look at cross-sectional area?
Why is that important?
Maybe from a research perspective or from a conceptual piece.
Any ideas?
Yeah, like what if I just took, in my analysis as
I'm doing these biopsies, I just took a bigger chunk of muscle
and I compared the type 1 fiber to a smaller, a really small chunk of type 2x fiber.
And then I put them on a force transducer and I'm
like, oh look, type 1 fibers are generating more force.
Well, that's not a fair comparison because you just have
way more muscle in the type 1 fiber sample compared to the type 2.
And so larger muscle fibers, they do produce more force than smaller muscle fibers
because they contain more actinomycin, but you have to
make sure we're on the same cross-sectional area question.
OK.
With that in mind, what do we think here?
Okay, I'll close this down here.
Double check you have something in.
I'll close it down in five seconds or so.
All right, three, two, one.
Okay, like most things, right?
Are males stronger than females?
Well, it depends, right?
It's clear that if I got into an arm wrestling
match or any type of resistance training, I'm almost positive I'm
going to be at a disadvantage compared to this athlete over here.
I would even say that for this room or the varsity
athletes that we have in this school, there are a lot
of individuals who are stronger than me, female athletes.
And I know, we didn't have a leader board up the entire
time, but I know some of you ladies are throwing down some large watts on the wind gate.
I'm like, whoa, that's pretty impressive.
But, so, my point is though, right, it depends.
It really depends.
So, if we're just talking about a broad perspective, like,
oh, this person is stronger than that person, well, it does depend on the context of the question.
And we're going to try to parse out some of these things here.
OK, so skeletal muscle mass in men and women.
On an average base, if we took all the males and
compared them to the females, men have a significantly greater
total upper body and lower body skeletal mass.
They just typically have on average more muscle compared to females.
That doesn't mean every female has less muscle than the male, right?
But on average, they typically have a lower body mass.
If you have more muscle, you typically can generate a
higher absolute kind of force or weight movement.
So in terms of absolute force production, if we take examples from the Olympics,
the highest amount of weight for an Olympian, when we're
looking at the snatch, that is being produced by male athletes.
But if I look here,
There are women Olympians who are producing or have a higher snatch weight compared to the men.
And that's the same for other events.
So we can see that at certain areas, if we're looking at weight class,
that yeah, individuals who just have more muscle mass, an individual who's 105 kilograms,
I would expect them to be able to produce more force
than someone, even male or female, who is 50, 60 kilograms in body mass.
Then we need to look at maybe fiber type distribution.
There appears that
Between age and sex, there's no difference in fiber type distribution, meaning there's an equal,
on average, an equal amount of individuals or people across
age ranges and sex that have the same amount of type one percentage fibers.
Yes, there are some individuals who have more type one
compared to others, but between sexes and age, it's about the same.
So then let's take an account for all of these things.
If you express force production or strength, so this is
arm flexor strength on the Y and cross sectional area.
If you express it based on cross sectional area, there
is no difference between men and women on force production.
So if I take the same cross-sectional area muscle from any individual
and compare it to another individual of the same fiber
type, you're going to produce the same amount of force.
This would be kind of the same figure that we're
talking about, so knee extensor and elbow flexion.
If I am looking at force production on a cross-sectional area,
I can eliminate any differences in strength.
So regardless of sex or age, if an individual has a
higher muscle mass, I would expect them to generate more force, independent, again, of sex and age.
And we see that we've kind of provided that evidence by looking at these cross-sectional areas.
It just so happens to be that younger individuals who
are male have a higher muscle mass compared to others.
Okay, number three on the contractile property, higher power output.
So this is talking about high force, fast fibers have high power output.
If we're looking at power, we're looking at force times the shortening velocity,
the maximal power, like what we've been talking about before,
but type one's lowest, type two A is in the middle, type two X is the highest.
No surprise there.
Number four, muscle fiber efficiency.
Efficiency like we talked about, lower amount of ATP used to generate force.
The efficiency is quite low with type 2X fibers and high with type 1 fibers.
So we just talked about this and we don't need to break
off into a group or anything like that or class discussion.
Maybe I'll just get some ideas right now.
So now we know there's no apparent age or
sex difference in fiber type distribution, yet everybody's muscles are different.
The percentage of type one fibers that I have in my
body is going to be different from someone in this class.
It might be the same, but more than likely it will be different.
So why is that?
So what determines the distribution of respective fiber types in a muscle?
Genetics is probably the biggest piece.
Training, good.
That one we'll get into.
Sometimes people think like cart before the horse or chicken before the egg, right?
was I born with this fiber type distribution and then when
I was put in these sports and I just happened to excel
in them and then continue there, or did the training push me through?
A lot of times it's a little bit of both, but there's this debate that we believe
that it's more maybe you're just born with these fiber type distributions
and then you realize like, oh, I'm pretty good at
sprinting, I'm gonna stick with this because I hate running long distance and then vice versa.
What else?
Kind of on the same topic, but.
What would be the main difference, we've talked about
maybe on average, I'm saying men typically have a higher muscle mass compared to women.
Why?
What's different?
Hormones, right?
So hormones play a large role and you can see after
puberty, there's a big difference in the lean muscle mass compared to boys and girls, right?
Okay, so genetics, exercise habits, blood level of hormones,
those are all playing roles in the amount of maybe fibers or fiber type distribution.
But it is true that typically if we start sampling
from all of the power athletes or sprinters, they typically have a higher percentage of fast twitch fibers.
The endurance athletes or the distance runners typically have
a higher percentage of the slow fibers.
Again, we don't really know if it is only training or only genetics.
It's probably a little bit of both, but this is typically the distribution that we see.
Please do not try to memorize this table, but it is
nice to look at if you're curious on fiber type distribution between different athletes.
If you want to spend a lot of time on a
table with these distributions, you could just look at this one, right?
So in general, distance runners have a higher percentage
of type one fibers compared to track athletes, and then non-athletes typically are right in that 50%
like kind of area.
But there is a considerable amount of variation among successful athletes.
You don't have to have 80% type one fibers to be a successful endurance athlete.
We just typically find that spread in the highest amount for these types of athletes.
And in addition, oh yeah, go ahead.
Exactly, yeah, yeah.
There is no one parameter that is predicting performance, no matter what event it is.
It's usually a wide, multifactorial combination of parameters
or indices that are determining whether someone has good or high success in a particular sport.
For a while, people thought Usain Bolt would never become a good sprinter because he was too tall.
But it turns out he's one of the greatest short distance sprinters that we've seen.
But things happen, right?
It doesn't necessarily mean you have to have a certain mold to be successful at a sport.
OK.
So now that we've kind of gone through and I'm saying,
okay, all these fiber types are kind of pushed in over here and that we have these type of distributions.
I'd like to share really quick a study on these fiber types because it's quite interesting.
A lot of these are done
These muscle biopsies are not easy to do.
And if I was an Olympic athlete, I would not want to take these muscle biopsies ever.
You are removing a piece of force-generating tissue, and I don't really want to undergo that.
So we have to be careful about some of this data.
But there was a really great study done in 2015 where they took a
very recent retired world record holder for short distance Olympic event.
So as soon as he kind of said he was retired,
they asked him to be in the study, and he was like, sure.
And they took a bunch of muscle biopsies.
No surprise here, if we're looking at type 1 versus type
2 over here, these are both type 2, that 30% type 1 and then maybe closer to the 60%.
And then there are these hybrid fibers where you have type 1
and type 2A and then type 2A and type 2X.
And so that's in there too, and that's what these are.
Don't worry too much about that, and I'd never test you on these hybrid fibers.
This is more for kind of, it's fun to look at some of these things.
Okay, so this sprinter has a larger percentage of type two fibers versus type one,
and so maybe that's why, or there's nothing really special
going on, and maybe something else is going on that's helping with his performance.
If we look at maybe the single muscle fiber power
that's being generated, this is kind of the trend that we're looking at, right?
If we're looking at a fast twitch type to a fiber, they're all
It's nothing crazy, right?
They're all generating around the same amount of power.
And then the slow type one fiber over here, everyone's
kind of generating the same amount of fiber regardless if
you're a distance runner versus untrained versus a competitive swimmer, right?
But let's look at this kind of Olympic athlete.
What was surprising here is the amount of power that this individual muscle fiber was generating.
was quite high.
And so this started to question this notion that we all have
the exact same type of type 1, type 2 fiber.
Now, this is one person that doesn't necessarily mean, OK, now we have to change our thought.
We would theoretically have to get a larger sample size to be able to kind of parse this out.
But this kind of questions this idea that, OK, everybody's
fiber is going to be generating the same amount of power.
I would never test you on this.
Please stay on the same track that we've been going on in class.
But it's fun to see these things.
Potentially, right?
And so this stirred a lot of debate, like, well, we need more data.
Like, this just happened to be the reason why this sprinter was successful.
Let's check, because it's always like, well, did they train
to this point, or were they born like this?
And so that's why that debate will never go away until
we can actually, we would never do this, right?
Get a bunch of children and start like typing them
and then pulling muscle fibers out and then follow them
through their career, like breed them into Olympians, right?
Then we can do that.
Someone else had a question up here?
No?
Maybe I missed some.
But yeah, this is pretty interesting, right?
And it's hard to look at these things with just one
individual, but this is pretty crazy as far as the
amount of power that it was being generated from some of these individuals here.
But yeah, they did hold the world record, and so that could be something there.
Could be something.
OK.
This might be a good place to stop here.
We'll talk about force regulation and muscle on Tuesday.
Stay warm.
Have a great weekend.