you
All right.
Welcome back, everyone.
We'll get started here.
I'm sure you are all very eager to get your lecture exam scores back.
I am still waiting on those to get back to me, so as soon as I know, you'll know.
But that does remind me to make sure we're kind of
shifting a little bit of the attention to the next big assessment, which is what?
Yeah, the lab exam.
So you have the lab exam in a couple of weeks.
So make sure you're staying on top of that.
So this week would be lab five.
That'll be the last lab that you'll be responsible for for lab exam one.
The nice thing is next week you'll have an entire lab
section to go over any of the previous labs as well as lab five.
You can work through some worksheets, maybe review the
quiz questions and anything that you've gotten wrong.
That way you have a better understanding of maybe what you need to focus on to study.
And then obviously get through some of the calculations that you might not have understood.
Did you have a question?
Yeah.
Yeah, because there won't be enough chairs in a lot
of the other sections, we're hoping that you go to your signed section.
But again, if it's like if something comes up and you
really can't go, then maybe you can reach out to see if they have some room in the other section.
But one of the other big things is your TA is going
to hand back your worksheet as well as your old quizzes that you can review.
So it works out a little bit better for everyone if you can.
But we understand that things come up.
Yeah.
Yeah, thanks for asking, though.
I'll have some more details next week on maybe what you should be looking for on the lab exam.
But for now, are there any broad questions?
Okay, very good.
So we are starting on the new unit, so this will be the second unit for your second lecture exam.
The exams are not cumulative, but you could imagine that if you don't really understand
energy production from a certain pathway that might hinder
your ability to understand some of these upcoming concepts.
So no, I will not directly ask you on, say, chapters three and four lecture slides,
but if we're using some of that base fundamental knowledge
to go over something in the skeletal muscle, it might be good to make sure you understand those concepts.
Exam two, we're gonna start with skeletal muscle.
We're gonna go through the structure as well as function and how it applies to exercise.
Okay, so.
Structure and function is where we're gonna start.
Just like I mentioned, we'll go through muscle
actions, neuromuscular junction, and muscular contraction.
We'll get into the oh-so-popular exercise-associated muscle cramp
topic, so that'll be kind of interesting.
We'll briefly go through muscle fiber types and the different.
the different types of muscle fibers as well as how we actually get to fiber typing.
So the different procedures in typing muscle fibers.
Force regulation in muscle.
And then another really popular topic with muscle soreness,
which I think you will probably have an idea where I'm going with that already.
So we'll just start with an easy question here just to get people going.
Muscle weighs more than fat.
True or false?
Okay, so we'll take a couple more seconds with this one.
If you need a little bit more time, let me know.
Yeah, no worries, no rush.
We'll take about another 30 seconds.
I'll check back in in 30 seconds here.
It's just a question to get you thinking about these different tissues.
Okay, does anyone need a little bit more time getting set up?
Okay, I'll close this down here in five seconds.
Three, two, one.
Okay, most of you are answering true, but like most
of these type of questions that I've shown you,
It depends, right?
So what's a better way that I could have worded this question?
Yeah, so which one is more dense?
That would probably be the better way to word this, but it
was just to get you to think about this concept that
Well, one pound of fat is the same thing as one pound of muscle.
The largest difference between these two tissues would be that
muscle is more dense and takes up less space.
If something's more dense for the same amount of weight, it just takes space.
So here on the left, this is always a fun picture to
look at, but if this is five pounds of fat, this would be five pounds of muscle.
Muscle.
weighs or takes up a large proportion of our total body weight.
Depending on each individual, it is different, but on average,
we're looking at more than 40 to 50% of your total body weight.
And there are over 600 skeletal muscles in the body.
Luckily, you do not need to worry about those
600 muscles because you've already taken anatomy, meaning you've already been tested on that, right?
I'm not gonna test you on all 600 here.
But let's look at the basic structure and function.
So anytime we start reviewing some of these concepts, remember that they are review.
You shouldn't spend a lot of time on them, but you should just know the basic understanding of it.
So skeletal muscles are attached to bones by tough connective tissues.
We call those tissues tendons.
One end of the muscle is attached to the bone that does not move.
we call that the origin.
The opposite end is fixed to a different bone and we call that the insertion.
And that one is moved during muscular contraction.
And so here we can look at the masseter muscle here and it's moving the mandible up and down here.
So this is kind of basic origin and insertion that
just helps us determine whether you're actually moving another bone.
We also want to get into the structure of the skeletal muscle.
So it's good to, or I recommend maybe starting here and then kind of working your way down.
You definitely can start lower and work your way up.
But if we are looking at
This little chart here, we go from muscle to fascicles
to cells or fibers, and then myofibrils, and then thick and thin filaments.
So here on the top, we have an entire muscle.
And then inside of this muscle bundle, we have our fascicle.
And then inside of the fascicle, we have a muscle fiber.
And then inside the fibers, we have myofibrils.
And then inside of there, we have our kind of contractile protein, the sarcomeres.
So these are kind of where we're actually generating the force.
We'll touch on this a little bit more, but the big
thing or I guess controversy that we kind of have or
debate in exercise physiology is can we increase the number of fibers?
And we'll touch on that, but in general, we typically
don't increase the number of fibers, we typically increase the
number of sarcomeres, and we do that in parallel.
But again, we'll touch on that when we get to that topic.
So, no, you don't have to memorize these, but if we start talking about
increase in muscle fibers or changes in muscle fibers, you know we're talking at this level.
If we're talking about sarcomeres, we're talking at this level here.
Okay, but we don't just have a bunch of muscle fibers or sarcomeres.
We have other structures that are very important in muscular contractions.
For example, we have mitochondria, we have the
transverse T-tubules, we have sarcoplasma, sarcolemma, we have all
kinds of things that are associated with the muscle fiber.
Some of the more important organelles that we will be
focusing on will be the mitochondria as well as some of the nuclei that are surrounding the muscle fiber.
So skeletal muscle fibers are very unique because they have
a lot of nuclei among or around the entire length of the muscle fiber.
And as far as the mitochondria, this also makes sense
to me because if these contractile proteins are in high demand of energy,
Well, we would need the organelles that are responsible for generating a lot of energy.
So we have a lot of mitochondria on the surface and within the muscle cells.
Two distinct mitochondria or subpopulations of mitochondria that we'll be focusing on.
One would be the subsarcolemia mitochondria or the SS mitochondria.
This is located directly underneath the cell membrane or the sarcolemma.
These mitochondria are more important or they kind of
supply the majority of the energy, the cellular energy to
maintain active transport of ions across the sarcolemma.
Does anyone remember, you don't need to know this, but sometimes it's nice to think about it,
but does anyone remember what those transporters are or
what they're called or what they're transporting or moving across the sarcolemma?
Any ideas?
Say again?
So yeah, not in this instance, but maybe just to establish the membrane potential.
Yeah, the sodium potassium pumps.
So that's essentially what they are powering here.
OK, the intermyofibular mitochondria or the IMF, these are
located near the myofibular proteins or those contractile proteins.
These are the mitochondria that are supplying the ATP needed for contraction.
This is just a longitudinal section of a skeletal
muscle that are showing the different mitochondria that are kind of dispersed along these cells.
OK, so how do we go from a single cell to these muscle fibers?
Well, we have these myoblasts.
They differentiate into satellite cells.
They get some nuclei.
And then you have an immature muscle fiber that then
eventually develops into this muscle fiber in itself.
So the key piece here which we'll talk about would be the myoblasts and then the satellite cells.
It's kind of the focus that this slide is trying to get you to look at here.
What are satellite cells?
Well, satellite cells are important cells that play a role in muscle growth and repair.
If an individual is in the process of creating more
muscle fibers or even, I guess, sarcomeres, we increase the number of satellite cells.
In addition, we increase the number of nuclei.
So, more nuclei allow for greater protein synthesis.
we are reliant on these nuclei for muscle growth.
Because of that, if we increase a lot of these nuclei,
we typically see a large change in those numbers as we experience hypertrophy or muscle growth.
The nice thing about that, these nuclei are slow
to degrade compared to the actual muscles themselves.
So the sarcomeres kind of reduce at a faster rate compared to the nuclei.
And so when you get some type of atrophy or loss of muscle,
you maintain the nuclei that are surrounding the fibers.
And so it takes a shorter time to get you back to the previous state of hypertrophy.
So here we have that untrained individual.
You get the satellite cell fusion that are going to increase the number of nuclei.
And that's going to really help with hypertrophy.
If you are under a state of detraining or atrophy, you will maintain the number of nuclei.
That way retraining becomes a lot easier or you decrease the
time to get to the same level of hypertrophy.
Okay, functions of skeletal muscle.
Ultimately, we think of skeletal muscle as force production cells
that really help us do work as far as mechanical work.
We also produce force in order for us to move air in and out of our lungs.
Everyone right now is experiencing some sort of postural support.
So me standing up right now, are you sitting, right?
We're able to maintain posture, and that's because our
muscles are using some sort of force production.
The one piece that I know we all know about but
we kind of forget sometimes would be that our muscles are extremely good at generating heat.
We kind of touched on this concept before because our
muscles or our body's ability to convert food energy into
actual kind of mechanical work, it's not very good at that, right?
We're not very efficient.
We actually generate
a substantial amount of heat when we are converting some of the energy in our bodies.
So this is the piece right here.
A more recent function of the skeletal muscle that I
kind of introduced in the previous unit would be muscle as an endocrine gland.
So skeletal muscles produce something called myokines during contraction.
Some of the signals that are believed to be sent are
dealing with glucose update as well as fatty acid oxidation.
These signals also promote blood vessel growth or capillary
density inside of the muscle or around the muscle.
And then they also promote liver glucose production and triglyceride breakdown.
There are other functions that we've kind of touched on.
One of those myokine signals were believed to help
with the glute four translocation to the surface of the membrane to bring glucose in.
Some other ones would be interleukin-6, IL-6.
This is just a pro and anti-inflammatory signal.
If we undergo kind of regular submaximal kind of moderate exercise intensity,
that can help promote an anti-inflammatory environment and
reduce some of that chronic inflammation and reduced risk of
heart disease and other types of metabolic disorders.
So we've kind of touched on this one already about
You know, this concept of inflammation and how acute
inflammation cannot necessarily always be a bad thing.
We always kind of label it as a bad thing, but it can be quite helpful.
Chronic inflammation is something that we try to reduce,
and regular exercise activity can help that.
Okay, muscle actions will be the next topic here.
This one's pretty straightforward, right?
We can either have some type of action where we're, if I'm looking at the joint angle,
my elbow here, I can flex and decrease the joint angle
here or I can extend and that's gonna increase the joint angle.
So these are two types of movements that we have.
But we also know we can produce quite a bit of
force without actually changing the length of the object or even the joint angle.
So static actions, static muscle actions are just when you
are trying to produce force, but you're not really changing any distance or muscle or joint angles.
So if I were to just press on this wall here, and
I'm trying to move the wall, well, the wall wouldn't move, but
I'm generating a lot of force and attempt to move the wall.
Okay, so now we have these three kind of
major muscle actions or force-generating pieces, right, flexion, extension, and static.
We wanna talk about going back to the flexion and extension, some type of dynamic movement.
So dynamic movement, we're just talking about movement, right?
If I have a static movement,
That's you can't really have static movement But if you have a static muscle
that muscles not moving if we have a dynamic muscle it is moving concentric Activities
or actions are when the muscle shortens during force production
So in this instance you would have an arm kind of holding a weight down here and
And moving it up, if we're talking about the bicep, the
bicep is flexing, and this is a concentric motion.
So muscle shortening during the force production.
Eccentric is where we have the force production, but the
joint angle, if we're talking about the bicep here, is getting larger.
So the length is increasing here.
These eccentric movements are extremely important when an individual
is trying to focus on muscle growth.
The reason being is it causes the majority of the
muscle fiber injury, then your body responds to that stress by hypertrophy or growing and repairing those.
But it is also associated with the majority of the
soreness that we experience during any type of weight-bearing exercise.
So this will be important when we start talking
about these concepts of muscle injury and soreness.
It's the eccentric motions that are causing the most damage.
Okay, this is a little summary slide of everything that
we just kinda went over on the muscle actions.
So if you would like to kind of review things, this might be a good table to look at.
So if in a couple weeks you can look at the slide
and you can define all these terms here, you're gonna be in good shape.
Okay, muscles just can't contract on their own.
They need to be sent a signal to tell the muscles to contract.
This is where we get into this neural muscular junction and contraction topic here.
But before we do that, it's nice to talk about
the peripheral nervous system and the central nervous system here.
So the central nervous system is the brain and the spinal cord, right?
So we're just talking about the central or the center of the body.
This is also a good point to talk about, like if
you've ever heard, you may have seen this question already,
but if we talk about central versus peripheral fatigue, this is kind of what it's referring to.
Maybe central nervous system is responsible for some of that fatigue versus the periphery.
Okay, peripheral nervous system is over here.
We're gonna be looking at the motor division.
There are two branches, somatic as well as the autonomic.
we're gonna be focusing on the somatic nervous system for these skeletal muscles.
Okay, somatic motor neurons of the peripheral nervous
system are responsible for sending that signal from the spinal cord to the skeletal muscles.
So when I'm telling my arm to move, that signal's coming
from the brain moving all the way down and getting the arm to move through the somatic motor neurons.
Each one of these neurons, motor neurons, are synapsing on a number of different fibers.
We can compile or kind of categorize the motor neuron
and all the fibers that it happens to innervate as a motor unit.
So if we have this motor neuron here and it's synapsing on these different fibers,
Well, the neuron as well as the fibers in that junction is the motor unit.
Here's just another kind of figure showing that motor unit.
So we have the neuron here, and it's synapsing on these different fibers here.
This synapse here kind of forms a motor end plate.
So this pocket formed around the motor neuron by the sarcolemma here.
We can then zoom in on this area here to kind of just see the motor end plate.
So if you remember, we're going to just review some of this physiology.
You get that signal from the brain.
It goes all the way down.
We get to that motor end plate or that junction.
Calcium is rushing in kind of into the motor neuron.
And then from there, acetylcholine is released.
It then binds to the sarcolemma.
And then you get that signal to go down the T-tubule.
We're going to talk about all that.
And then you get into the sarcoplasmic reticulum.
Calcium comes out in that whole fun process.
But before we do that, we need to talk about what is that kind of functional unit.
This is the functional unit.
So sarcomeres are that functional unit that we're gonna be talking about.
They contain specialized arrangements of thin and thick filaments.
When we're talking about the thin filaments, we're
talking about the actin, tropomyosin, and troponin.
The thick filaments are the myosin.
To make sure we can kind of understand the movement of
the sarcomere, we need to make sure we remember or review some of the major components of a sarcomere.
So we have our Z line, our M line, kind of the I band, A band, and the H zone.
All of those can be found up here, right?
So we have our M line, which is basically this centerpiece right here.
And then if we want the Z disk, we're looking at this
kind of Z structure or Z pattern right here, which is also in this piece right here.
If we want to look at the I band, it would be kind of the spacing between the myosin.
So if we're looking at this spacing that's over the Z disc, that would be this I band.
And then the A band would be just the length of these thick filaments right here.
So if we're looking at the A band, we're over here.
And then the H zone would just be in this kind of in between the thin filaments.
So between this one and this one would be the H zone here.
And we're gonna basically be closing in on the H zone during contraction.
Or you would reduce the H zone.
So no worries if you don't remember this from anatomy,
physiology, but you'll just spend a little bit of time reviewing these pieces here.
Okay, so how do we actually get a muscular contraction?
Well, this is happening due to something called the sliding filament model.
So we can get that H zone to kind of
compress by shortening these sarcomeres, or these muscles, due to
the movement of the thin filament over the thick filament.
In order for those two to make a connection and
have that movement, we need to form something called a cross bridge.
Once you make that cross bridge, those myosin heads can
then pull on those thin filaments and again cause the sarcomere to kind of shorten or contract.
When that sarcomere does contract, we can see the spacing here changes.
So we're reducing the distance between the z lines of each sarcomere that's lined up.
So if we have one sarcomere on the other one.
If you are bringing the z lines closer to each other, you're also closing this gap here.
As you can see with these kind of subsequent figures.
Okay, let's take a few minutes, just in case, if you
haven't already, and label the diagram of the sarcomere with the appropriate terms.
So we'll take a couple minutes.
This will be a nice little break for you to review some of these pieces.
Okay, how are we doing with this one?
Doing okay?
Anyone need a little more time?
Okay, so I would say it would be good, we won't spend too much time on this
because I've already went through it, but it would be good
to make sure and fill in this chart or circle the correct answer.
That way,
you can prepare yourself for questions like this one.
During a bicep curl, the sarcomeres within the biceps brachii shorten.
What else will shorten within the sarcomere?
All right, let's take maybe 30 more seconds on this one, unless you need more time.
I'll check back in in 30 seconds.
Not that I need to remind you, but is there anything going on with the clicker questions?
Is there any unique advantage to getting the clicker questions right?
Say again?
Yeah, yeah.
So if we can get 100%, I'm gonna put it on the exam.
So just throwing that out there.
Thank you.
Okay, I'll close this one up here in 10 seconds.
Double check that you have something in.
All right, three, two, one.
Okay, nice job, nice job.
The correct answer is E.
And B. So if you remember, the H zone and the I band do shorten or you kind of close those areas.
The A band is just the length of the thick filaments.
So that'll never really change.
So here's that H zone here and then the I band over here.
The A band is just, again, the length of the thick filaments.
Okay, you probably knew this was coming, but we're
gonna talk about the relationships among troponin, tropomycin, mycin, and calcium.
Right?
So.
We already talked about this, but if you just remember,
calcium is gonna be released from the sarcoplasmic reticulum, and
then you're gonna get that calcium to bind to troponin.
That's gonna cause a conformational change in these
little strands right here called the tropomycin.
That's gonna reveal the actin binding site, and that's gonna
allow for these myosin heads here to then bind and form a cross bridge.
and then you'll have that movement or these heads pivot in order for us to get that power stroke.
To have all of this continue to cycle, we need energy during this process.
So ATP is required for muscular contraction, but I mean,
we know overall it's part of the contraction, but the actual
role for ATP, does anyone remember what the ATP directly does when it kind of gets to the myosin head?
Yeah, so that actually causes the release of the myosin
head and then you have the interactions to kind of get it
into the kind of high energy state a little bit later.
That way you don't waste any time.
So as soon as that actin site is available or that
binding site is available, then the myosin head will grab onto it.
So you don't have to waste time into getting into that kind of high energy state.
But myosin ATPase breaks down the ATP as the fiber contracts.
This is kind of that interaction that we've already
kind of touched on before, where you're breaking the ATP down
into ADP, but it releases a phosphate as well as some energy.
We don't need to spend time right now going
through the ATP sources for muscular contraction because we've already done that.
But this might be a quick review slide that might be helpful.
Even though I already did it for you, let's
place the five stages of the excitation-contraction coupling in the correct order.
Use one for the earliest event and five for the latest event.
If you need some reference on the order, the one is up
here and the five is down here, and start labeling the appropriate ones
for the descriptions down here.
Okay, are we doing pretty good with this one?
You're like, ah, it's too easy.
Well, let's see how easy it was.
Reading from top to bottom.
What are the five steps of the excitation contraction coupling?
OK, let's go another 20 seconds, 30.
We'll go 30 seconds from here.
Okay, does anyone need a little more time?
Okay, I'll close it down in three, two, one.
All right, nice job.
Most of us got this correct.
We are looking for D. No, oh, you wanna see, yeah.
87.
That's not bad, though.
That's good.
OK.
So the first one we're going to be dealing
with, action potential stimulates acetylcholine release at the neuromuscular junction.
Acetylcholine produces that action potential that then propagates
across the sarcolemma down the T-tubule.
Action potential gets calcium to be released from the sarcoplasmic reticulum.
Calcium binds the troponin.
initiate tropomycin displacement, revealing those binding sites, and
then you get the mycin forming the cross bridge.
Okay, so then when you get the cross bridge, what happens?
So let's place the following seven stages of the cross bridge cycling in the correct order.
You probably know what's coming after this, so.
I guess technically you only had to do six stages, because you have the first one at least.
Okay, when you're ready, let's put them in order, rating from top to bottom here.
Okay, let's take a couple more seconds with this, unless someone needs a little more time.
We have, I think, one clicker missing.
I'll close it down in 10 seconds here.
Five, three, two, one.
Okay, how did we do?
We did great, nice job.
Okay, yes, the correct answer would be B. So we can,
you can kind of look through these and view them on your own time here.
So hopefully this was a little bit of review from physiology as well as anatomy.
But overall, these steps are pretty important for you to understand so we know
if there was an issue at one of these steps because
of exercise or because of something going on, it's nice
to know where in that process something's being disturbed.
For example,
I know I'm hitting you with a lot of clicker questions
today, but I'm trying to give some relevant type questions.
If an athlete takes a drug that increases calcium release from the sarcoplasmic reticulum,
but it does not enhance muscle contraction, it is
suspected that the drug accidentally bound to the thin filament,
blockade of which structure in the thin filament would
prevent calcium binding and skeletal muscle contraction.
OK, how are we doing with this one?
A little more time?
See one or two nods.
Let's go another 20 seconds then.
All right, I'll close this down in three, two, one.
Oh, we're getting more clickers.
Now I'll close it down.
Three, two, one.
Okay, how'd we do?
Oh, I thought we were, that's okay.
No, this is good.
This is good.
Okay.
So the correct answer is D.
Does the structure of this clicker question look familiar?
Does that seem like close to the exams?
Okay.
So, hopefully I can keep giving exam-style questions on
these clicker questions to get you thinking.
If someone was trying to enhance contractions by increasing
the amount of calcium that's being released, you first have
to recognize what calcium is doing in that entire process.
Calcium, getting released from the sarcoplasmic reticulum, is
binding to troponin, and that way you can initiate that
whole cross-bridge cycle to get that muscle contraction.
If I take a drug, or I take anything,
and inadvertently that drug also binds to something that
blocks any type of myosin head from binding to an area
or from tropomyosin from even moving, that would be a big problem.
In this one, the problem is that calcium cannot bind to something to move tropomyosin.
In that instance, the only thing that could be would
be the binding site for calcium, which is troponin.
Are we OK with this question?
Does anyone have any comments or concerns?
Or maybe even in the wording?
OK.
Okay, let's move on to exercise-associated muscle cramps.
This is just a clicker-filled day today.
True or false?
Salt tablets, bananas, pickle juice, and sports drinks
can prevent and relieve exercise-induced muscle cramps.
Okay, let's go 20 more seconds here.
Five clickers.
Three, two, one more.
Okay, I'll close this down in three, two, one.
Okay.
I like to show this only because it's nice to see where everyone's at, right?
Most people are saying true here.
I'm not gonna grade it because we're gonna talk about this here.
I hope I get a lot of feedback here from the group.
Okay, muscle cramps.
Muscle cramps could be kind of defined as a
kind of involuntary muscle contraction that's happening at maybe a
higher rate and you kind of feel your muscles tense up, right?
So you get that muscle cramp.
Often, people associate this with prolonged high-intensity exercise.
There is a theory that most of you believe,
which is the electrolyte depletion and dehydration theory.
This theory states that water and sodium loss via sweating causes spontaneous muscle contractions.
These contractions are more likely to occur in a hot environment.
This is where we're gonna ruffle some feathers here.
To date though, few, if not any studies support
the concept that exercise induced muscle cramps result from the electrolyte imbalance.
This has been well established in the exercise physiology community.
But I like to throw it out to the group.
What are some of the limitations of the electrolyte
depletion and dehydration theory to explain muscle cramps?
So based on what you've heard, what you've learned maybe in
the past, to get you to answer true, 98% of us answer
true, but I just told you that very few studies support this concept or this theory.
So try to go onto the other side and poke holes into your existing belief.
What are some limitations of the electrolyte depletion
and dehydration theory in explaining muscle cramps?
So try to chat with your classmates for a little bit
and let's come up with a few maybe limitations of this theory.
Okay, what are we thinking?
Can I get some ideas from this side of the room here?
Not that I'm picking on this side at all.
But put on your like, your researcher hat, right?
You want to...
come up or provide some evidence to support your
previous claim, right, true versus false, that there needs to
be some type of electrolyte solution that is going to help reduce cramps.
If that is the case, right, because we need to be careful with associations.
Just because something's associated doesn't mean there's a causal relationship.
So how do we parse this out?
So one, either come up with some limitations, or two,
maybe come up with a study design really quick.
So what are we thinking on this side?
How could we prove this, or how could we look at this, or what are some limitations here?
Yeah, yeah, so that's one of the easiest and the first studies that were done.
Just get two individuals or two groups of individuals, have
them go out, one has electrolytes and one does not, and see whether one group cramps more than the other.
So that's a good one.
What else?
Any ideas?
What are some limitations or ways we can look at this?
Say that one more time.
Yeah, so we just spent a lot of time on these clicker questions.
Tell me where on there that we're having a really
big issue with blood concentrations of these electrolytes and in the muscle contractions.
Yeah, yeah.
I will say a lot of that still kind of local
inside of the muscle in the sarcoplasmic reticulum does a perfectly fine job of providing enough calcium.
Now, there could be issues with the re-uptake of calcium, or if I have acetylcholine
and acetylcholine esterase isn't there to clear that up, so
you're sending that signal on and on and on, but that has nothing to do with eating a banana.
Any other limitations?
So one of the things we can think about is the same concept for lactate.
If we did that study, we could also add another arm to that study or a group
and say, well, let's look at two different groups or everybody and who cramps
and doesn't cramp, then I could just take some blood
samples and look at the differences between electrolyte and dehydration.
And they have done those studies.
And there is no difference.
and when someone is severely dehydrated versus hydrated or
not dehydrated, and the number of cramps that they're experiencing.
In addition, they've done a lot of studies where they've electrically stimulated muscles, right?
Very similar to something you might see at like a, maybe at like a,
I don't know, physical therapy clinic where they're putting
on some electrodes and they stimulate the muscle.
Well, they do that at a much higher current and frequency
and they see at what point in time will someone start cramping and then look at some of these factors.
And they have not found anything associated with electrolytes.
Another issue would be where are electrolytes in the blood distributed?
Do you have blood everywhere?
Yeah.
Where do you normally have a cramp?
Your whole body?
When you're dehydrated, yeah, like one single muscle.
When you're dehydrated, are you just dehydrated in that muscle?
No, your whole body's dehydrated, but we don't just go into a full body cramp, right?
And same thing with electrolytes.
They've measured those.
They've changed those concentrations.
And that systemic kind of blood concentration of these electrolytes aren't really causing issues.
In addition, what if I get a cramp or you see
on television an athlete having a cramp, what's the first thing
you see maybe the athletic trainer trying to help out with?
Does anyone know?
Yeah.
They'll try to stretch it or maybe massage it.
And if you've had a cramp, do you feel like massaging and stretching sometimes helps?
Probably most of you would agree that, yeah, some
sort of manipulation of that area, physical manipulation of that
area does help, whether it's massaging or stretching.
I'm not saying that it's impossible, but as of right
now, we don't have any evidence to support this dehydration electrolyte theory in muscle cramps.
Why are, what do electrolytes do?
Yeah, that's where the debate comes, where some would
argue that there are large industry groups that are promoting something to make sales.
But I don't want to introduce that piece.
The other thing though is electrolytes are very important, not necessarily for cramping though.
If I go out and I don't have some type
of solution that is replacing electrolytes and carbohydrates and fluid,
I'm gonna run into a lot of issues, especially with dehydration, right?
So that's a separate issue as far as from
a thermoregulatory standpoint, but not a cramping standpoint.
So then the next question should be, well, if
it's not the electrolyte theory, electrolyte dehydration theory, what else can we look at?
Well, to date, the altered neuromuscular control theory is
the only one where we have substantial evidence supporting the contribution of this theory and cramps.
So there's an abnormal spinal reflex activity due to fatigue.
This results in increased excitatory activity of the muscle
spindles and a reduction in the inhibitory effect of the Golgi tendon organ.
Whoa, muscle spindles and Golgi tendon organ.
You probably haven't heard of those.
in a long time.
So let's look at this.
If we have increased muscle spindle activity, the muscle
spindles, their goal is to detect stretches in the muscle.
The sensory neurons conduct action potentials in the spinal cord, and that helps with
the muscle to contract and resist being stretched.
So if you stretch your muscle too much, the muscle
spindle is basically like, whoa, whoa, whoa, whoa, too much.
We don't wanna cause damage, so we wanna activate and kind
of get it to come back, not to stretch it too much.
That means in this theory, there's just an increase in this activity.
If you increase this activity, it's gonna cause additional
contractions when you don't really want it.
In a lot of animal models, yeah.
Well, yeah, and so those are very similar to this
piece where they think there's an overactivation of something.
One of those somethings would be the muscle spindle.
So in many animal models, they've induced cramps and they cut this signal and the cramps go away.
which kind of makes sense, right?
If I cut that neuron and I sever the connection, then there's nothing telling it to over-activate.
And then on the flip side, if you stimulate the
muscle spindles excessively, you induce a cramp, yeah.
And then on the flip side to the muscle spindle, the Golgi tendon organ activity decreases.
So the Golgi tendon organ detects tension when applied to a tendon.
Inhibition of the alpha motor neuron causes muscle
relaxation, relieving the tension applied to the tendon.
So this is if I have too much, then you get
this inhibitory action of the goldie tendon organ to try to get the muscle to relax.
If you decrease that inhibitory action, you are going
to increase the chances of getting a contraction.
So the two are kind of in play here.
Okay, now that I've probably caused some tension here with
your salt tablet pickle juice habits, I think this might be a good point to take a break here.
I'll see you on Thursday.
Enjoy the rest of your nice, cool evening.