Okay.
Welcome back everyone.
Hope you had a good Wednesday.
We are going to finish up chapter 11, the acid-base balance during exercise.
And then if we have some time left over, we'll start the physiology of training.
But just a reminder that that will not be part of your second exam.
I just realized
I may not have posted those, but that's okay.
Okay, so we're gonna do a quick little review of where we ended off.
We talked about lines of defense against pH changes during exercise.
So if you remember, we had this kind of concept where at the muscles or the tissues
that are creating energy through cellular metabolism, we're producing
a lot of CO2 that quickly dissociates into carbonic acid and then bicarb and hydrogen ions.
So the production of hydrogen ions from lactate, CO2, and
ATP are all going to cause some imbalance in the pH, so a drop in that pH.
We typically don't like that to happen, so we have a few lines of defense.
We first talked about the first line of defense against the muscle pH changes.
And this first line of defense would be the cellular buffer systems.
So the cellular buffer systems include the bicarb, phosphates, proteins, and cardicene.
And we had touched on how carnosine is probably contributing
to the majority of the buffering of the hydrogen ions, so around 60%.
Whereas some of the other ones are still extremely
important, but maybe the magnitude of contribution for buffering the
pH changes in the muscle cell are not as high.
But of course,
These cellular buffer mechanisms aren't, or those four are
not 100% efficient for like extremely long periods of time.
And so eventually you're gonna get an over accumulation of
hydrogen ions inside of the muscle and we need to transport those out of the muscle.
We do those with two separate transporters.
We have a sodium hydrogen exchanger, NHE.
So you're going to bring a sodium in, and that allows for hydrogen to leave.
And then we have the monocarboxylate transporter, or the MCT transporter.
And this is a symporter.
So you're going to move lactate and hydrogen out at the exact same time.
So that's this piece here.
utilize these two transporters in order to decrease these hydrogen ions here.
And then that means we kind of see that spillover occur inside of the blood.
Okay, then we ended on that slide, and now we need to
move over to this other concept here, or the second line of defense against blood pH shifts.
So we'll start with this respiratory compensation for
metabolic acidosis and how that utilizes bicarbs, so the bicarb buffering system.
This one, hopefully, is not too bad because I've shown you this several times now.
But it's just this bicarb buffering system here.
In the muscle, we are producing a large amount of CO2
that's going to combine with water to make carbonic acid.
And then it'll dissociate into bicarb and hydrogen ions.
So it's going to encourage the movement of this system from left to right.
But if we are trying to get rid of all these molecules or decrease the pH,
Well, if I'm in a region where the CO2 is low,
the concentration of CO2 is low, then that's gonna push the curve from the right to the left.
Where do we typically see some pretty low partial pressures of CO2 in our body?
So what would encourage the reaction to move left?
So obviously, if you have too many hydrogen ions, we're going to push it towards the left.
But what would allow for the CO2 to start dropping?
Yeah.
So the alveoli, if we're bringing in inspiratory air in,
of 0.03% CO2, well, that partial pressure of CO2 is quite low.
And so we can exhale the CO2 out.
And that's going to help continue this curve to shift to the left.
And then CO2 is removed by the lungs, eliminating hydrogens and increasing the pH.
Any questions on this?
Okay.
I know it's kind of rough to just jump straight into it, but let's do it.
Okay, what do we think, maybe 30 more seconds?
Does anyone need more time than that?
Okay.
All right, 15 seconds.
We'll go five more seconds, double check you have an answer in.
Three, two, one.
Okay, yeah, we did pretty good here.
B is the correct answer.
So if I have elevated CO2 levels, that's going to push the equilibrium equation to the right.
So right away, we're looking at B, D, or E. That's going to cause the creation of more.
And if we're looking at these ones over here, it's possible
we can look at maybe D still, as well as E and B. So we're still actually OK.
I could argue that.
you would create more carbonic acid.
Although, in general, that quickly dissociates.
So maybe that wouldn't be the best answer.
So you're kind of on B and E, maybe D. And then blood pH.
So if I increase the acidity, whether it's carbonic acid
or hydrogen, that's going to cause the pH to decrease.
So we would want B over here.
So the correct answer is B.
Yeah.
Oh, yeah, yeah.
So I don't know if I'd give you this equation, but yeah,
you would always assume the CO2 is on the left and then the hydrogen bicarb on the right.
Yeah.
Yes.
Okay.
How about this one then?
All right, let's make sure we have something in.
Double check you have an answer.
I'll close this down in like 10 seconds or so.
Let me know if you need more time.
Okay, I'll close this down in three, two, one.
How do we do?
Not too bad.
Okay, so we kind of touched on it.
If you have a decrease in pH, then you are going to make the blood more acidic.
The humoral kind of response that we're looking at,
or those chemoreceptors, are going to detect those changes in pH.
and CO2 that's going to then send signals to the respiratory control center to do something.
Do we want an acidic environment for our body?
No, we don't.
And we can't really get rid of it inside of the blood.
So the best thing we can do is try to exhale those
CO2 molecules so we can drive the reaction to the left.
Good.
And so that's this piece here, right?
So we're gonna drive this down over here.
Any questions on this?
Very nice.
Okay, so if we're increasing ventilation to try to blow
off excess CO2 production or to try to counterbalance this decrease in pH,
We can kind of bring back this concept that you learned
in lab four, where we talk about the ventilatory threshold.
So this increase or this change in slope, right?
So if we have the red curve here as ventilation, so
we're looking at VE on the y-axis and then intensity and oxygen consumption on the x-axis.
We typically have a linear increase in ventilation, and then
after a certain point in time, we get an exponential increase
or a large change in the slope of ventilation.
This change in slope is caused by an increasing blood
PCO2, so a partial pressure of carbon dioxide, as well as the hydrogen ions.
We just talked about it.
We have that increase in acidity or that decrease in pH, so
we want to get rid of that, so we're going to increase ventilation.
The ventilatory threshold also increases in blood potassium
levels or rising temperature, which we kind of touched on last lecture.
Elevated blood catecholamines and possible neural influences may also control with this.
So we talked about kind of the neural and the humoral responses to ventilation.
So that's what this is talking about.
OK, so it says PCO2 and hydrogen.
I did leave something out, and that's lactate.
Do we think lactate concentrations or the production of
lactate or lactic acid then dissociates into lactate and hydrogen ions?
Do we feel like that is contributing to the lactate threshold here?
Maybe, maybe not.
So I'm going to say no, it doesn't.
What support?
do we have for that?
Does anyone remember?
So if we're looking at lactate or lactate concentration in individuals
who are exercising, what's one condition we talked about where
we can start to dissociate the two concepts?
Anyone remember what that's called?
Yep.
Yeah, so in this instance, we're not really going, it
is not related to cramping, but we're not trying to go that route.
I guess I'm trying to say this respiratory compensation or
the increase in slope is primarily due to partial pressure
CO2 and hydrogen ions, but I didn't mention lactate because sometimes, yeah, it is people with McCardles.
the ventilatory threshold still occurs in individuals who do not produce any lactate.
So if you look here, you've seen this before on these dotted or filled in circles,
we have McArdle's patients who are not producing
or changing any lactate concentration here, whereas the controls do
have an increase in lactate, but both McArdle's and
the controls have this ventilatory threshold.
So even though they have this respiratory compensation point,
they are not producing any lactate.
So we know the lactate threshold or the ventilatory
threshold is not being caused by the production of lactate.
Instead it is from the partial pressure of CO2 or the
production of CO2 molecules as well as a change in the pH or those hydrogen ion concentrations.
Are we okay with that?
And I think you remember the contribution for lactate as
far as hydrogen ions is quite small compared to the other ones.
Okay, so let's look at graded exercise in an untrained subject.
You've seen this curve before, but let's go through each and every single one of these.
Okay, arterial PO2, or the partial pressure of oxygen in the arteries.
This is maintained quite well between 10 to 12 millimeters
of mercury from the resting value here in untrained individuals.
So it stays relatively constant.
Arterial PCO2, or the partial pressure of carbon
dioxide, slightly decreases with maximal exercise.
So we see it kind of maintained here.
And then we see this decrease.
And that's due to this kind of change in slope, that ventilatory threshold.
We have that hyperventilation now.
We have these non-metabolically produced CO2 molecules.
We're trying to get rid of them.
And so we're getting a little bit of excess hyperventilation
to kind of drive this decrease in PCO2.
And then arterial pH, we get a decrease with maximal exercise.
We see pH here, pH is here, and then all of a sudden it starts to fall off.
And then we just touched on ventilation.
So there's a linear increase up to about 50 to 75%,
and then we get that exponential rise in ventilation.
So linear, linear, linear, and then all of a sudden it starts to curl upwards.
Okay, so then we have this other one here, venous PO2.
So the partial pressure of oxygen in the veins or the blood returning back to the heart.
Take a couple, like a minute or two, chat with your neighbors.
Why do we think venous partial pressure of oxygen decreases during graded exercise?
So as we start to increase intensity.
All right, go ahead.
OK, this one might be a little bit more straightforward.
What do we think here?
Why do we see the partial pressure of oxygen in the
blood returning back to the heart, the veins, decrease?
Any ideas?
Yeah, yeah.
So your muscles are consuming the oxygen, the
mitochondria in particular, or the electron transport chain, right?
Through that ATP synthase, you're combining oxygen with the hydrogen molecules.
You make some water.
Well, that oxygen's gone.
You no longer have that oxygen available.
And so the partial pressure drops inside of the muscles.
And that encourages the offloading of oxygen from the
hemoglobin to the myoglobin inside of the muscles.
Okay, good.
So that's why we see this decrease here.
And if you had the right units here, this value from
this value, so the arterial PO2 to the venous PO2, well that's just the AVO2 difference.
So we just know how much is being dropped off here.
Then you add in heart rate stroke volume, well that's the Fick equation.
Okay, so another couple,
maybe a minute or so, what about this?
Why does arterial pH decrease with maximal exercise?
Okay, what about this one?
This one's a little bit, it's not as straightforward, meaning
you have to bring in maybe another concept to try to help this.
I'm gonna see if I can get someone from this side.
What are we thinking?
Yeah?
Good, so I do like that.
Everything you said there was true.
When pH drops, you're shifting the hemoglobin dissociation curve to the right.
That's going to encourage the offloading of tissues.
And that might even help some of the partial pressure of O2, the venous O2, to drop.
That's encouraging the offloading of oxygen molecules so the muscles can consume more.
But that still doesn't really explain why this is decreasing.
So why is it that arterial pH through certain levels of exercise is maintained?
And then even we see an arterial PCO2 decline.
And oddly enough, right when that declines, we're seeing
like a pretty substantial decline or the started decline in pH.
When we just talked about this.
If there's an increase in those hydrogen ions, we're going to
try to shift the curve to the left, produce more CO2 to exhale it out.
Seems like maybe the PCO2 is going down, but then
that should mean the hydrogen ions should also go down.
Are you going to have a guess?
Yeah, so that is one limitation.
So the answer was like, we're kind of capped out.
We were saying, in general, this is like the untrained individuals.
Our ventilation is maxed out, and we can't really continue to blow off excess CO2.
So I would agree with that piece.
But then I would also say, if that were the
case, if that explained everything, the decline in partial pressure of CO2 would help
Increase pH.
So maybe we wouldn't see as drastic of a drop.
So it's in the bicarb buffering equation.
What does hydrogen have to bind to?
Any ideas?
Yeah, the bicarb.
So you have to have the hydrogen bind to the buffer and then drive the equation over to the left.
We do not have unlimited bicarb inside of our body.
If you start buffering these hydrogen ions, eventually you're not going to have
the ability to buffer some of these hydrogen ions.
And so you're basically seeing this drop in pH, even
though we have the encouraging drop in PCO2 to drive the equation towards the left.
And so yeah, two big things.
The major thing is we lose that buffering capacity.
And we can almost assume maybe there's some
mechanical limitation in these untrained individuals, where the lungs
might be not ventilating as much out.
So I like those two.
Okay, so then this last piece, this one's pretty straightforward.
I don't think we need to touch on it because one
of your classmates did kind of mention this, but why does arterial PCO2 decrease here?
Who wants to help me out with this one?
What's causing the decrease in PCO2?
It's definitely not the hydrogen ions.
The hydrogen ions are going up.
If anything, it's going to drive it over to the left, and we're going to have an increase in PCO2.
Why do we see this drop in PCO2?
Yeah, you're just exhaling more CO2.
You have that respiratory compensation point like both your classmates mentioned.
You have that hyperventilation, and so you're blowing off excess CO2.
Maybe it's not enough to really make a big difference in the arterial pH.
But again, we're seeing this drop here, drop here because we're losing the buffering capacity.
So you're all seniors, smart individuals, you're gonna soon become some entrepreneurs, right?
So if you're seeing this and you just heard this, what do you think might be the next step?
This is a problem in performance.
What do you think one could suggest?
Yeah, some type of buffer, right?
So then let me ask you, if that's what you're thinking about,
Could the ingestion of a buffer improve short-term high-intensity exercise performance?
Okay, let's go another 30 seconds or so on this one.
Okay, maybe 10 more seconds from now, unless anyone needs more time.
All right, we'll close it down in five.
Three, two, one.
So we're like 50-50 here.
So first, how do you think one can get ahold of BiCard?
It is readily available at your nearest grocery store.
Any ideas?
Yeah.
You can go and you can get some baking soda.
You probably shouldn't go that route.
But you can also do sodium citrate.
And I'm not recommending this at all because we'll talk about some downsides here.
But this would make sense, right?
If I could get more bicarb in my body, well, then
they're going to accept some of those hydrogen ions.
And then we can drive the equation this way.
And we can help blow off some excess CO2 to
decrease the acidity or change the acidity and decrease the number of hydrogen ions.
But then we saw about 50-50 here.
Does it improve performance, does it not?
So we need to be a little bit careful with this, right?
Some studies showed improvement in performance with ingestion of buffers.
They found that it can increase the time
to exhaustion during high-intensity exercise, and individuals appear
to maybe recover a little bit faster.
Whereas other studies show no improvement.
So I don't know if, well, we'll get to the no improvement here in a second,
but if we're looking at blood bicarb concentration here
and then blood hydrogen concentration, the control is in blue.
on this side and that side.
And then the bicarb concentration, it looks like they infused
it into the blood and it worked quite well, meaning the concentration of buffer or the bicarb did go up.
And it looks like it was able to decrease the
hydrogen ion concentration across exercise as well as recovery.
Now, maybe the 50%, 60% of you know, but like,
Why don't you think it might not work?
Has anyone tried this?
What do you think would happen if you ingested a decent amount of bicarb?
Has anyone done those little volcano experiments when you're younger?
So then when I say that, you're like, OK, maybe that's not a good idea.
So yes, they have different methods of trying to get it in.
But we need to be careful.
It can definitely cause some nausea and vomiting, especially with sodium bicarbonate.
Large doses are also problematic.
If you consume too much bicarb, because ideally, you would
be doing it before exercise, not as you're exercising.
So if you consume too much, that could change the
pH in the opposite direction while you're at rest.
And another consideration would be maybe it's banned.
So there was a period in time where a lot of athletes were actually consuming baking soda
or sodium citrate, and they were trying to get some of
this bicarbonate out of their body as a performance enhancement.
But it causes a lot of GI distress.
It's very uncomfortable, and we don't really know how much gets absorbed.
Because the previous study I showed you, they just infused it into the blood.
So that definitely has been shown to be quite effective.
But again, consult your sports regulation agency to see if you can use bicarb.
I know WADA, I think, it might be on that list.
OK, so that would be bicarb.
So we definitely know that has a buffering capacity.
Does anyone else know of a supplement that is
still relatively popular, especially amongst maybe resistance training
individuals that is usually added to maybe a pre-workout mix?
Yeah.
Creatine is one of them, and usually it is with
creatine, and so creatine's definitely gonna help with your immediate energy store.
Beta alanine, yeah.
Has anyone heard of this beta alanine?
Like sometimes people consume these beta alanine drinks, and
they get like a little tingly feeling, and they're like, oh man, I'm ready to go now, right?
So beta alanine is an important precursor to carnosine.
Wait, where have you heard carnosine?
Say again.
First line of defense, it's a chemical buffer that is really helping with muscular pH defense.
So beta alanine is going to help increase
the ability to create those carnosine buffers.
Well, that's nice, because carnosine buffers about 60% inside of the muscle.
So it's kind of the primary buffering substance that we have inside of our muscle.
And so they've done a lot of studies, not as much
recently, because as soon as this came out, this was on the craze.
So everyone was like beta-alanine human performance.
But it's a non-essential amino acid that's produced in the liver.
relatively low levels in the blood, but it is an important precursor to carnosine.
And supplementation and the research that kind of has been provided suggests
that there is an improvement in performance, especially
with the short duration high intensity exercise.
So obviously not that big of a deal for these
kind of longer duration submaximal exercise, because again, we're
not seeing these large disturbances in pH.
But ideally, maybe towards the end of an exercise.
But what hasn't been shown is after two hours, do
you still maintain the high levels of the cardicine after beta-alanine supplementation?
So really, the majority of the evidence is supporting
kind of the short term or short duration high intensity exercise with beta-alanine.
Okay.
Oh, man.
I gave this one away.
But I'm just going to have to put it on the exam now.
Which proposed mechanism would beta-alanine directly improve to potentially enhance performance?
Important word here is directly improves.
Where is beta-alanine directly impacting in the pieces that we've talked about so far?
Okay, we'll go five more seconds unless someone needs more time.
It's not as close as I thought it was gonna be.
I'll close this down here.
And three, two, one.
Okay, so the correct answer is D here.
So if you remember, the cellular buffer system has carnosine over here,
whereas the blood buffering, we're really kind of
relying on the respiratory compensation, bicarb, the phosphates and proteins over here.
OK.
So if we shown, yeah.
You could, but it's actually a little bit harder to consume those and manufacture them.
Yeah, yeah.
That's a good idea.
And you can, though.
This one is just a little bit easier.
All right, supplementation suggests that it does improve performance.
So if you're like, oh, man, I'm going to the gym, and
I'm going to have a great workout, how much do I need?
You don't need a whole lot, two to three grams per day.
It does improve the muscle's buffering capacity.
And it's really only going to be inside of that one to
four minutes, as far as kind of this high intensity exercise.
There's some evidence that suggests that if there
is a well-trained individual, typically we've already kind of
maximized the amount of carnosine that we can have inside of our muscles.
So it may not improve for well-trained individuals, but
there are some individuals who still improve who are kind of
on that elite, sub-elite category as far as the lower intensity.
Definitely, if you do decide to do it or you
are recommending it to anybody, they would probably want to try
it in training and then apply it before a race.
I would never try something brand new before an event.
But it seems like all you need is two to three grams
per day to get a pretty decent improvement in the buffering capacity of the muscles.
Yeah.
Well, a lot of times, it happens to be associate.
Like, the manufacturers put a lot of those things inside.
So then you're like, oh, man, it's going to work.
Yeah.
I mean, they sold a lot of stuff.
So it kind of, like, from a selling standpoint, it worked quite well.
All right.
So maybe you're like, no way.
Everything's too expensive.
Inflation, I don't want to spend money on beta alanine.
What else do you think?
could help before exercise.
One of those things might be one of the things we just talked about.
So could hyperventilation before short-term high-intensity exercise improve performance?
All right.
Just take about 15 more seconds, double check you have an answer in.
We're missing a handful of clickers.
I think we're missing two clickers.
All right, I'll close this down in three, two, one.
Okay, so 60-40 split, right?
Man, I've never, it's like right on 60-40, I like it.
60-40 split here, we're saying some people yes, some people no.
Well, from what we kind of talked about, maybe we
need to be careful about what kind of hyperventilation, right?
We don't want to just do increasing frequency, because
then we're just exchanging dead space, so maybe those kind of deep breaths in.
That will kind of decrease the CO2, and it's going to drive the reaction to the left.
And so it will.
At least from a blood standpoint, we're going to increase the partial pressure of oxygen.
But we don't really care about that too much
in this instance, because we're talking about short-term high-intensity exercise.
Plus, you're already at 100% saturation.
Not that big of a deal.
But here's where we're trying to see if it works.
And so yeah, hyperventilation does decrease the partial pressure of CO2.
So then in theory, if you decrease the partial pressure of CO2 in blood,
we would need to see then does that relate to performance?
And so there is a pretty interesting study done with repeated or interval exercises
and hyperventilation implemented during recovery intervals of
repeated sprinting did attenuate performance decrements, meaning
it improved performance in subsequent exercise bouts.
So that's pretty cool because
From a broad concept, yeah, that makes sense.
If I hyperventilate enough to drop my PCO2, that should
encourage the ability for my body to maybe defend against drops in pH for a little bit longer.
Or if I did have that drop in pH, well, maybe
I can increase the hyperventilation to try to get those hydrogen molecules to leave the body.
Now, this is the one where you definitely want to try
this in a safe space with some friends before implementing it, right?
If you start hyperventilating before start line, you got all
things going on, and you pass out, that's not on me.
that's on you, right?
So you definitely want to practice this if you're really like, oh, I'm going to do it.
And you'll kind of notice on some of the sprints, like the shorter distance sprints,
100 meter Olympics, you'll see some of the athletes kind
of doing this when they're down into the blocks.
But it is interesting to see that it potentially could help out with the buffering capacity.
And we'll touch on this once we get to thermoregulation.
But there's a very polarizing character who came up
with alternative breathing techniques to try to maybe implement this as well as some other things.
But has anyone heard of that individual, that breathing technique?
All right, we'll get to that in thermoreg.
But anyways.
Okay, so let's move on then because the lungs are great,
bicarb are great, but we need to know where this bicarb comes from.
So the regulation of acid-base balance via the kidneys.
So kidneys are extremely important, but they're more important in the long-term acid-base balance.
Not a really significant contribution during exercise.
So at rest, the kidneys can contribute to this
acid-base balance by regulating the bicarb concentration.
And this does, or the kidneys do this by regulating how much bicarb they excrete.
And this is where we get into the little bit of a problem where individuals,
if they consume some bicarb and they don't consume enough
of it, well, the kidneys are just gonna excrete it over a certain period of time.
But during exercise, if we're controlling bicarb excretion, why
is it during exercise we're not seeing a significant difference
or maybe a significant benefit with the kidneys and bicarb?
Yeah, yeah.
So the blood flow in the kidneys are already really low.
And so if it's trying to grab some bicarb in the first place or more, well,
there's very little even going through the kidneys in the first place.
So during exercise, usually the kidneys have very little regulation of our bicarb concentration.
It's more at rest when we have a little bit of a higher blood flow in the kidneys.
Good, good, good.
Okay, regulation of acid-base balance after exercise.
So you've kind of gone through this high intensity exercise.
You have all these hydrogen ions.
Your acidity is really high.
The pH is really low.
How can we try to return back to normal?
Well, we have some recent evidence that we have some lactic acid that's oxidized.
So in order to try to get it back to pyruvate, well, now lactate is a hydrogen acceptor.
You need to combine it with the hydrogen to get it
back to the pyruvate so then you can then convert it back to glucose.
So that's a decent amount, and we do that through the Cori cycle.
And then the majority of the other lactate molecules are then converted to amino acids.
So there is this recovery piece.
Yeah, you're going to continue to exhale some of those
carbon dioxide molecules as well as kind of move the hydrogens over.
But you also are going to reconvert some of the lactate molecules.
So even though it's a smaller amount, that's OK.
It's still contributing a little bit after exercise.
One thing to note though is following strenuous exercise,
lactic acid is removed more rapidly with light exercise during recovery.
So if someone went through this really intense high intensity exercise
and then they just rested, well blood lactate levels
are more elevated compared to light exercise and we're talking like 30, 35% VO2 max.
then we see a decrease in the lactate concentration.
What would be the problem of doing maybe a moderate to higher intensity exercise for recovery?
So why does it have to be this lower intensity exercise?
One, why does it work?
And two, why couldn't we do moderate to high intensity exercise?
Any ideas to that?
Yeah, if I just do high intensity exercise, I'm producing more lactate.
So that should not be the route to maybe clear some of this and anything.
Lactate just happens to be a marker that we can easily see.
Then number two, why would light exercise work then?
Yeah, you're increasing blood flow.
And if you increase blood flow at this light
intensity exercise, well, you're increasing blood flow to the liver.
And so you're able to maybe clear some things a
little bit faster at light intensity exercise versus no exercise.
And definitely better than high intensity exercise, because
now you're reducing blood flow to these important areas.
And then on top of that, you're producing more hydrogen ions.
So optimal intensity, where we're looking at maybe 30,
35% is going to potentially increase blood flow, which is also
good if you're trying to deal with maybe inflammation or other types of things to clear.
So then same deal.
It's like, well, if this concept is based on increasing blood flow to get it back to the heart,
What are some things that have been made available
for purchase that may help encourage this without exercise, or maybe during exercise?
Any ideas?
Maybe less common now, but maybe sort of happens a lot.
But has anyone heard of compression socks?
Yeah, so we don't have to answer this one, but compression wear improves recovery after exercise.
I'm not gonna run this clicker, so don't worry about that, but in theory, what do you think?
Who can help me out here?
Do you think this would work?
Recovery after exercise?
Maybe, yes, no, should I run the clicker instead?
So you're saying yes?
Or you're saying run the clicker?
Run the clicker?
OK.
Let me just see what we're thinking.
All right.
Can compression wear improve recovery after exercise?
Let's go like 15 more seconds here.
Double check you have something in.
All right, I'll close it down in three, two, one.
Yeah, most of you are saying yes, and I'd have to agree with you, right?
Like if the whole purpose is that if I'm standing up or
if I have blood pooling down inside of my leg muscles or
the leg, it could help me kind of redirect blood flow to the,
I don't know, to the central of your body and get it back to your heart.
Here's a review question.
By what mechanism are we working on this increase in end-diastolic volume?
the skeletal muscle pump, right?
You are literally just squeezing on the veins and encouraging blood to go back up.
So you're kind of working on that principle to get the blood back to the heart.
If you increase end-diastolic volume, you're gonna increase stroke
volume, and so then you're kind of increasing blood flow a little bit more passively.
And so that's why sometimes you'll see a lot of
compression wear, but if you look at this individual, this individual's running with compression wear.
So then the next question probably is, well, what about during running performance?
Well, if we think about that same principle that it's
kind of compressing on the veins, well, your muscles are doing a better job than the compression wear.
And so you can't close a vein more than you already are closing it.
And so we can see that control low, medium, and high compression has no bearing on performance.
And so it might be comfortable for the individual or
might make an individual feel better or whatever it happens to be.
But as far as a kind of improvement in performance,
it's not really doing anything for those individuals.
But as I mentioned, after performance, we are seeing a
little bit of a benefit because it's encouraging the blood flow to increase.
OK.
Compression wear, maybe that's not doing as good of a
job because it's just applying a certain amount of compression and that's it.
What do you think you could design or what have you
seen maybe out there that can maybe simulate muscular contractions even better?
Yeah, wait, say it again.
Yeah, yeastim actually would work.
Anything else?
I'm only looking at you because you probably have used it.
Yeah, compression boots or compression wear.
So has anyone heard of Normatec?
So they actually designed some of these where they
would begin compression down towards the feet and then slowly
compress to encourage the movement of blood flow from the bottom
of your feet all the way up back towards your heart.
And so it'll kind of
add that compression, then let it all go so you can
get it to refill, and then add the compression down and push the blood all the way up.
I think these are, this is kind of an outdated price, but
if you're like, yes, I'm going to go and get some, they are pretty expensive to get.
But sometimes you'll see it, like, they'll have, or they used to have booths after, like,
what do you call it, the Boulder Boulder, the 10K over here.
So they'll just have people and you can go and try them out and things like that.
But from principle, it actually works quite well.
But like all things, moderation is key.
Too much is also not good.
Any questions so far?
OK.
That then concludes all of the material up till the second exam.
So again, chapters eight through 11.
So from skeletal muscle all the way till what we talked about right now.
It's gonna be 30 around, it'll be 33 multiple choice questions because you did get one bonus.
Use the lecture notes, learning goals, and in class worksheets to study.
The worksheets are just the things that you fill out on the tables, that might help.
So you will not see these large equations or big calculations to do.
But you can imagine, even if it's a simple calculation, you might want to rely on a calculator.
That's why that's there.
And then just make sure you know your ID.
If there's a formula or a conversion needed, I'll give that to you.
Yeah, I'd give that to you, but you still need to, if
I tell you to calculate cardiac output and I give you a
heart rate and a stroke volume, you gotta type that in yourself.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Okay, well, I'm okay with calling it a day here.
Enjoy, we'll start on Tuesday, we'll start with physiology of training though.
Have a good one.