All right, welcome back everybody.
Good to see you again.
All right, so we're gonna pick up where we left off on circulatory responses to exercise.
We kind of just got done reviewing the pressure volume loop and maybe
how to read that and how the pressure volume
loop is impacting certain things like end-diastolic volume or
how certain factors are impacting how you might read the pressure volume loop like end-diastolic volume.
Maybe that mean arterial pressure or some of that inotropy like contractility.
So this is that figure that kind of summarizes some of the big pieces here.
So if we're gonna increase venous return, that's gonna impact diastolic volume.
If we kind of implement the sympathetic nervous system
activity or we get some epinephrine coming from the adrenal glands, that's gonna impact contractility.
Afterload can also impact stroke volume due to decreases or increases in arterial pressure.
But if we're talking about an increase in stroke volume,
that's a decrease in afterload is going to improve stroke volume.
So I think this is always a good little review slide to just check maybe
whether you remember some of the factors, because we talked about several factors
that impact end diastolic volume, several factors that
impact contractility, and then several factors that talk about arterial pressure or that afterload.
So preload, inotropy, afterload.
And we looked at each side, right?
Like, is it impacting end diastolic volume?
Is it impacting end systolic volume?
Is it impacting pressure?
And we looked at it in these three different kind
of individual ways, but in reality, regulation of stroke volume
during exercise is a little bit more dynamic.
Increasing that stroke volume during exercise is due to multiple different things,
as well as the impact of afterload is going to
maybe alter stroke volume or prevent stroke volume from maybe going up as much as we might expect.
We then looked at this particular overall, I guess, cardiac output formula here.
and then some of the impacts that maybe parasympathetic
nerves can inhibit cardiac rate or heart rate.
About up to what heart rate is a parasympathetic nervous
system and the withdrawal of that system impacting heart rate?
About where, as far as beats per minute, does anyone remember?
So if we're at rest, 60 beats per minute,
The primary way we can increase that heart rate
is through parasympathetic withdrawal up to a certain point.
Does anyone remember what that point was around?
You can take a guess.
Help me out here.
You can look at your notes or you can just take a guess.
That's okay, I don't wanna pressure anybody.
100, thank you.
Yeah, so up to 100.
That's typically primarily done through withdrawal, the
parasympathetic nervous system, and then kind of above 100.
And again, these are general areas, but above that,
now we're getting more sympathetic nervous system input that's
causing the increase in cardiac heart rate.
And then we talked about these three things here.
Did we end up doing this piece?
I think we left off right here.
OK, yeah.
So let's kind of get an idea of the stroke vong here for each of these conditions.
So the blue, A.
This smaller pressure volume loop here, the blue one that is labeled A, is indicating rest.
The kind of middle one here, B, is indicating low-intensity cycling.
And the largest one here, C, this red one here, is indicating high-intensity cycling.
So maybe a couple minutes, just try to get a
a decent estimate of the stroke volume for these three pressure volume loops.
And then we'll move on in just a second, or a couple minutes, a minute or two.
Okay, so hopefully you have a general idea of where these
stroke volumes are for each one of these conditions.
Keep in mind that we do have, before we kind of looked at cardiac output,
but we do have these typical values for heart rate,
cardiac output, and stroke volume given an individual whether they're
at rest or exercise or male or female and untrained, untrained.
So we're gonna take this a little bit further.
But given the following cardiac outputs, calculate the heart rate for each one of these.
So find the heart rate for curve A if the cardiac output
is 6 liters per minute, and then B, 10.5, and then C, 19 liters per minute.
OK, how are we doing here?
Anyone need a little more time?
I guess you don't need to be 100% done here to move on to the next piece.
OK, so we'll try some clicker questions.
If you're not done with the calculations, that's okay.
Don't worry, they don't necessarily have to be done, but they could potentially help you out here.
So let's try this first one here.
Which exercise curve shows an increase in stroke
volume primarily due to an increased contractility or inotropy?
Okay, let's try to get something in.
I'll close it down in maybe 20 seconds or so.
How are we doing?
Okay, 10 seconds here.
Double check you have something in.
Five seconds.
Three, two, one.
Okay, how did we do?
Oh, that's okay.
I like the enthusiasm.
I was hoping for that too actually.
Okay, so yes, the correct answer is C.
Who wants to help me out with this?
Because there's a lot of moving parts here.
So you have to kind of remember, one, what inotropy is, or increased contractility.
Two, what does that typically do to the pressure volume loop?
And then three, which one is primarily contributing to the increase in stroke volume here?
Any of those pieces, maybe, can someone help me out?
So increase in contractility is usually due to what?
Good, yeah, so typically if you increase contractility, you
do see some increase in pressure a little bit because you're increasing contractility,
but the biggest thing you want to look for is the fact that if I'm starting at rest,
which is this blue one for end systolic volume, and I
move down, then I have a decrease in end systolic volume, and
a decrease in end systolic volume is going to lead to an increase in stroke volume.
Here's the other piece.
What is the mechanism?
It is the sympathetic nervous system, but how does
the sympathetic nervous system increase this stroke volume?
What is it releasing?
Yeah, good, catecholamines, norepinephrine, epinephrine.
Those typically increase and they're at the highest during what type of intensity of exercise?
high-intensity exercise, right?
And so it kind of all checks out.
The primary kind of factor in increasing stroke volume is due to increased contractility.
If we go back to the mechanisms, well, sympathetic
nervous outflow onto those cardiac accelerator nerves is
epinephrine coming from those postsynaptic ganglions and the
adrenal medulla secreting some of the epinephrine, getting
it to be increased concentrations during high-intensity exercise.
OK, so what about this one here?
Which exercise curve shows an increase in stroke volume
primarily due to an increase in venous return?
I'm hoping we're going to do really well on this one, just by process of elimination.
Okay, do we have everyone's clicked in?
Anyone need a little more time?
I'm trying not to look here, because I'm excited, I'm excited.
We're gonna do well on this one.
Let's try like 10 more seconds here.
Okay, we're missing actually a handful of clickers,
I'll close it down, ooh, there we go.
In three, two, one.
That's okay, this is pretty good, nice job.
This is good, I'll take it, I'll take it.
All right, so curve B does show
an increase in stroke volume primarily due to an increase in venous return.
If we look at the original graph, which is rest, this A,
both B and C have an increase in stroke volume.
But we're trying to see which piece or which mechanism is primarily increasing the stroke volume.
I would agree that C
does have an increase in end diastolic volume, which
is contributing to the increase in stroke volume.
But the magnitude that the end systolic volume decreases
is greater at increasing the stroke volume.
So for C, like we talked about on the previous question,
it was primarily due to a decrease in end systolic volume.
So that's why C wouldn't necessarily be a good option here.
B, well, end systolic volume doesn't change at all for
B. The only thing that is increasing over here is the end diastolic volume.
If the end diastolic volume is the one that's
primarily responsible for the increase in stroke volume, that's the question in itself right here.
Any questions here on this one?
All right.
So let's think about this one for a couple minutes, or maybe just a minute, very quickly.
Mechanistically, we went from low intensity exercise and
diastolic volume increase because we increased preload for all the mechanisms that we talked about.
But look at that, we went from low intensity to high
intensity and we didn't see an increase in this end-diastolic volume.
We instead saw a decrease, so it pushed a little bit down.
Why do we think that's happening?
Let's maybe chat with your neighbors for a couple seconds
and then we'll try to come back together to think about some mechanisms.
OK, what are we thinking here?
That's a little odd.
Increasing end diastolic volume is going to increase systolic volume.
So we want to think that end diastolic volume would increase as we increase exercise intensity.
Did you have your hand up?
Yeah.
That's exactly right, that's exactly right.
So at higher intensity exercises, the heart is beating at
a much faster rate, which means there's less time for the ventricles to actually fill.
So in an ideal world, we'd want those ventricles to
fully fill, but if the heart's beating too fast, it's contracting
before we can get a full kind of volume or endostolic volume prior to the next cycle.
So that's why this is quite common to see this end
diastolic volume start to press down a little bit after you
start to get to the higher intensities during exercise.
OK, great job.
OK, so now we'll move on to changes in oxygen delivery to the muscles during exercise.
This should remind you, if I'm looking at oxygen in delivery,
Well, that brings in this nice little equation, the Fick equation.
This now ties in our concept of cardiac output, which we just covered.
So we now have gone through all of the Q. We're
going to start moving over to this AVO2 difference to get
this overall idea of oxygen delivery to the muscles.
Because essentially, that's all we are trying to do to
make sure we can survive or conduct some sort of mechanical work.
As we already have seen during lab, as well as some
of the other examples, oxygen demand by the muscles during exercise is quite a bit higher than rest.
So sometimes it can get 25 times greater than rest.
So that we already know.
We know we need more oxygen as we increase exercise intensity.
What we need to be thinking about now is, how does it do that?
So increased O2 delivery is accomplished by a few things.
No surprise if the Fick equation is Q times AVO2 difference.
Q, if that increases, well, that's going to increase the O2 delivery.
If we have an increase in cardiac output up to about 40% to 60% of VO2 max,
So if we go from rest to about 40 to 60% of
VO2 max, the increases in cardiac output are primarily due to
increases in heart rate as well as increases in stroke volume.
So both of these are contributing to the increase in cardiac output.
Anytime we get above this threshold, the increase in cardiac
output is primarily due to heart rate alone.
We'll talk about some exceptions, but after this
range, for most individuals, stroke volume plateaus, therefore, it's
primarily only due to an increase in heart rate.
So then what's kind of this idea of heart rate max?
Well, there are a few different equations we can use to predict heart rate max.
There's 220 minus your age, as well as 208 minus 70% of your age.
In lab, we're primarily going to use this one, but
just know that there are two different equations out there.
If I wanted to implement some predictions and heart rate max and see how
that might help me then determine maximum oxygen consumption,
I could predict someone's heart rate max, get a few
submaximal speeds here, extrapolate this because we know it's
relatively linear to their predicted max, and then drop this down to find the peak oxygen uptake.
So this is pretty nice because we can't always measure VO2 max.
So let me ask you this, in what instance would you
need to estimate VO2 max just using submaximal heart rate data?
Why do we think we would need to do that?
Because ideally, wouldn't we just wanna measure VO2 max?
Like I would agree with that.
But sometimes we can't do that.
Any ideas as to why we might want to estimate
as opposed to directly measure or indirectly measure VO2 max?
Maybe we need a few seconds.
Yeah, go ahead.
Yeah.
Yeah, I would not want to put my 90-year-old grandma on
a VO2 max test and try to trigger some type of cardiac
event just because we need to get an accurate measure of VO2 max.
There are a lot of health implications that would contraindicate a maximal exercise test.
In addition, you all have seen it.
We need some really expensive equipment.
You need people to be able to run it.
You need people to be well motivated to undergo it.
So if I wanted to know the VO2 max of everybody here on CU Boulder on the campus,
it would not be realistic to try to bring in 50, 60,000 people to do a VOT max test.
Instead, maybe they can get some submaximal heart rates on their own in the gym,
and then we send out a little survey to try to
get some submaximal points, and then we can estimate the VOT max.
So maybe like cost, logistics, health, right?
You can imagine a bunch of different things here.
Okay, so it is important that we can get an idea of how to estimate VOT max.
And now that I've shown you and maybe distracted you enough, let's try to answer this one here.
Assuming the athletes are the same age and weight, who would have a greater aerobic capacity here?
OK, let's take another minute, maybe less.
About 30 more seconds here.
It's a lot simpler than it looks.
15 seconds.
Double check you have something at least in.
Okay, close it down here in three, two, one.
Okay.
We weren't that close.
We did good though.
All right, so the answer is A. Why would this be A?
Can anyone help me out?
Aerobic capacity is kind of indicating what?
Or you can just tell me.
Yeah, that's exactly it, right?
So if someone has a greater aerobic capacity that's looking at VO2 max
or larger oxygen uptake, all you are really doing is
just drawing these lines or following these lines all the way up to their predicted max.
And then we drop down here, and their VO2 max is
about 2.9 liters per minute, and this one's 3.6 or so.
So athlete A would have the higher VO2 max or
the higher aerobic capacity or the higher oxygen uptake.
Okay, going back to changes in stroke volume during exercise,
or I guess we just finished kind of the idea of calculating or estimating heart rate.
Now we can look at changes in stroke volume and how that's gonna impact our cardiac output.
From about rest to, again, around that 40 to 60% range,
we get an increase in stroke volume, and then stroke volume starts to plateau in untrained subjects.
This is because of that decrease in filling time with
the higher kind of cardiac psych or beats per minute heart rate.
Like what we talked about before in the pressure volume
loop, we get a decrease in end diastolic volume and that leads
to a decrease or an overall plateau of that stroke volume.
Keep in mind though, it has been thought that kind
of this elite group, we're talking maybe like Olympic
development or Olympic type caliber athletes, it appears that
their stroke volume does not plateau or plateaus at a much higher percent of VO2 max.
And so this top line here is indicating the elite group
And as we increase in heart rate, stroke volume does not
appear to plateau at least at this point in time, but it
does start to level off a little bit down towards heart rate max.
But even in the trained group, we typically still see
a higher stroke volume than the untrained group, or at least
a higher point in time where the stroke volume plateaus.
And that's why we have that range where we say between
40 and 60% increases in cardiac output are primarily due to heart rate and stroke volume.
But then above the 40 and 60 is only heart rate.
That range kind of depends on the individual as well as their fitness.
Another piece that can impact stroke volume is body position or body position during exercise.
So here we have supine and upright exercise.
So supine's over here, so they're kind of laying down.
If they're laying down, we don't really have to worry
too much about getting that blood back up towards the
heart because it's already more filling towards the heart.
So you have that increase in central venous pressure.
So no surprise here, we have a higher stroke volume compared to an upright position
where we have to work a little bit harder to get all
the blood from the bottom of our legs back up towards the heart.
So you have a smaller or lower stroke volume here.
You've already seen this graph, so I'm gonna go ahead and skip this.
All right, number two, increased O2 delivery is also accomplished by redistribution of blood flow.
So we are taking some of that cardiac output from the inactive organs,
and when we say inactive, we're not saying like they
now shut off, it's just they're not primarily active or contributing
to the given work that we're trying to do.
So that's this redistribution of blood flow here.
So increased blood flow to the working skeletal muscles.
A lot of that blood is going to be redirected
from some of the organs that aren't necessarily being active in that given work.
So at rest, 15% to 20% of the cardiac output goes to
the muscles, but it increases to about 80% to 85% during maximal exercise.
So there's a substantial amount
a blood that's being redirected towards the muscles.
The majority of the redirection is because we're decreasing
the blood flow to the liver, the kidneys, the GI tract.
So we can see this is percent VO2 max here.
And spinic blood flow is basically kind of redirecting some
of the blood flow to these areas over here.
That decreases as we go to maximal exercise, but muscle blood flow increases.
So liver, kidneys, GI tract.
What other places have we talked about that start maybe changing the redistribution of blood flow?
Any ideas?
So is it always going to go to the muscle when we increase in exercise intensity?
Yeah, it definitely goes to other.
We definitely need some blood flow at the brain and the heart.
So those are good.
Anywhere else?
Yeah, the skin for thermoregulation.
So that's one.
Yeah, I like the idea there, but typically we redirect blood flow from that area.
It's a good thought, though.
The lungs, yeah, the respiratory tissues.
It actually takes a substantial amount of blood flow away from the working muscles to the lungs.
They even termed it respiratory steel.
So there was a lot of research coming out in like
the 90s out of Dempsey's group, and they looked at
respiratory muscle work compromising leg blood flow during maximal exercise.
They did a really cool study where they increased and decreased the work of breathing.
So down here on the x-axis, they have work of breathing.
100% is just normal.
So that's how much effort you would have to put in
to get your lungs to kind of inflate and deflate.
What they ended up doing is made it easier by using a proportional assist ventilator.
So it's just a ventilator they put on them, and it kind of forces air into the lungs.
So you really just, you don't have to put a lot of effort into getting more air into the lungs.
So you decrease the work of breathing, or decrease
the work that the respiratory muscles are doing.
Then they increased the work of breathing.
So they made it substantially harder to breathe or move air in.
If you were to take a guess, what's the easiest way do
you think you can get someone to make it really, really hard to breathe?
Any ideas?
Like a mask?
Yeah, a mask would be good.
But even more, like a mask would make it harder to breathe.
But what's the way we can do it really hard?
Lower oxygen is a good idea, but that actually
decreases partial pressure as opposed to putting more effort on the respiratory muscles.
They essentially had them breathe through a straw.
They had them do maximal exercise and have them breathe through a straw.
So they're really, really working hard.
So once they increased the work of breathing, made it really, really difficult, they saw
that the cue to the legs or the cardiac output to
the legs started to decrease with an increase in work of breathing.
But it increased.
due to a decrease in work of breathing.
Well, then someone could say, well,
You're just redirecting blood flow, maybe more blood flow to
the muscles, less blood flow to the muscles.
How do we know that's actually increasing or decreasing oxygen uptake?
Well, they looked at that, too.
So VO2 in the legs, they ran arterial lines all the way down to the muscles to exercise.
So they had one in the arteries and then one in the vein.
And they just looked at the oxygen before it reached the muscle bed and then afterwards.
And then you have a VO2 difference there.
It's a really cool study.
So they looked at the VO2 at the legs directly.
And indeed, with a lower work of breathing, it increased the VO2 at the legs.
And an increase in work of breathing decreased the oxygen consumption at the legs.
So this was a really, really good study here.
They then, not this group, but another group, actually looked and saw the blood flow,
the cardiac output to the respiratory muscles as well
as oxygen consumption at the respiratory muscles.
And they confirmed that side of it too, but that happened maybe 15 years later,
just because it was a little bit harder to get blood
flow as well as oxygen consumption at the respiratory muscles.
Because at first, they're like, oh, yeah, well, you're taking
it away from the legs and bringing it to the legs.
But we don't know where it's going.
Well, now we know it's going to the respiratory muscles.
And you all have probably experienced this.
If you have exercise at a higher intensity, sometimes
you can feel, like maybe the respiratory muscles or your lungs,
as sometimes people call it, start to get a little tired.
Or you can tell that they're working a little bit harder at those higher intensity exercises.
The other thing to keep in mind though is when we have some type of redistribution of blood flow,
even though we're going from maybe, I don't know, 15% in
the brain to three to 4%, it's not necessarily saying that you're getting less blood flow to the brain.
It's just a fraction of the overall cardiac output of five liters per minute.
So yeah, it's a lower percent, but you're taking a
lower percent of a higher cardiac output and actually gets pretty close to what it was at rest.
Again, that's because we don't want to eliminate blood flow
to the brain or eliminate blood flow to the digestive tract.
It's just we would rather send more of it to other areas.
And if we have a higher cardiac output, well, sometimes
that can kind of account for the decrease in relative distribution of blood flow.
That's where this diagram comes into play.
I'll have you fill this out on your own time here
so you can calculate the absolute blood flow at rest and then the average blood flow during exercise.
And then you can compare it to rest.
So we know kind of what happens on a relative basis, but
now it would be good to use these values here, so 25 liters per minute.
Just multiply the fractions here by that.
Put that one in the second row.
And then you could do the same thing for rest,
five liters per minute, and then multiply these across.
You'll see you actually get a decent amount of blood
flow in some of these smaller areas, but nowhere near what we would have kind of in different situations.
The magnitude of these redistributions do depend on metabolic rate.
If I'm exercising at a higher intensity and the
muscles are demanding an increase in oxygen consumption or
energy production, well, the magnitude of these redistributions are gonna get bigger.
So here we have exercise intensity and then cardiac output over here.
So this one right here in the center, this kind of
orangish color here, this is blood flow or cardiac output to the muscles.
That is now increasing.
as we go from rest to high intensity exercise.
The kidneys are taking a substantial decrease as we go from rest to exercise.
And you can kind of look at the remaining here, but this is kind of nice.
This is an absolute.
So this is cardiac output liters per minute.
The kidneys are decreasing, but not as much as what we would expect from this piece here.
Okay.
So then the next question should be, look at all
of this blood being redirected to the muscles required for locomotion.
So I'm starting to work out or run.
I'm activating these muscles.
But what is actually telling the body to send more blood to those muscles?
The heart does not determine where the blood goes.
The heart just pumps blood and more blood comes out, right?
There has to be some type of signal in the muscles to say,
or the body to say, hey, I want to send the blood to a certain area.
This is where we get into this concept here.
So the regulation or even the redistribution of muscle
blood flow during exercise is primarily mediated by local factors.
So it's not that you're trying to say I want to send blood to the muscles.
It's some type of auto-regulation at the muscles themselves.
So there's intrinsic control of blood flow by increasing
local metabolites that lead to a vasodilation in that area.
If you have a vasodilation inside of the kind of blood
vessels at the muscle, you all of a sudden get a change in pressure.
you get a large decrease in pressure in that area and
all of a sudden by default from what we learned about on
the change of pressure and blood flow, blood flow will be redirected to that area.
As soon as you get a huge drop in pressure at
the muscles, well then the body has to compensate and say, whoa, that was kind of extreme over here.
Everything else kind of vasoconstricts to maintain perfusion pressure to the rest of the body.
Are we okay with that concept?
If all of a sudden all these blood vessels here vasodilate,
that would cause a little bit of a problem.
And I think we may have experienced this every now and
then, where if you're laying down, you get up too fast and all the blood rushes down.
I think we talked about that, that if you didn't try
to maintain perfusion pressure to the rest of the place, that would be a problem.
And so naturally everything else starts to vasoconstrict.
It's a local factor, local factors that are contributing
to promote vasodilation to increase blood flow to the working muscles.
There are other theories that kind of contribute to this, just like the muscle pump theory, right?
Like if you just contract that blood vessel and
let go, then that's automatically going to encourage blood to go there.
But I guess the primary factor would be any of these local metabolites here.
You don't need to memorize any of these local metabolites
in these parentheses, but in the past I've got the question of what are those?
So I just put them in here as an example.
The one thing, you don't need to know this, but the
one thing that I don't really like, how the textbook and a lot of figures depict how the
blood vessels are open or closed.
Here during rest at this muscle capillary bed, it's
almost assuming that there's no blood flow here.
So we actually know now that there is blood flow to
these areas, but there's just a very small amount of blood
flow, plus the hematocrit goes way, way, way down.
So it's mostly like plasma and maybe a few red blood cells that are going through here.
So there is flow going through all of these muscular beds here.
And they just vasodilate, and then we redirect blood flow during high-intensity exercise.
So nothing's really closed or absent of blood flow.
There's just a very, very small amount.
Any questions on this?
Nice.
So that was Q, cardiac output.
Let's move on to the AVO2 difference here.
A higher arterial venous difference or the AVO2 difference.
is due to, or if we're going to define it first, it's
just the amount of oxygen that is taken up from 100 milliliters of blood.
So this A represents the arterial side, the V represents
the venous side, and it's saying the O2 content in the arteries and the O2 content in the veins.
If we have exercise intensity here on the x-axis and the AVO2 difference here on the y-axis,
we see that as we go from rest to maximum exercise,
there is a slight increase or a continual increase in the AVO2 difference.
No surprise, right?
We want to deliver more oxygen to the muscles.
The muscles take up more oxygen, so we can use it for oxidative phosphorylation.
This is a nice little figure here, but I think the next one does a little bit of a better job.
So in general, if I have A and B over here, this
is a muscle at rest, and this one's a muscle during intense aerobic exercise.
The amount of blood
In these two given scenarios, if they're just equal, we're not changing training
or blood doping or something like that, the amount of
blood being delivered to the muscles is constant.
If I have 100% SPO2 or 100% arterial oxygen saturation,
well, the amount of blood that's being carried is always going to be constant or the same.
It passes through the capillary, goes to the vein, but over here, you can imagine,
or you can draw like a little muscle here, the oxygen
is gonna diffuse from the capillary to the muscle.
Whatever is left over, so we went from 20 mils to 15
to 16 mils of oxygen per 100 milliliters of blood.
Well, that is the AVO2 difference.
So we are just taking the difference here.
So this is the amount of arterial oxygen content or the amount of oxygen in the arteries.
This is the amount of oxygen in the veins.
This right here is the AVO2 difference, which is depicted similarly over here.
Once we start to increase exercise intensity, well, the
amount of oxygen per 100 milliliters of blood is the same,
just what we talked about before because of SBO2.
But now there's a greater demand at the muscle.
We're working harder, so we need to uptake more oxygen.
So now instead of a delta of four to five and the veins
have 15 to 16, we have a delta of 15 and we leave over like five milliliters of blood.
The venous content decreases.
The arterial content remains relatively steady.
This is not at zero.
Is that saying that our muscles don't take everything up?
It's kind of implied in the term here.
But why do we think this is not at zero?
So it's called mixed venous content.
In this particular study, they grabbed the venous O2 content in the vena cava, next to the heart.
So why wouldn't that be at zero?
Why aren't we at zero?
So typically, the muscles take almost everything.
It wouldn't make sense that we leave some oxygen here,
especially if we can consume all of the oxygen.
Why are we not at zero with the mixed venous content?
Any ideas?
Are the muscles the only place consuming oxygen?
No.
We have inactive areas, so like my arms, they're closer to this top one.
So they have a higher venous O2 content, and then you mix them in the heart
so some of the inactive areas aren't consuming all of the
oxygen, and you get a little bit of an elevation here.
So this isn't necessarily saying that the muscle is
leaving five milliliters of O2 per 100 milliliters of blood.
It's possible it does.
But since we're sampling it in kind of the
heart, where everything's bringing the venous O2 content from
all of the other areas, that doesn't necessarily mean that it is or isn't at zero at the muscle here.
Okay, circulatory responses to exercise here.
Elevated heart rate and blood pressure in emotionally charged environment.
This can happen to an increase in sympathetic nervous system activity.
This can increase pre-exercise heart rate and blood pressure.
But no surprise, it does not increase peak heart rate or blood pressure during exercise.
And we kind of saw that with that Murdoch study in
your lab where they put an artificial pacemaker and increased heart rate.
doesn't really do a whole lot there.
So it doesn't matter how amped up you are or how
much Rocky the Three soundtrack I had the tiger you're listening
to, you're not going to be able to increase your maximum heart rate.
But it definitely would put, well, not definitely, but if you
enjoy this type of music to get you kind of hyped up, that would increase your pre-exercise heart rate.
So we know there's this influence of kind of that
sympathetic outflow to be able to increase your heart rate.
This transition topic, we've already discussed this, but is the rapid increase in heart rate
and stroke volume as well as cardiac output, so cardiac output increases, stroke volume increases,
and heart rate increases, until we can finally match
the steady state value to ensure we're getting the adequate amount of oxygen delivery to the muscles.
Kind of the same story, but we're just adding another variable here, blood pressure.
So cardiac output increases, and then there's a change here in slope.
Why do we have a change in slope right here?
So cardiac output over intensity, we're increasing to about
40%, and then there's a change in slope.
Yeah, the stroke volume's plateauing off, so now we get a
little bit of a decrease in the slope, but we still
increase in cardiac output because it's primarily due to an increase in heart rate.
Heart rate's pretty linear.
Blood pressure's pretty linear as well.
Mean arterial pressure is also linear, but just at a
lower intercept, so it's kind of pushed down a little bit.
Diastolic blood pressure, we expect it to remain pretty steady.
If anything, it might have a slight decrease.
Increase in diastolic blood pressure would be a little bit of a problem.
That's a contraindication.
OK, what about these responses to arm and leg exercise at the same oxygen uptake?
Arm work results in higher blood pressure as well as a higher heart rate.
The blood pressure is because you get some vasoconstriction
in the areas that you aren't sending the blood to.
So kind of reverse of what we talked to with the leg exercise.
If I start doing arm exercises or I'm on an
arm crank ergometer, you're gonna vasodilate the blood vessels
to supply those arm muscles and then vasoconstrict in the other areas like your legs.
So blood pressure would increase at the same oxygen
uptake compared to leg exercises, and same with heart rate.
And this should make sense, right?
If you tried to send all of the blood to the arm muscles compared to the leg muscles,
well, by default, you're sending a lot of blood to
a smaller region, and that's going to increase blood pressure.
Okay, what about intermittent exercise?
You've probably noticed this, but recovery of heart rate and
blood pressure does depend on a few things.
If an individual's a little bit more fit after exercise,
we start to recover a little bit faster, your heart rate decreases a little bit faster.
Temperature and humidity, well, that's just kind of a byproduct of intensity.
And then duration and intensity of the exercise.
So here in blue, we have kind of an increase in watts.
So these are like intermittent or interval exercises, and
then it decreases and then increases, decreases, increases, decreases.
That's this blue line here.
So the power output is the same at all of the intervals and the rest.
But this green little line here, we get an increase in heart rate, as expected.
But during the rest, it's not enough time for our heart rate to fully recover.
And then we go to the next bout, and then our
heart rate starts to increase a little bit, and sometimes it even increases higher than the previous one.
And you get this little step increase with heart
rate with intermittent exercise, or increases in intervals.
You also can imagine that if I'm increasing the intensity
here, epinephrine is kind of coming out into the bloodstream.
It's really hard to kind of get rid of that, so no surprise.
This kind of matches with the increased epinephrine concentration
and the inability to kind of remove that from the system.
Okay, what about prolonged exercise, right, for increasing duration?
No surprise if I need to supply the muscles with
a certain amount of oxygen, cardiac output stays steady as we increase in exercise time.
In this example down on the X axis, we have 90 minutes.
So cardiac output is pretty steady.
Stroke volume decreases and heart rate starts to increase.
A lot of this is influenced by some sort of thermoregulatory behavior.
If I'm starting to warm up due to the exercise, eventually
the body's going to try to get rid of that heat.
It needs to send blood flow to other areas, which means the stroke volume is going to decrease.
And we compensate by increasing this heart rate.
This is the cardiac drift.
So that's this piece here.
Yeah.
Well, so the amount of heat that's being generated from the
heart in itself is going to be pretty minor.
But yeah, it would increase more heat.
And you also have to think about things like if
I'm redistributing blood flow from the leg muscles to the
skin, well, that's less oxygen that we're delivering to the muscles.
It's possible then we're going to get a different type
of recruitment and recruit some of those less efficient type 2 fibers.
And so overall, it's kind of a tough process where the
body starts to work a little bit harder, generate more heat.
to lose the heat.
So it becomes a little bit problematic, but we'll talk
more about that when we get to thermal regulation.
OK, so this cardiovascular drift here, like what we saw before, heart rate starts to go up.
We kind of maintain this cardiac output.
There is a little bit of a decrease to
blood volume, and that's because we're expecting individuals to start to sweat.
And then mean arterial pressure goes down as well as stroke volume.
So then how do we think we can prevent cardiovascular drift during prolonged exercise?
Any ideas here?
So if the main reason that we just talked about, if this is some given distance
and we are maintaining our pace, but our heart rate does
not just stop at the given heart rate that we would expect
for the pace and it starts to increase, we get this cardiovascular drift.
Any ideas how we can try to prevent it?
And it's in quotes because it might not be ideal.
Yeah, try to maintain some hydration or some other aspects to try to improve thermal regulation.
A lot of this cardiovascular drift is due to the
fact that you're trying to maintain perfusion pressure due to
the redistribution of blood flow to the periphery.
Another thing you obviously could do is just slow down.
We don't really want to do that if we're trying to compete.
But if you're out going for a nice little run and you start to see that drift,
well, yeah, if you're trying to reach a certain distance,
it might benefit you from kind of slowing down a little bit.
OK, so during recovery, after you're done exercising, so that's this dotted line here.
No surprise, we see this decrease in heart rate,
stroke volume, and cardiac output going back towards the rest.
Again, how long that takes does depend on a few things,
like intensity of the exercise as well as training state.
We also talked about this recovery piece here as far as oxygen consumption.
So if you remember, that's called EPOC.
So heart rate, stroke volume, cardiac output is one piece of that EPOC.
Okay, so regulations of cardiovascular adjustments to exercise, we
can kind of take big picture here, right?
So exercise requires some sort of ATP.
If you wanted to review that, then we could just be like, well, how do we store ATP?
Well, we have the ready-made ATP, creatine phosphate, we store
it in the form of carbohydrates and fats.
Then sustained exercise,
primarily uses which one of those?
We can kind of think about that.
And then what do we need in order to use those energy stores?
Well, we need oxygen.
So then your next question is, well, how do I get oxygen into the body?
And then how do I get it delivered to the muscles?
And you can start going through all those mechanisms.
I think this is a pretty good summary of the responses to exercise where
if I'm trying to deliver more blood to the muscles, there
are a lot of different factors that are going to get there.
I would be careful with this arrow here, right?
Yes, an increase in cardiac output in most situations
leads to a direct increase in skeletal muscle blood flow.
but not at all exercise intensities and durations, because hopefully
I've shown to you that I can redirect blood flow
due to thermoregulation or even an increase in respiratory rate.
The other pieces down here kind of really help with some
of the, I guess, aspects of control of that cardiac output or the blood flow to the muscles.
Are we good there?
OK.
So that finishes up this for the cardiovascular piece.
Hm.
I do have this set for Thursday, so I think we can stop here.
Keep in mind, I am a little behind on emails.
Some of you may have noticed.
So just give me some time and I'll eventually get to those emails.
So thanks for being patient with those.
Have a great rest of your day.