OK, welcome back.
Very briefly, before we get started, this Monday, March
3, I'm hosting a colloquium speaker that typically happens every Monday for this semester at 11.15.
But the speaker that I'm hosting on Monday, so Dr. Hokehammer, he
Did a post-doc here at CU, and we did some of
the original research together on those Nike, the first Nike
performance shoes, so those vapor flies that I think we had touched on.
So he's gonna be coming to give a talk on
the latest research on performance running shoes, and thought you might be interested.
No worries if you're not, but if you are, Humanities 250, Monday, March 3rd at 11.15 a.m.
That should be a pretty interesting talk.
All right.
So we're gonna pick up where we left off on Tuesday, circulatory responses to exercise.
So we're on that chapter nine.
We touched on, or I guess the last few slides that
we looked at were regarding kind of this idea of the Wiggers diagram.
It gives us a really good idea of how pressure changes
in the heart lead to blood kind of leaving or filling inside of the ventricles.
The Wiggers diagram is something that you all have seen before in physiology.
I had mentioned that we are no longer, or at least
for exercise physiology, we're not going to be really worried about the Wiggers diagram.
But since you know the Wiggers diagram a little bit
better, it's nice to kind of reference the Wiggers diagram to get to the ventricle pressure-volume loop.
So we're now going to be using the pressure-volume loop.
As a reminder, we're going
kind of up and then left down to the right.
So this is the direction of the pressure volume loop.
Let's start off with trying to fill in some of these pieces here.
So we first talked about how if the mitral valve closes
here and we have an increase in this pressure, well, the
pressure is increasing with no change in volume here.
And then when the aortic valve opens, you still get a little bit of an increase in pressure,
but if you have that aortic valve opening, you get a
decrease in the amount of blood inside the ventricle because it's leaving the ventricle now.
And then during relaxation, the pressure drops, but you don't
get any movement in blood or blood volume doesn't change.
And then the mitral valve opens again.
Left ventricle volume goes up because it's passive and actively
filling up with blood for the next cardiac cycle.
So what I would like you to do now is to fill
in the appropriate boxes on the pressure volume loop using what you know from the Wiger's diagram.
So keep in mind, on the x-axis, you have the left ventricular volume.
On the y-axis, you have left ventricular pressure.
So let's take some time to label those.
I'll walk around if you have any questions, and then we'll come back in a couple minutes.
OK, not too bad, right?
Let's try this out then.
Using the two diagrams, match the letters A through D
with the appropriate event in the left ventricle.
You pretty much have already done that, but let's put that in an order here.
Okay.
Yeah, just to make sure, these A, B, C, D are A, B, C, D, if that helps.
Okay, how are we doing here?
Anyone need a little more time?
I guess I do see people pointing, so that's good.
Let's go maybe another minute.
Okay, let's get something in.
Double check you have an answer.
We'll close it down in 10 seconds.
Okay, three, two, one.
Okay, how do we do?
I think we're a little bit between
D and C, this is the correct answer.
I won't grade that one.
OK, so let's take a look at this.
D is correct.
If you had went with C, more than likely you're going
the wrong way with some of these pieces here.
OK, so if we want to find isovolumetric contraction,
We actually want to be on this side.
So we know it's contraction for a couple reasons.
One,
you typically have contraction once the left ventricle is at its highest volume.
Because when we contract, we want to move the blood out of the heart.
So we have isovolumetric contraction.
And even if you forgot what isovolumetric was, you
would say the ventricles are contracting with no corresponding volume change.
So if you look here, I have an increase in pressure
But the volume down here on the x-axis is not changing.
That's why it's isovolumetric contraction.
The pressure is going up.
Then eventually, the pressure inside the ventricle overcomes the
pressure on the aortic valve, and the aortic valve opens.
As soon as that aortic valve opens, blood moves outside of
the ventricle and into the aorta to go to the rest of the body.
We know this from the pressure volume loop because the
volume is decreasing in the left ventricle, so it's going to the left over here, or to your right.
No, your left, sorry.
So it's going this way over here.
Then,
You can't maintain the contraction forever, so the heart relaxes.
As soon as it relaxes, that valve closes down, the aortic valve, right?
No blood can go back into the ventricle.
So the pressure's decreasing, but there's no change in volume.
So you'd get your isovolumetric relaxation.
And then you get the filling.
Right?
You're going from a lower volume to a higher volume here.
And then you start the cycle again.
Any questions on this one?
Yeah?
Yeah, so B would be right here, so it would be isovolumetric contraction for B.
And then isovolumetric relaxation would be D, which is down this way.
So I'd put D in the second line right here.
And then A, ventricle filling, would be right here.
This is A. And this represents the ventricle's filling.
We OK?
OK.
Any other questions on this one?
So it's a relatively straightforward kind of figure, but please
make sure you spend some time on this one to understand what's going on at each point.
Okay, cardiac output would be the next concept here.
Cardiac output you are already familiar with.
It's the amount of blood pumped by the heart each minute.
If I want to know the amount or the liters of blood
per minute, then there are two things that you really need to have in play here to get cardiac output.
Number one would be heart rate because that gives you the number of beats per minute.
And then stroke volume.
which is basically how much blood is leaving per beat.
Cardiac output does depend on training state as well as sex.
What does that look like?
Well, if we are looking at untrained male and females, the cardiac outputs are different.
So men tend to have higher cardiac outputs than women.
And trained individuals tend to have higher cardiac output than untrained individuals.
We also see differences between rest and max.
So we'll have the highest cardiac output during maximal exercise and the lowest during rest.
So a few things going on right here.
We're comparing sex, differences in sex.
We're also comparing differences in training status.
And then this table's also comparing differences between rest and maximal exercise.
Okay.
Using kind of the idea of this table here,
we can get some good information or we can pair this with the pressure volume loop.
Let's try this out.
A pressure volume loop is created for an untrained individual.
This untrained individual is female and about 50
kilograms at rest and during different intensities.
Let's
see which one of these pressure volume loops have been created.
So you're trying to see when this pressure volume loop
was created during these three or none of these intensities.
So make sure to reference the table before.
That's gonna help you out.
Okay, double check you have something clicked in.
We'll close it down in 15 seconds here.
Five seconds.
Three, two, one.
Okay, how did we do?
B's the correct answer, but that's not great.
Let's kind of break this down.
First, we need to determine for this particular athlete here,
what is their stroke volume, or a round.
75 to 80, right?
So you're at 125.
You're at 50 here.
So that's at least 75.
It's a little bit below.
OK, 75 to 80.
Then we need to reference what a untrained female who's around 50 kilograms.
Well, would you look at that.
We have female who's around 50 kilograms.
We have untrained at rest.
their stroke volume's at 60.
At maximal exercise, it's 90.
So they're definitely not at rest, because they're working harder than being at rest.
And they're definitely not at max yet.
They're actually pretty close to in between.
So in this instance, it would be submaximal exercise.
Any questions?
Because then now that we know what cardiac output is,
well, you've kind of known that already, let's break
down the factors that actually regulate cardiac output.
We need to go kind of step by step here.
We're going to work our way first to the activity of the parasympathetic and sympathetic system.
And then we're going to break down stroke volume and heart rate.
One of the two kind of mechanisms to regulate heart
rate would be the parasympathetic and the sympathetic system.
If we increase the activity of the sympathetic nervous system
to the heart, we are gonna increase heart rate.
You also have a parasympathetic withdrawal.
So you are inhibiting the SA node less, and that's gonna help speed up heart rate.
So you have those two major factors that are contributing
to an increase in cardiac output, but primarily heart rate.
Okay, so if we're at the autonomic nervous system,
we talked about the somatic motor pathway before when we were dealing with skeletal muscle.
Now we're kind of moving over to this parasympathetic as well as the sympathetic pathway.
You don't need to memorize these, but it is sometimes
nice to know that the preganglionic fibers for
both parasympathetic and sympathetic are releasing acetylcholine on the post synapse.
Then on the post...
ganglionic fibers here.
Acetylcholine is the neurotransmitter that's being released to
the target tissue in the parasympathetic, whereas the sympathetic is using norepinephrine.
The reason why I point this out is because we
also have circulating epinephrine in the blood from the adrenal medulla.
So we have these organs here releasing epinephrine into the blood.
They also can bind to these receptors to cause changes in heart rate and contractility.
So now I would never
tests you on the ganglia and the neurotransmitters.
But if you understand those two pieces, it might help
you with some of the other mechanisms later on.
Okay, so primarily for the parasympathetic vagus nerve,
those are typically only kind of interfacing with or binding
or sending their neurotransmitter to the SA and AV node.
So they're really just kind of controlling the pace of
the heart by influencing the AV and SA node.
The sympathetic nervous system.
does the same thing, AV NSA node, but it also has connections to the myocardium.
So to the actual heart tissue, the muscles, the actual muscles.
We sometimes call these sympathetic pathways cardiac accelerator nerves.
And we'll touch on this again a little bit later.
Okay, so regulation of heart rate.
This is the how, right?
So why does heart rate increase?
Well, heart rate increases because we have to deliver more blood to the tissues.
How is heart rate increasing?
We have two major pieces like we touched on.
Parasympathetic nervous system has some sort of withdrawal.
This is via the vagus nerve, which we just looked at on that previous figure.
If you have the parasympathetic nervous system releasing
that acetylcholine, it's gonna slow the heart rate by inhibiting the SA and AV node.
So if you withdraw this activity, it's gonna help increase heart rate.
OK, like I talked about, we have acetylcholine binding to these muscarinic cholinergic receptors.
They cause these G-protein conformational changes.
They're going to allow for potassium to leave, which is going to cause a hyperpolarization.
It's also going to block calcium from coming in.
If you have a hyperpolarization and you have positive ions leaving, it's going to reduce.
It's going to make it more negative.
And you block positive ions from entering.
So that's the hyperpolarization here.
This is also considered the autorhythmic cell.
This is really helping us get our resting heart rate, right?
It's just, you have that consistent heartbeat at rest.
Okay, number two, sympathetic nervous system.
These are via the cardiac accelerator nerves.
Those are the ones binding directly to the myocardium.
And we can increase by stimulating the SA and AV node.
So if you remember acetylcholine from the parasympathetic
nervous system, epinephrine for the sympathetic.
So we have epinephrine or norepinephrine binding to these
beta receptors here, cause some G protein conformational change, secondary messenger.
Then you open these two channels that are gonna allow
for sodium and calcium to rush into the cell.
That's gonna make the membrane potential get more positive
and increase the chance you're gonna get an action potential.
We call that depolarization when we're making the membrane potential more positive.
So we talked about depolarization, hyperpolarization.
This is another figure that helps with some of this.
So the parasympathetic nervous system is going to make it more negative, hyperpolarize it.
And so it's going to be a little bit harder to get to this point here.
And so that's the membrane potential threshold.
So any time the membrane reaches this millivolt, then it will generate an action potential.
It'll slowly creep up and then generate the action potential.
So if we hyperpolarize the cell, it's going to take
a little bit longer before we reach that membrane potential to induce the action potential.
So we're gonna skip this one here, but we'll move on to regulation of heart rate.
So we know that we can, if from rest to maximal
exercise, we usually see a pretty linear increase in heart rate, but it's never just like, oh,
We don't really see the mechanisms behind it, but we
can start to separate where the influence of the
parasympathetic and the sympathetic nervous system are contributing.
So the initial increase is due to parasympathetic withdrawal.
So around the first 40% of intensity, this is on average,
that increase in heart rate, so when we see down here, this
is intensity over here, and then we have heart rate,
The increase in heart rate up to around this point here
is primarily due to the withdrawal of the parasympathetic nervous system.
So it's not inhibiting as much.
Again, on average, around 100 beats per minute.
So from rest up to that 100 beats per minute.
Additional increases in heart rate
we actually need to stimulate the AV node.
So we need to increase the signal that's being sent to it.
And so that's happening with sympathetic nervous system outflow.
So that's happening over here.
So these increases on the back end or higher
intensities are primarily due to sympathetic nervous system activity.
And you can always associate that with epinephrine.
So circulating epinephrine as well as those cardiac
accelerator nerves and the sympathetic nervous system attaching to the SA and AV nodes.
Okay, so we kinda touched on this before, but regulation
of heart rate, a change in body temperature can influence heart rate during exercise.
So if we have control here or cool room versus a
heated room, and we have an individual who's exercising, there
is a significant difference or an increase in the heart rate with an elevated temperature.
And the reason why the heart does this is because you do get a drop in blood pressure
because you're getting a little bit of vasodilation to
the periphery because you're trying to send some of that blood to the skin.
The heart or the body compensates by increasing heart rate to maintain perfusion pressure.
Okay, let me ask you this question really quick.
We won't take too long here, but having a really
high heart rate during exercise means you are more fit.
Okay, double check you have something in.
Close this down in 10 seconds or so.
Okay, five seconds.
Three, two, one.
All right.
Okay, yeah, most of you are saying false.
That is correct.
We cannot just base your heart rate or your maximal heart rate and link that to fitness.
So if we think about the why does heart rate even
increase, well we're trying to send more blood to the tissues,
or we just talked about maybe we're trying to send more blood to different areas to dissipate heat.
But if we're primarily sending most of that blood to the muscles,
It's just a product of how can I get a certain flow of blood to the muscles.
We can do that in a variety of different ways, and that changes depending on the individual.
Some individuals are larger than others.
Some individuals have larger hearts than others.
Some individuals have more or less blood.
So here's the comparison of heart rate, stroke volume, and
cardiac output between men and women at the same absolute and relative power output.
So over here, we're at the same absolute power.
So at 50 watts here, if we're looking at heart rate and stroke volume over here.
So heart rate.
Men typically have a lower heart rate compared to women at the exact same absolute power,
but if they're both at 60% of their VO2 max, so
relative intensity, they will have the exact same heart rate.
It's possible most of the time at the same relative
intensity, though, if we're looking at a bike, men typically are just at a higher power output.
And a lot of this can be kind of overall.
We can see that from this cardiac output over here
because they do have a higher cardiac output because they have a higher stroke volume.
So they're just sending more blood overall to the muscles because they're doing a higher power.
And when you have a higher power, you need more oxygen to create energy to do the work.
Any questions here?
OK.
Next topic will be heart rate variability.
You've probably seen this quite often by now.
A lot of these personal devices have heart rate variability,
whether it's your watch or maybe your phone.
They usually have this measure.
but today we're gonna learn about what it actually is.
So this is the variation in time between each heartbeat.
So every time you have a contraction, kind of this
QRST complex here, we're looking at the time between each one of these.
If we're looking at the QRST complex, it's measuring from the R to the R.
And we need EKG or ECG tracing in order to do this.
Okay, so if we have wide variation between resting
heart rate variability, this is a good indication that this
individual is probably a little bit more healthy compared to an individual who has low variation.
So when we say wide variation, we're saying the time between
each R to R complex on the EKG is variable.
So maybe the first one's .93 seconds before the next
heartbeat, and then .98 before the next heartbeat, and then 1.2 before the next one, and then 1.3.
This wide variation, again, is a good sign
of a maybe healthy or healthier individual.
Low variation means that you have the same time between each beat.
This should make a little bit of sense because the only
way I can have low variation or very similar time frame between each beat
is if I'm having more influence from the sympathetic nervous system.
Because the sympathetic nervous system is driving that heart rate.
That is not necessarily a good thing.
We don't want our sympathetic nervous system driving our heart rate at rest.
We want the parasympathetic nervous system driving that.
And when the parasympathetic nervous system is really driving
the resting heart rate, there's more variability.
Because there's no direct signal to say, beat, right?
Have a contraction.
And if you think about it, individuals who are a little bit more stressed,
Maybe their epinephrine's a little bit high, right?
Those are influences where you're increasing the activity of the sympathetic nervous system.
And that's generally a sign, or maybe a risk factor for mortality.
So there are diseases that promote a decrease in heart rate variability.
So again, that's not a great thing.
So depression, hypertension, heart disease, physical inactivity.
There are a lot of,
I guess investigations or research projects or groups that are
looking at how we can use heart rate variability with specific training programs.
So sometimes an individual or a company would say, okay, if you have a wide variation,
maybe you are a little bit more rested compared to
if you're just having sympathetic input into the heart.
Now, there are a lot of different factors that are influencing that.
And so this still isn't a really great indicator of how well rested someone might be.
OK.
So that's regulation of heart rate.
Let's move to the regulation of stroke volume.
Three major factors that we're gonna talk about that regulate stroke volume.
We're gonna start with end diastolic volume.
That's number one.
As a reminder, end diastolic volume is the volume in the ventricles at the end of diastole.
This is sometimes referred to as preload.
So how much blood is in the ventricle before you undergo a contraction?
This is another figure depicting the same thing.
So there's less preload here because there's less blood in the ventricles.
There's more preload here because there's more blood in the ventricles.
If I have more blood in the ventricles and I have
a contraction, well that means more blood is going to leave the heart.
So that in itself is going to regulate stroke volume.
Okay, now let's bring back, so if we're talking about
end diastolic volume, we have to bring back the pressure volume loop.
Here's the pressure volume loop.
Keep in mind that an increase in end diastolic volume will increase stroke volume.
Again, the y-axis here is pressure, x-axis is volume.
The way you wanna start with these graphs would be look at the control.
So this is the dotted black line here.
So we're starting here.
If I increase preload or end diastolic volume, which direction am I going on this graph?
Yeah, to the right because we're increasing the volume inside of the ventricles.
So we actually push the right side of the curve to the right.
Then you undergo the same increase in pressure, volume
leaves the ventricles, and then the end kind of systolic volume
doesn't change, and it fills back up to the original amount.
This delta here shows us there's an increase in stroke volume.
You could go the other way.
So if this is control, this is normal.
If I have a decrease in end diastolic volume, then I go to the left here.
So maybe I'm going from 125 to 100.
Well, now this delta here is much lower than control.
Notice that the pressure changes are about the same.
The only thing that is changing is the end diastolic
volume because that's what we are talking about right now, end diastolic volume.
Okay, so then sometimes we're thinking about, well, how do
I get more blood into the ventricles or less blood into the ventricles?
Well, one of the best mechanisms to increase end
diastolic volume is something called the Frank Starling's mechanism.
If I have a contraction, that contraction in itself is gonna
cause blood to move to the rest of the system, but it's also gonna cause more blood to come back.
So a greater end diastolic volume results in a more forceful contraction in itself.
Once you bring more blood back into it, the ventricles
start to stretch into a more optimal overlap and then you
have a stronger contraction on the next round and then more
blood coming into the ventricles and then they stretch even more.
So this is dependent on that venous return.
So if we have this normal resting value, an increase
in venous return is going to increase stroke volume just like what we talked about.
So not necessarily just because the way the ventricles
are positioned that every time you stretch it even more, it's
always going to be in the most kind of optimal overlap.
There are some issues with
We don't have to go down this route, but you sometimes
they do this with like race horses or ponies, but they remove
the sheathing on the outside of the heart so you can have even more expansion.
And that's how they can get some crazy performance out of like ponies and horses.
But then the flip side to that is if you go too much, then you can rupture some of the ventricles.
That becomes a problem.
And that has happened.
So, yeah.
OK, so then if we're on this piece, we can also think
about if all of this is dependent on venous return, what other factors can influence venous return?
Well, end diastolic volume and venous return, we're going
to talk about three major factors that influence venous return.
One would be venal constriction.
We typically don't think about the veins being able to be too malleable
as far as vasodilation or vasoconstriction, but this venoconstriction
does happen in a very small magnitude via the sympathetic nervous system.
And that's really, you're kind of getting some contraction with those smooth muscles in the veins.
If that happens, you can help accelerate or increase the venous return.
Number two, skeletal muscle pump.
So with your veins, they have some pretty nice
little anatomical adaptations where they have one-way valves that prevent the backflow of veins.
So you can think of it as like if you just had a hose full of water and you just squeeze on
that hose, well, blood's gonna, or water's gonna move up,
but if it goes through a one-way valve, it can never come back down.
And so the muscles are almost like squeezing the veins to
get the blood to move back up towards the heart.
So as soon as you squeeze that vein and you let it go, now you have a delta in pressure.
There's high pressure below, low pressure here, and you're always gonna get it to move.
Okay.
Oh, this is another artist rendering, right?
If I squeeze onto here, you're gonna get the blood to
move back towards the heart, but it's not gonna go back downwards because of these one-way valves.
And as soon as this opens back up, well, that
change in pressure is gonna automatically increase the flow back into this area.
because you want to go from a higher pressure to a lower pressure.
So as soon as that muscle relaxes, you can have blood
rush in and then the muscle contracts and you're helping move the blood down or up towards the heart.
Okay, the third factor would be the respiratory pump.
If you have changes in thoracic pressure, that also influences
blood to kind of return towards the heart.
This would be kind of a good, I guess, figure to look at where you have a couple things.
One, you can have compression of these, but
you're actually decreasing over here the intra-thoracic pressure, which
is going to influence blood to try to come back up.
When you exhale, that's going to encourage the blood kind of coming from the top end back down.
Same concept as the skeletal muscle pump, but it's
happening through ventilation and changes in pressure in the thoracic cavity.
So two different mechanisms, but they end in the same
goal, which is returning venous blood back to the heart.
Okay, filling time.
This is another piece that we need to be careful about.
There's only a certain amount of time that you have to
fill the ventricle before it goes ahead and contracts on the
next one and moves the blood out of the ventricle.
So we have to talk about filling time here.
So if we're at rest, a lot of the times moving through these different
Heart rates, we don't get too much of a delta
in this left ventricle and diastolic volume compared to athletes here.
One of the biggest things that we need to be
careful about is thinking about what's causing the decrease in
filling time towards the end of this area for the athletes here.
So we get an increase, an increase, but then we get a dip back down.
This happens in both groups, but it seems like there's a larger magnitude up here.
And this is that concept where the heart is beating too fast,
and it's not allowing for enough fluid or blood to get back into the ventricle.
So before you can have that optimal filling time, the heart contracts.
So that's why we see this dip here in the left ventricle and diastolic volume.
Number two would be body position.
So body position does influence the return or the filling time.
If we're all standing up, gravity is kind of pulling the
blood down into our feet, as opposed to if you were to
lay flat, the blood kind of evenly distributes to the rest of the body.
And so you don't really have to fight bringing this blood back up to the heart.
So this is actually a pretty big issue when there are studies looking at microgravity.
So if you have someone laying down or even in space,
you actually get all the blood to kind of come closer
up towards the top and you increase central venous pressure.
And that's why a lot of times astronauts have a lot
of trouble with too much ocular pressure or just higher blood pressure in general.
So this figure or this concept actually reminds me like, it was a long time ago,
but one of the first studies that I was involved with
was a NACID fundus study where we did head down bed tilt.
So you're simulating microgravity.
And you have the bed tilted down, and you have someone's head over here and their feet up here.
And we left them there for four days straight.
I know it's very uncomfortable, but it simulates microgravity that you would have in space.
And you actually, because of the increase in central
venous blood pressure, your body starts getting rid of blood.
Because it's like, whoa, whoa, whoa, this is way too much.
And you start kind of taking away some of the red
blood cells and decreasing blood volume to deal with that increase in central venous pressure.
OK.
They were compensated quite well monetarily.
Regulation of stroke volume, we just talked about this already.
Average aortic blood pressure.
So this is the pressure that the ventricles must pump against to eject blood.
This is also sometimes called afterload.
This is the mean arterial pressure.
So if we use that same example when you squeeze a vein
and the blood is moving back up to the heart, well as soon as you relax, where does the blood want to go?
It wants to go back down.
So it's pressing on that valve.
So it's the same thing in the heart.
When your ventricle moves blood outside of the heart, well
there's still blood in the aorta trying to get back in.
This kind of back-in pressure, or the mean arterial pressure, the blood pressure in the body,
is what you have to overcome to open that aortic valve to
get the next kind of flow of blood out of the heart.
So that's what this average aortic pressure is.
So this figure here, what it's basically trying to depict is
on the aortic arch or kind of after you move blood
out of the ventricles, you're getting an increase in pressure here.
If you have an increase in this afterload or the pressure
coming back in to the heart, you almost have to overcome that, right?
So then you have to supply more pressure.
Stroke volume is inversely proportional to the afterload.
If there's too much pressure coming back into the heart, you now don't have enough time
or you don't have as large of a stroke volume
because of that extra pressure coming back in because it's encouraging those valves to close.
So a decrease in afterload is going to increase stroke volume.
and vice versa, an increase in afterload is going to decrease stroke volume.
The way to look at this figure would be, so on the Y
axis we have stroke volume, on the X axis we have basically pressure.
If I have an increase in afterload here, I have to
generate more pressure in order to get the same amount of blood flow.
So that means to get more, then you basically have
less stroke volume with an increase in afterlife.
So here's the normal graph you wanna start here.
And if you decrease the pressure coming back into the
heart, then you're gonna get a higher stroke volume.
If I increase the pressure going this way,
then now you're at a lower stroke volume compared to
normal and compared to a decrease in afterload.
If you don't like this figure, that's OK, because
we're primarily working with the pressure volume loop.
So here on the afterload,
If you remember, from end diastolic volume, we are
shifting this side, while for afterload, we're shifting the left side.
So remember, we wanna start with this center dotted curve here.
If I have to overcome some amount of pressure
over here, because there's increasing pressure coming back to the heart,
I would have to go, so I'm on the red curve right now.
There's so much pressure on the valve, I'm
increasing pressure, I'm increasing pressure, I'm increasing
pressure, still increasing pressure, still increasing pressure.
Finally, I've generated enough pressure to open the aortic valve.
Then I move blood out of the heart, but by that
time, the pressure's coming back to close the aortic valve, so we're
not able to move as much blood out of the ventricle.
So the delta here is now much lower.
If I decrease the pressure on the outside of the ventricles coming back in,
Well now I don't have to generate as much pressure to open those valves.
So I'm on the green curve now, so I'm generating pressure, going up the graph here,
generating pressure, generating pressure, and then now the valve's open,
and all of a sudden I'm moving more blood out of
the heart because there's less pressure to close the valves coming back in.
And so now my end systolic volume
is much lower at the same end diastolic volume would
give you a larger stroke volume, this delta here.
Yeah.
That is correct.
You can almost think about it like a, I don't know, a door or something like that.
If someone's on the back of the door,
like preventing you from opening the door, you have to push
or generate a lot of force to open the door.
But eventually, if you start to relax, it's gonna be a
lot easier to close that door so the valves don't stay open as long.
So that's why you only get to move a small amount of blood here.
Whereas if the door was pretty easy to open, maybe you can
open it all the way and then you can get more blood out of the heart before the next relaxation.
Okay, so that's after load.
Number three would be the strength of the ventricular contraction.
We call that inotropy.
So that's this piece here.
This is enhanced by circulating epinephrine and norepinephrine.
Because if you remember, those beta adrenergic receptors
are accepting epinephrine and that's gonna cause the cell to depolarize.
We also get the direct sympathetic stimulation of the
heart and those are via the cardiac accelerator nerves that we saw on this graph here.
So it's this right here.
And then just as a reminder, if I have circulating epinephrine, these receptors are not selective.
They don't care where the epinephrine came from.
If the epinephrine or epinephrine binds to this receptor,
it's going to cause a depolarization in the cell.
So more inotropy would be more epinephrine binding onto
the beta adrenergic receptors, causing a more forceful contraction.
less epineurothrin or less inotropy, well, you're just activating less muscle fibers.
So sometimes you can think of it like if you have a towel
that you put in water or a shirt and the heart kind of twists.
So if you wring the towel just a little bit,
Well, that's only a little bit of water that's gonna come out.
But if you wring the towel a lot more, then more water comes out.
And that's essentially what you're doing here.
If you can activate more muscle fibers and get that
twisting motion of the heart, it's going to help move blood out.
Okay, so the increase in inotropy is going to increase stroke volume.
Let's bring it back to the pressure volume loop here.
So end isolic volume, we moved this way.
Pressure, we're having to generate more pressure on the up, on the Y axis.
End systolic volume here is over here.
So here we have the black curve to start with, or the black dotted curve here to start with.
If I have an increase, or the more forceful contraction,
then you will by default cause more blood to move outside
of the heart, and then you would have an end systolic volume that is lower.
And so now the delta for an increase in inotropy is
going to result in an increase in stroke volume.
A decrease in the inotropy is gonna cause a decrease in the stroke volume.
So the best way to try to, like, if you
saw a pressure-volume loop with those three scenarios, well, if
they're at the same pressure, then we know we're not really dealing with afterload.
And we're dealing with this piece here, inotropy, or the strength of the contraction.
Questions?
Okay, regulation of stroke volume goes back to this piece.
We pretty much talked about all of them,
endostalic volume, increasing contractility or the inotropy, and
then the decrease in arterial pressure or the afterload.
Those all are going to influence stroke volume.
Keep in mind the venous return is really gonna be influencing the end-diastolic volume.
Sympathetic or epinephrine is going to be increasing the
inotropy or the contractility of the heart.
Afterload is really dependent on that mean arterial pressure
or the pressure kind of being exerted back onto the heart.
Okay, so we talked about these three kind of pressure-volume loops separately.
But that doesn't happen, right?
Like we don't just see one thing changing, all three are kind of happening at the same time.
So the regulation of stroke volume during exercise is due
to all three of these factors, but the overall theme is that
we do see an increase in stroke volume from rest to maximal exercise.
We primarily have the increase in diastolic volume, which is that preload,
and we eventually always get that increase in inotropy,
especially when we're kind of beyond that 100 beats per minute, right?
Because underneath 100 beats per minute, that's primarily through parasympathetic withdrawal.
And then once we start getting into higher intensities,
it's primarily due to that sympathetic outflow.
You already know this, but sometimes it's nice to see all of these factors kind of tying in.
When you're looking at this figure, the dotted line is inhibition.
The parasympathetic nerves are inhibiting the cardiac rate or the heart rate.
Sympathetic nerves are increasing heart rate, so that's why you see a solid line here.
Mean arterial pressure is not necessarily inhibiting, but it
is decreasing your stroke volume over here.
And then of course, don't forget about the Frank Sterling law over here as well.
How are we doing?
Is that a lot?
Maybe we can keep going.
No.
All right, that's fine.
Have a good weekend.
Enjoy, enjoy.